<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;0 on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;0 on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Acknowledgements</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/01_Acknowledgements/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/01_Acknowledgements/</guid>
      <description>A work of this type cannot happen without the effort of a group of dedicated persons. My brother Rangarajan, Prof. Naagabhushan, Mr. Gopal who had an intimate and long association with Shastriji have been the prime movers of this programme. All the three have spent many hours with me for realising this project by helping me with the transcription, by putting it into a readable format. They spent hours of their precious time by going through the pages line by line and made the necessary correction keeping in mind, the Shastriji’s style of narration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 Preface to the second edition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/02_Preface_to_the_second_edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/02_Preface_to_the_second_edition/</guid>
      <description>In our enthusiasm to bring out the book as quickly as possible, we hurriedly rushed through the first edition in which some small but relevant aspects were left out. In spite of this deficiency the appreciation of the contents were valuable and prompted us to take a second look at the editing work. The suggestion from the readers who were mostly the Shatriji’s core group came in handy to look at the whole manuscript again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 Editors Note</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/03_Editors_Note/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/03_Editors_Note/</guid>
      <description>My association with this great teacher was for a very short period. I heard him directly six or seven times. But the impact of that listening was so great that it prompted me to listen to many of his taped lectures several times. More than six hundred hours of taped talks covering various aspects have been put into an mp3 format for better storage at the request of Mr. Vinayak Joshi who had recorded them using his little recorder.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 Foreword</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/04_Foreword/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/04_Foreword/</guid>
      <description>I write this foreword with a sense of humility and gratitude to Shastriji, my Guru. He is the inspiration and spirit of this book which contains his message on wisdom from the Upaniṣad-s.
There exists a myriad of commentaries, interpretation and treatises written on Upaniṣad-s. The reader may wonder as to the significance of one more such exposition. The uniqueness of this book lies in the scientific approach to concepts like happiness and sorrow (Sukha &amp;amp; Duḥkha), demystifying the concept of enlightenment and liberation (Mukti) as espoused in Vedanta.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 Why read this book?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/05_Why_read_this_book/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/0/05_Why_read_this_book/</guid>
      <description>In what way this book is special in content and quality is a natural question that arises in the mind of any reader. Hence it is the responsibility of the editor to highlight the salient features of this book.
Shastriji, with a strong scientific temper, began to question the orthodoxy in respect of certain vedāntic truths cherished by traditional scholars. This led him to do intense research in Upaniṣad-s and Yoga- Vāsiṣṭa in order to find practical solutions to the problems encountered by the modern mind.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
