<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;हरिहरैक्यम् on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;हरिहरैक्यम् on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bodhendra hariharAdvaita</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/bodhendra-hariharAdvaita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/bodhendra-hariharAdvaita/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Refutation of Bodhendra Saraswati&amp;rsquo;s objections against Vaishnavism in &amp;ldquo;Hariharadvaita Bhushanam&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter on the refutation of Hari-Hara Aikyatva Vada, we consider the arguments of a relatively recent advaitin who was supposed to be of the “tolerant” kind, known as Sri Bodhendra Saraswati.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bodhendra Saraswati is said to have been an advocate of nAma sankIrtanam, and chanted Rama nama one lakh times every day. He was a contemporary of the illustrious karnATaka-smArta devotee of Shiva known as Sridhara “Ayyaval” who lived in Tiruvisanallur. This advaitic personality who lived during/after Appayya Dikshita’s period, advocated that in the Vedas, both Hari (Vishnu) and Hara (Shiva) are praised as the One Supreme Being.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No hari-haraikya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/no-hari-haraikya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/no-hari-haraikya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;introduction-refutation-of-hari-hara-aikya-vada&#34;&gt;Introduction: Refutation of Hari-Hara Aikya Vada&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Illogical Premise of Hari-Hara Aikya (Shiva=Vishnu) Vada&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is well known that ancient advaitins, including Shri Shankara Bhagavatpada and his immediate disciples, were  Vaishnavas. This will be proven in the following passages. Before that, let us examine the claims of the modern day smArtas. They claim that both vishNu and siva are equal (though most are either shaiva or outright vishNu dvEshIs in their outlook) and they try to discredit vaishNavas by saying the following things:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shiva-lIlAH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/shiva-lIlAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/hari-haraikyam/shiva-lIlAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shiva Leelas&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Sri Krishna says:janma karma ca me divyam evam yo vetti tattvatah tyaktva deham punar janma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The simple meaning of this statement is that those who understand the divine nature of his form and activities attain liberation. Many misunderstand this into thinking this involves just a rudimentary comprehension of his avatArAs. They believe that mere acceptance of krishNa as paramAtma and knowledge of his activities such as stealing butter, dancing with gOpIs, etc is enough. While such knowledge is no doubt very lofty, it is not what bhagavAn means here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
