<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 fourth pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;fourth-pāda&#34;&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(On the soul&amp;rsquo;s) having entered (into the highest light), there is manifestation (of its own nature); (as we infer) from the word &amp;lsquo;own.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Thus does that serene being, having risen out of this body and entered into the highest light, manifest itself by its own nature&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 12, 3). Regarding this text a doubt arises whether the Self &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; manifests itself through some adventitious distinction&amp;ndash;as the Self (of him who possesses the lower knowledge only) does in the world of the gods and other abodes of enjoyment&amp;ndash;or only through its own Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Self whose true nature has manifested itself is) released; according to the promise (made by scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That soul, of which the text says that it manifests itself, is released from its former bondage and abides in its own pure Self; while previously its Self was stained by the three states (i.e. the state of waking, dreaming, and dreamless sleep), according to Cḥ. Up. VIII, 9-11, &amp;lsquo;It is blind;&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;it weeps as it were;&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;it goes to utter annihilation.&amp;rsquo; This is the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The light into which the soul enters is) the Self; owing to the subject-matter of the chapter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how can the soul be called &amp;lsquo;released,&amp;rsquo; considering that the clause &amp;lsquo;having entered into the highest light&amp;rsquo; speaks of it as within the sphere of what is a mere effect? For the word &amp;rsquo;light,&amp;rsquo; according to general usage, denotes physical light. And none who has not passed beyond the sphere of what is effected can be released, it being known that whatever is an effect is tainted with evil.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The released soul abides) in non-division (from the highest Self); because that is seen from scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt here arises whether that soul of which the text says, &amp;lsquo;Having entered the highest light it manifests itself by its true nature,&amp;rsquo; remains separate from the highest Self, or abides in the state of non-division from it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Somebody might be inclined to think that&amp;ndash;because in the passage, &amp;lsquo;He moves about there,&amp;rsquo; a distinction is made between the abode and him who abides; and because the clause, &amp;lsquo;Having entered the highest light,&amp;rsquo; mentions an agent and an object (of the agent&amp;rsquo;s activity)&amp;ndash;the soul remains distinct from the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;By (a nature) like that of Brahman (the soul manifests itself); (thus) Jaimini (opines); on account of reference and the rest.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been concluded that the clause, &amp;lsquo;by its own nature,&amp;rsquo; means that the soul manifests itself by its own Self only, not by some other adventitious character. What has now to be inquired into is the specific qualities of that nature. Here the Sūtra at first states the opinion of the teacher Jaimini. According to him the soul&amp;rsquo;s own nature is &amp;rsquo;like that of Brahman,&amp;rsquo; i.e. it comprises all the qualities beginning with freeness from sin and concluding with truthfulness of conception (i.e. the qualities enumerated in Cḥ. Up. VIII, 7, 1), and also omniscience and omnipotence; and in this nature the soul manifests itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;By the sole nature of intelligence (the soul manifests itself), as that is its Self; thus Auḍulomi (opines).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although the text enumerates different qualities, such as freeness from sin, &amp;amp;c., these qualities rest only on fanciful conceptions due to difference of words; for what the text intimates is only absence in general of all qualities such as sin and the rest. Intelligence alone constitutes the nature of the Self, and hence it is proper to conclude that it manifests itself in a nature consisting of that only. This conclusion will also agree with other scriptural texts, such as Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 13. &amp;lsquo;Thus this Self has neither inside nor outside, but is altogether a mass of knowledge.&amp;rsquo; Qualities, on the other hand, such as having true wishes, are indeed mentioned by the text as real (positive) attributes, the meaning being that his wishes are true, i.e. truly existent; but all the same they, as depending on the connexion with limiting adjuncts, cannot constitute the true nature of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thus also, on account of the existence of the former (qualities), (admitted) owing to reference and so on, there is absence of contradiction, (as) Bādarāyaṇa (thinks).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thus also, i.e. although it be admitted that intelligence only constitutes the true nature of the Self, also the former nature, i.e. lordly power like that of Brahman, which is intimated by reference and the rest, is&amp;ndash;with a view to the world of appearances&amp;ndash;not rejected; and hence there is no contradiction. This is the opinion of the teacher Bādarāyaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And for this very same reason (the released soul is) without another lord.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For this very same reason, i.e. owing to the fact of the will of the released person not being barren, he who knows has no other lord over himself. For not even an ordinary person when forming wishes will, if he can help it, wish himself to be subject to another master. And scripture also declares this when saying, &amp;lsquo;Those who depart from hence, after having discovered the Self and those true desires, for them there is freedom in all worlds&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 1, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The absence (of a body and sense-organs, on the part of the released) Bādari (asserts); for thus scripture says.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage, &amp;lsquo;By his mere wish the fathers rise,&amp;rsquo; shows that the released possesses a mind (internal organ, manas) whereby he wills. A question however arises whether he&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;who knows, after having reached lordly power, possesses a body and senses, or not. Here the teacher Bādari is of opinion that the glorified possessor of knowledge is without body and sense-organs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The presence (of a body and senses) Jaimini (asserts); because the text records option (of the released person multiplying himself).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The teacher Jaimini is of opinion that the released person possesses a body and sense-organs as well as a mind. For passages like &amp;lsquo;He is onefold, he is threefold&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 26, 2) declare that the Self has the option of manifold existence which cannot be brought about without manifoldness of body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For this reason Bādarāyaṇa (opines that the released person is) of both kinds; as in the case of the twelve days&amp;rsquo; sacrifice.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The teacher Bādarāyaṇa, again, thinks that for this reason, i.e. because scripture contains indications of both kinds, the proper conclusion is that the released person exists in both&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;conditions. When he wishes to have a body, he appears with one; when he wishes to be disembodied, he is without one. For he has various wishes, and all his wishes are realised.&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;As in the case of the twelve days&amp;rsquo; sacrifice.&amp;rsquo; As the soma sacrifice extending over twelve days may be viewed either as a sattra or as an ahīna sacrifice, because both alternatives are indicated by scriptural passages [^sbe38331.htmfn_234]; so it is here also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When there is no body, (the process) may take place as in the dreaming state.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When there is no body and no sense-organs, the process in the state of release may be viewed as analogous to that in the state of dream, when objects wished, such as a father and so on, have a perceptional existence only while body, senses, and objects do not really exist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When there is (a body), (it may be) as in the waking state.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When, on the other hand, the released person has a body, then the objects of his wishes&amp;ndash;fathers and so on&amp;ndash;may have real existence, as in the waking state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The entering (of one soul into several bodies) is like (the multiplication of) the flame of a lamp; for thus scripture declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Under Sūtra 11 it has been shown that the released person is embodied. The question now arises whether the bodies which the released create for themselves when rendering themselves threefold and so on are soulless like wooden figures, or animated by souls like the bodies of us men.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(What scripture says about absence of all specific cognition) refers either to deep sleep or union (release); for this is manifested (by the texts).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By &amp;rsquo;entering into one&amp;rsquo;s own Self&amp;rsquo; is meant dreamless&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;sleep; according to the text, &amp;lsquo;He is gone to his own Self, he sleeps they say&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 1). &amp;lsquo;Union&amp;rsquo; means blissful isolation (final release), according to the text, &amp;lsquo;Being Brahman he goes to Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 6). What the texts say about absence of specific cognition is said with reference to either of those two states, dreamless sleep or final release.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;With the exception of world-business (the released possess all lordly power), (the Lord) being the topic (where world-business is referred to), and (the souls) not being near (to such business).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following doubt here presents itself. Do those who through meditations on the qualified Brahman enter, together with their manas, into a condition of equality with the Lord, possess unlimited lordly power, or power limited to some extent?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that their power must be unlimited, because we meet with texts such as &amp;lsquo;He obtains Self-lordship&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Saṁh. I, 6, 2); &amp;lsquo;All the gods bring an offering for him&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Saṁh. I, 5, 3); &amp;lsquo;For them there is freedom in all worlds&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 1, 6)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Should it be said that the souls must possess unlimited power) on account of manifest teaching; we reply No, because scripture states him who, entrusted with office, abides in the spheres (of the sun and so on), (to be that one on whom the soul&amp;rsquo;s obtaining lordly power depends).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It remains to refute the remark, made by the pūrvapakshin, that absolute power on the part of those who know must be inferred from texts directly asserting such power, as e.g. &amp;lsquo;He obtains self-lordship.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (there is also a form of the highest Lord) not abiding in effected things; for thus scripture declares his abiding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, according to scripture, there is also an eternal form of the highest Lord which does not abide in effects; he is not only the ruling soul of the spheres of the sun and so on which lie within the sphere of what is effected. For the text declares his abiding in a twofold form, as follows: &amp;lsquo;Such is the greatness of it; greater than it is the Person. One foot of him are all beings; three feet of him is what is immortal in heaven&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 12, 6). And it cannot be maintained that that form of him which is divorced from all effects is reached by those who put their trust on his other form; for their minds are not set on the former. Hence as he who does not reach that form of the double-natured highest Lord which is divorced from all qualities stops at that form which is distinguished by qualities, so also, unable to reach unlimited power within the latter form, he stops at limited lordly power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And thus perception and inference show.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture and Smr̥ti both declare that the highest light does not abide within effected things, &amp;lsquo;The sun does not shine there, nor the moon and the stars, nor these lightnings, and much less this fire&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 2, 10). &amp;lsquo;The sun does not illume it, nor the moon, nor fire&amp;rsquo; (Bha. Gītā XV, 6).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtra is meant to show that the non-abiding of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the indications of equality of enjoyment only.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lordly power of those who take their stand on the effected Brahman is not absolute, for that reason also that scripture teaches that their enjoyment only is equal to that of the eternally perfect Lord. For scripture contains statements and indications of the difference (of the Lord and the released soul); compare &amp;lsquo;To him he says, Water indeed is enjoyed [^sbe38338.htmfn_237] (by me); that world (is to be enjoyed by thee also)&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. I, 7); &amp;lsquo;As all beings honour that deity, so do all beings honour him who knows that&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 5, 20); &amp;lsquo;He obtains through it equality (in body) and sameness of abode with that deity&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 5, 23). But from the circumstance of the lordly power of the released souls not being absolute it follows that it comes to an end, and then they will have to return from the world of Brahman!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/4/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Of them) there is non-return, according to scripture; non-return, according to scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those who, in following the road of the gods, to which the vein and the ray are leading, and on which light is the first stage, reach the world of Brahman as described by scripture&amp;ndash;where &amp;rsquo;there are the two lakes Ara and Ṇya in the world of Brahman, in the third heaven from hence,&amp;rsquo; and where &amp;rsquo;there is the lake Airammadīya and the Aśvattha tree showering down Soma. and the city of Brahman Aparājitā and the golden hall built by Prabhu&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 5, 3)&amp;ndash;and set forth at length in mantras,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
