<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But there is (a scriptural statement of the origination of ether).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conjunction &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; indicates the adoption of another alternative.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The origin of ether may not be stated in the Cḥāndogya; but it iś stated in other scriptural passages. For the text of the Taittirīyakas, after having introduced Brahman as the general subject-matter,&amp;ndash;in the words, &amp;lsquo;The true, knowledge, without end is Brahman,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;goes on to say, &amp;lsquo;From that Self sprang ether&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 1).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Vedic statement concerning the origination of ether) has a secondary sense, on account of the impossibility (of the origination of ether).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The ether does not originate on account of the absence of scriptural statement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That other passage which (apparently) declares the origination of the ether must be taken as having a secondary (figurative) meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why? On account of the impossibility. The origination of ether cannot be shown to be possible as long as there exist followers of the opinion of the reverend Kaṇabhuj (Kaṇāda). For the latter deny the origination of ether on the ground that it is impossible to demonstrate the existence of the required apparatus of causes. Whatever is originated, they say, is originated from inherent causes, non-inherent causes, and operative causes. Of a substance the inherent causes are substances belonging to the same class and more than one in number. But for ether there are no such originating substances, belonging to the same&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the word (of the Veda).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word of the Veda also proclaims the non-originatedness of ether; for it declares that &amp;lsquo;air and ether (antariksha) are immortal&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 3, 3), and what is immortal cannot have an origin. Another scriptural passage (&amp;lsquo;omnipresent and eternal like ether&amp;rsquo;), by comparing two attributes of Brahman, viz. omnipresence and eternity with the other, intimates that those qualities belong to the ether&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The one (word &amp;lsquo;sprang&amp;rsquo;) may be (taken in its secondary as well as in its primary sense), like the word &amp;lsquo;Brahman.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Sūtra contains the reply to a doubt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If we admit the opinion maintained hitherto, how can one and the same word &amp;lsquo;sprang&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;from that Self sprang the ether&amp;rsquo;) be used, in the same chapter, in its primary (real) meaning with regard to fire and so on, and in a secondary meaning with regard to ether?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The non-abandonment of the promissory statements (results only) from the non-difference (of the entire world from Brahman), according to the words of the Veda.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In all the Vedānta-texts we meet with promissory statements of the following nature:&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;That by which we hear what is not heard, perceive what is not perceived, know what is not known&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 1, 3); &amp;lsquo;When the Self has been seen, heard, perceived, and known, then all this is known&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 6); &amp;lsquo;Sir, what is that through which if it is known everything else becomes known?&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 3); &amp;lsquo;Outside that which is there is no knowledge.&amp;rsquo; These promissory statements are not abandoned, i.e. not stultified, only if the entire aggregate of things is non-different from Brahman, the object of knowledge; for if there were any difference, the affirmation that by the knowledge of one thing everything is known, would be contradicted thereby. Non-difference again of the two is possible only if the whole aggregate of things originates from the one Brahman. And we understand from the words of the Veda that that affirmation can be established only through the theory of the non-difference of the material cause and its effects. For the affirmation contained in the clause &amp;lsquo;That by which we hear what is not heard,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., is proved by the analogous instances of clay, &amp;amp;c., which all aim at showing the identity of effect and cause. In order to establish this, the subsequent clauses also (&amp;lsquo;Being only, my dear, this was in the beginning, one only, without a second; it thought; it sent forth fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.) at first state that the aggregate of effects belongs to Brahman, and then declare its identity with Brahman, viz. from the passage &amp;lsquo;In it all that exists has its Self&amp;rsquo; (VI, 8, 7), up to the end of the prapāṭḥaka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But wherever there are effects, there is division; as in ordinary life.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conjunction &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; is meant to exclude the suspicion of impossibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We must not imagine the origin of ether to be impossible, because wherever we observe effects (modifications of a substance), such as jars, pots and urns, or bracelets, armlets and earrings, or needles, arrows and swords, we also observe division; while, on the other hand,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;nothing which is not an effect is seen to be divided &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Now, we apprehend ether as divided from earth and so on; hence ether also must be an effect. Thereby (i.e. by the circumstance of their being divided) place (diś), time, mind (manas) and the atoms also are shown to be effects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hereby air (also) is explained.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The present Sūtra extends the reasoning concerning ether to the air of which the ether is the abode. The different views about air also are to be arranged in an analogous manner. The pūrvapakshin maintains that the air is not a product, because it is not mentioned in that chapter of the Cḥāndogya which treats of the origination of things. The opposite opinion is, that the air is mentioned in the parallel chapter of the Taittirīyaka (&amp;lsquo;from the ether sprang the air&amp;rsquo;). The two scriptural passages being of a conflicting nature, the pūrvapakshin maintains that the passage which declares the air to have originated must be taken in a secondary sense; firstly on account of the impossibility (of the literal sense being adopted), as shown (in the adhikaraṇa treating of the ether); secondly on account of that passage which denies that it ever sets, &amp;lsquo;Vāyu (the air) is the deity that never sets&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 5, 22); and thirdly on account of those passages which declare it to be immortal. The final opinion on the other hand is, that air is a product; in the first place because this conclusion is conformable to the general tendency of scripture; and, in the second place, because it is generally admitted that whatever&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But there is no origin of that which is (i.e. of Brahman), on account of the impossibility (of such an origin).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Somebody, who has learned from scripture that ether and air, although not in themselves likely to have originated, yet actually are things with a beginning, might feel inclined to suspect that Brahman itself has sprung from something else. And further somebody, who has learned from scripture that from ether and the other elements which are themselves mere effects further effects are produced, might think that also Brahman, from which ether has sprung, is a mere effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fire (is produced) thence (i.e. from air); for thus (the text) declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Cḥāndogya it is said that fire has for its source that which is (Brahman), in the Taittirīyaka that it has the air for its source. There being thus a conflict of scriptural passages with regard to the origin of fire, the pūrvapakshin maintains that fire has Brahman for its source.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the text, after having stated at the outset that there existed only that which is, teaches that it sent forth fire; and because the assertion of everything being known through Brahman is possible only in case of everything;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Water (is produced from fire).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have to supply from the preceding Sūtra the words &amp;rsquo;thence&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;for thus the text declares.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Water is produced from fire; for the text says, &amp;lsquo;it sent forth water&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 3), and &amp;lsquo;from fire (sprang) water&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 1). These explicit statements allow no room for doubt &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Sūtrakāra, however, having explained the creation of fire, and being about to explain the creation of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The earth (is meant by the word &amp;lsquo;anna&amp;rsquo;), on account of the subject-matter, the colour, and other passages.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read, &amp;lsquo;Water thought, may I be many, may I grow forth. It sent forth food (anna)&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 4).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here a doubt arises, whether the word &amp;lsquo;anna&amp;rsquo; denotes things fit to be used as food, such as rice, barley and the like; or cooked food; or else the earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of the indicatory mark supplied by their reflecting (i.e. by the reflection attributed to the elements), he (i.e. the Lord is the creative principle abiding within the elements).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt here arises whether ether and the other elements do themselves send forth their effects, or if the highest Lord abiding within certain Selfs produces, after reflection, certain effects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the pūrvapakshin maintains that the elements themselves send forth, because the texts speak of them as acting independently; compare, for instance, &amp;lsquo;from ether sprang air, from air fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. The objection that non-intelligent beings cannot enter on independent activity is invalidated by the fact that the elements also are spoken of in the sacred texts as endowed with intelligence, cf. for instance, &amp;lsquo;fire thought,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;water thought&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 3; 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The order (in which the elements are retracted into Brahman) is the reverse of that (i.e. the order in which they are created); this is proved (by its agreement with observation).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having considered the order of the creation of the elements we now proceed to consider the order of their retractation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question here is whether their retractation takes place in an indefinite order, or in the order of the creation, or in the inverse order. That the origin, the subsistence and the retractation of the elements all depend on Brahman, scripture declares &amp;lsquo;That from whence these beings are born, that by which when born they live, that into which they enter at their death.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that between (Brahman and the elements) the intellect and mind (are mentioned; and that therefore their origination and retractation are to be placed) somewhere in the series, on account of there being inferential signs (whereby the order of the creation of the elements is broken); we&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;deny that, on account of the non-difference (of the organs and the elements).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In what precedes we have said that the creation and the retractation of the elements take place in direct and reverse order; further that the creation proceeds from the Self, and that the retractation terminates in the Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the designation (as being born and dying) abides in the (bodies of beings) moving and non-moving; it is secondary (metaphorical) if applied to the soul, as the existence (of those terms) depends on the existence of that (i.e. the body).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of certain popular modes of expression such as &amp;lsquo;Devadatta is born,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Devadatta has died,&amp;rsquo; and the like, and on account of certain ceremonies such as the Jātakakarman some people might fall into the error of thinking that the individual soul has a beginning, and in the end undergoes destruction. This error we are going to dispel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The (living) Self is not (produced) as there is no scriptural statement, and as it is eternal according to them (i.e. scriptural passages).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is a Self called the living one (the individual soul), which rules the body and the senses, and is connected with the fruits of actions. With regard to that Self the conflict of scriptural passages suggests the doubt, whether it is produced from Brahman like ether and the other elements, or if, like Brahman itself, it is unproduced. Some scriptural passages, by comparing it to sparks proceeding from a fire and so on, intimate that the living soul is produced&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For this very reason (the individual soul is) intelligent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Owing to the conflicting views of the philosophical schools there arises a doubt whether, as the followers of Kaṇāda think, the soul is in itself non-intelligent, so that its intelligence is merely adventitious; or if. as the Sāṅkhyas think, eternal intelligence constitutes its very nature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that the intelligence of the Self is adventitious, and is produced by the conjunction of the Self with the mind (manas), just as, for instance, the quality of redness is produced in a jar by the conjunction of the jar with fire. For if the soul were of eternal (essential) intelligence, it would remain intelligent in the states of deep sleep, swoon, and possession, while as a matter of fact, men when waking from sleep and so on declare in reply to questions addressed to them that they were not conscious of anything. Men in their ordinary state, on the other hand, are seen to be (actively) intelligent. Hence, as intelligence&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(On account of the scriptural declarations) of (the soul&amp;rsquo;s) passing out, going and returning, (the soul is of atomic size).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now have to consider of what size the soul is, whether of atomic size or of a medium size, or of great (infinite) size.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, it has been shown above that the soul is not a product and that eternal intelligence constitutes its nature, whence it follows that it is identical with the highest Self. Now the infinity of the highest Self is clearly stated in scripture; what need then is there of a discussion of the soul&amp;rsquo;s size?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the two latter (i.e. going and returning) being connected with their Self (i.e. the agent), (the soul is of atomic size).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We admit that &amp;lsquo;passing out&amp;rsquo; might possibly be attributed to the soul even if it does not move, viz. if that expression be taken to mean the soul&amp;rsquo;s ceasing to be the ruler of the body, in consequence of the results of its former actions having become exhausted; just as somebody when ceasing to be the ruler of a village may be said to &amp;lsquo;go out.&amp;rsquo; But the two latter activities, viz. going and returning, are not possible in the ease of something which does not move; for they are both connected with the own Self (of the agent), going (and coming back) being activities abiding in the agent &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Now going and coming are possible for a being that is not of medium size, only if it is of atomic size. And as going and coming must be taken in their literal sense, we conclude that the passing out also means nothing but the soul&amp;rsquo;s actual moving out of the body. For the soul cannot go and return without first having moved out of the body. Moreover certain parts of the body are mentioned as the points from which the soul starts in passing out, viz. in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;Either from the eye or from the skull or from other places of the body (the Self passes out)&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 2). Other passages mention that the embodied soul goes and comes within the body also; so, for instance, &amp;lsquo;He taking with him those elements of light descends into the heart&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 1); &amp;lsquo;Having assumed light he again goes to his place&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 11).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (the soul is) not atomic, on account of scriptural statements about what is not that (i.e. what is opposed to atomic size); we deny&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;that, on account of the other one (the highest Self) being the subject-matter (of those passages).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it may be objected, the soul cannot be of atomic size, because there are scriptural statements of what is not that, i.e. because there are scriptural statements of its size being the opposite of atomic size. So that by accepting the alternative of atomic size we should place ourselves in opposition to scriptural passages such as the following, &amp;lsquo;He is that great unborn Self who consists of knowledge, is surrounded by the Prāṇas, the ether within the heart&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22); &amp;lsquo;Like the ether he is omnipresent, eternal;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Truth, knowledge, infinite is Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II. i).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And also on account of direct statement, and of inference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The soul is of atomic size for that reason also that scripture contains a direct statement to that effect, &amp;lsquo;By&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;thought is to be known that atomic Self into which breath has entered fivefold&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, 1, 9). That the Self spoken of there as atomic is the living Self, i.e. the individual soul, we see from its connexion with breath.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is no contradiction, as in the case of sandal-ointment.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just as a drop of sandal-ointment, although in actual contact with one spot of the body only, yet produces a refreshing sensation extending over the whole body; so the soul, although abiding in one point of the body only, may be the cause of a perception extending over the entire body. And as the soul is connected with the skin (which is the seat of feeling), the assumption that the soul&amp;rsquo;s sensations should extend over the whole body is by no means contrary to reason. For the connexion of the soul and the skin abides in the entire skin, and the skin extends over the whole body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that the two cases are not parallel), on account of the specialisation of abode (present in the case of the sandal-ointment, absent in the case of the soul); we deny that, on account of the acknowledgment (by scripture, of a special place of the soul), viz. within the heart.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here it may be objected that the argumentation relied upon in the last Sūtra is not admissible, because the two cases compared are not parallel. If it were a settled matter that the soul dwells in one point of the body, the drop of sandal-ointment might be adduced as a parallel instance. But, as a matter of fact, we know from perception that the drop of sandal-ointment is in contact with one spot of the body only, just as we know that it refreshes the whole body; while in the case of the soul observation tells us only that it is percipient all over the body, but not that it abides in one spot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or on account of (its) quality (viz. intelligence), as in cases of ordinary experience.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the soul although atomic produces effects extending over the whole body, is not contrary to reason, on account of the pervadingness of intellect which is its quality. From ordinary experience we know that luminous things, such as lamps or gems, although occupying only one spot of a chamber, produce, by means of their light which fills the chamber, an effect in every part of the chamber.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The extending beyond is as in the case of odour.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just as odour, although a quality, extends beyond the odorous substance&amp;ndash;as appears from the fact of our perceiving odour even without actually grasping flowers which are the seat of odour&amp;ndash;so the quality of intelligence also may extend beyond the soul although the latter be atomic. It therefore is an undue stretch of inference to maintain that a quality, such as colour and the like, cannot separate itself from the substratum in which it inheres, because it is a quality; for we see that odour although a mere quality does separate itself from its substratum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And thus (scripture also) declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture also, after having signified the soul&amp;rsquo;s abiding in the heart and its atomic size, declares by means of such&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;passages as &amp;lsquo;Up to the hairs, up to the tips of the nails&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. IV, 20; Br̥. Up. I. 4, 7), that the soul pervades the entire body by means of intelligence which is its quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the separate statement (of soul and intelligence).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the passage &amp;lsquo;Having by knowledge taken possession of the body&amp;rsquo; which represents the soul and intelligence as separate, viz. as respectively the agent and the instrument of action, we understand that the soul pervades the body only by means of intelligence, its quality. Again the passage &amp;lsquo;Then (the intelligent person) having through the intelligence of the senses absorbed within himself all intelligence&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 1, 17) shows intelligence to be different from the agent, i.e. the embodied soul, and so likewise confirms our view.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But it is designated thus (i.e. as atomic), on account of its having for its essence the qualities of that (i.e. the buddhi); as in the case of the intelligent Self (i.e. Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; is meant to set aside the opinion maintained hitherto.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The soul is not of atomic size, since scripture does not declare it to have had an origin. On the contrary, as scripture speaks of the highest Brahman entering into the elements and teaches that it is their Self, the soul is nothing else but the highest Brahman. And if the soul is the highest Brahman, it must be of the same extent as Brahman. Now scripture states Brahman to be all-pervading. Therefore the soul also is all-pervading.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 third pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ether &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (does) not (originate), on account of the absence of scriptural statement.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Vedānta-texts we meet in different places with different statements concerning the origination of various things. Some of those passages declare that ether originated; some do not. Some record the origination of air; others do not. Other passages again make analogous statements concerning the individual soul and the vital airs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The objection (raised above) is not valid, since (the connexion of the soul with the buddhi) exists as long as the soul; it being thus observed (in scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We need not fear that the objection formulated above can be proved.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;On account of the existence of the connexion of the soul with the buddhi, as long as the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;soul exists.&amp;rsquo; That means: as long as this Self is in the saṁsāra-state, as long as the saṁsāra-state is not brought to an end by means of perfect knowledge, so long the connexion of the soul with the buddhi does not cease. And as long as its connexion with the buddhi, its limiting adjunct, lasts, so long the individual soul remains individual soul, implicated in transmigratory existence. In reality, however, there is no individual soul but in so far as it is fictitiously hypostatized by the buddhi, its limiting adjunct. For in attempting to determine the object of the Vedānta-texts we meet with no other intelligent substance but the one omniscient Lord whose nature is eternal freedom. This appears from innumerable texts, such as the following:&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;There is no other seer but he, there is no other hearer but he, there is no other perceiver but he, there is no other knower but he&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 23); &amp;lsquo;There is nothing that sees, hears, perceives, knows but it&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 11); &amp;lsquo;Thou art that&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 7); &amp;lsquo;I am Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 4, 10).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the appropriateness of the manifestation of that (connexion) which exists (potentially); like virile power.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As in ordinary life virile power and so on, existing potentially only in young children, and being then looked upon as non-existing, become manifest at the time of puberty&amp;ndash;and do not originate at that time from previous non-existence, because in that case they might originate in eunuchs also&amp;ndash;; so the connexion of the soul with the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Otherwise (if no manas existed) there would result either constant perception or constant non-perception, or else a limitation of either of the two (i.e. of the soul or of the senses).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The internal organ which constitutes the limiting adjunct of the soul is called in different places by different names, such as manas (mind), buddhi (intelligence), vijñāna (knowledge), citta (thought). This difference of nomenclature is sometimes made dependent on the difference of the modifications of the internal organ which is called manas when it is in the state of doubt, &amp;amp;c., buddhi when it is in the state of determination and the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The soul is) an agent, on account of scripture having a purport (thereby).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In connexion with the doctrine that the soul possesses for its essence the qualities of the buddhi, another attribute of the soul is set forth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The individual soul is an agent, because thus scripture has a purport. For only on that assumption scriptural injunctions (such as &amp;lsquo;He is to sacrifice,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;He is to make an oblation into the fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;He is to give,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.) acquire a purport; otherwise they would be purportless. For they all teach special acts to be done by agents; which would not be possible if the soul did not possess the quality of being an agent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (the text) teaching its wandering about.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The quality of being an agent has to be attributed to the soul for that reason also, that, in a chapter treating of the soul, the text declares it to wander about in the state of sleep, &amp;lsquo;The immortal one goes wherever he likes&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 12);&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and again, &amp;lsquo;He moves about, according to his pleasure, within his own body&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 1, 18).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of its taking.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The quality of being an agent has to be attributed to the soul for that reason also that in the same chapter treating of the soul the text speaks of the soul taking its instruments, &amp;lsquo;Having taken, through the intelligence of the senses, intelligence,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;having taken the senses&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II. 1, 18; 17).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The soul is an agent) also because it is designated as such with regard to actions; if it were not such, there would be a change of designation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The quality of being an agent belongs to the soul for that reason also that the sacred texts speak of its agency in sacred and secular actions. &amp;lsquo;Understanding performs the sacrifice, it performs all acts&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 5).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection may here be raised, we have seen that the word &amp;lsquo;understanding&amp;rsquo; applies to the buddhi; how then can it indicate the circumstance of the soul being an agent?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The absence of restriction is as in the case of perception.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just as this Self, although free with regard to perception, yet perceives unrestrictedly what is unpleasant as well as what is pleasant, so we assume that it also brings about what is unpleasant as well as what is pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The objection that in the act of perception also the soul is not free because it depends on the employment of the causes of perception (i.e. the sense-organs), we invalidate by the remark that the use of the causes of perception is merely to present the objects of perception, that however in the act of perception the soul because endowed with intelligence does not depend on anything else &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the reversal of power.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The soul distinct from &amp;lsquo;understanding&amp;rsquo; has to be viewed as an agent for the following reason also. If the buddhi which is denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;understanding&amp;rsquo; were the agent, there would take place a reversal of power, i.e. the instrumental power which appertains to the buddhi would have to be set aside, and to be replaced by the power of an agent. But if the buddhi has the power of an agent, it must be admitted that it is also the object of self-consciousness&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the impossibility of meditation (samādhi).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover the meditation taught in the Vedānta-texts, whose aim is the realisation of the Self as represented by the Upanishads, is possible only if the Self is the agent &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Compare the following passages, &amp;lsquo;Verily, the Self is to be seen, to be heard, to be perceived, to be marked&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 4, 5); &amp;lsquo;The Self we must seek out, we must try to understand&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 7, 1); &amp;lsquo;Meditate on the Self as Om&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 2, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And as the carpenter, in double fashion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the embodied Self is an agent, has been proved by the reasons set forth in Sūtra 33, &amp;amp;c. We now have to consider whether this agency depends on the fundamental nature of the Self, or is due to its limiting adjuncts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If here it be maintained that for the same reasons which were employed to prove the Self&amp;rsquo;s being an agent its agency must be held to be natural, there being no reasons to the contrary, we reply as follows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But from the highest (Lord there result saṁsāra and moksha), because scripture teaches that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now enter on the discussion whether the agentship, characterising the individual soul in the state of Nescience and founded on its limiting adjuncts, is independent of the Lord or dependent on him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that the soul as far as it is an agent does not depend on the Lord, because the assumption of such a dependence would serve no purpose. For as the individual soul has motives in its own imperfections, such as passion, aversion, and so on, and is furnished with the whole apparatus of the other constituents of action &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, it is able to occupy on its own account the position of an agent; and what then should the Lord do for it? Nor does ordinary experience show that in addition to the oxen which are required for such actions as ploughing and the like the Lord also is to be depended upon. Moreover (if all activity depended on the Lord) it would follow that the Lord is cruel because imposing on his creatures activity which is essentially painful, and at the same time unjust because allotting to their activities unequal results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But with a view to the efforts made (by the soul) (the Lord makes it act), on account of the (otherwise resulting) purportlessness of the injunctions and prohibitions, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; removes the objections started.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Lord makes the soul act, having regard to the efforts made by it, whether meritorious or non&amp;ndash;meritorious. Hence&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there is no room for the objections raised. Having regard to the inequality of the virtuous and vicious actions of the souls, the Lord, acting as a mere occasional cause, allots to them corresponding unequal results. An analogous case is furnished by rain. As rain constitutes the common occasional cause for shrubs, bushes, corn, and so on, which belong to different species and spring each from its particular seed&amp;ndash;for the inequality of their sap, flowers, fruits, and leaves results neither when rain is absent nor when the special seeds are absent&amp;ndash;; so we also must assume that the Lord arranges favourable or unfavourable circumstances for the souls with a view to their former efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The soul is) a part of the Lord, on account of the declarations of difference, and (because) in a different way also some record that (Brahman) is of the nature of slaves, fishers, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have shown that the individual soul and the Lord stand to each other in the relation of what is being acted upon and what is acting upon. This relation is observed in ordinary life to exist only between things connected, such as a master and a servant, or a fire and its sparks. Now as the soul and the Lord also are acknowledged to stand in the relation of what is acted upon and what is acting, a doubt arises whether their connexion is analogous to that of a master and a servant, or to that of a fire and its sparks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the mantra.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A mantra also intimates the same view. &amp;lsquo;Such is the greatness of it; greater than it is the Person. One foot of it are all beings, three feet of it are the Immortal in heaven&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 12, 6). Here the word &amp;lsquo;beings&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;denotes all moving and non-moving things, among which the souls occupy the first place; in accordance with the use of the word in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;Not giving pain to any being (bhūta) except at the tīrthas&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 15). Herefrom also we conclude that the individual soul is a part of the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moreover it is so stated in Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Īśvaragitās (Bhagavad-gītā) also it is said that the soul is a part of the Lord, &amp;lsquo;an eternal part of me becomes the individual soul in the world of life&amp;rsquo; (Bha. Gī. XV, 7). With regard to the assertion made above, viz. that in ordinary life the relation of ruler and ruled is known to hold good in the case of master and servant &amp;amp;c. only, we remark that, although that may be the case in ordinary life, we ascertain from scripture that the relation of part and whole and that of ruler and ruled may go together. Nor is there anything contradictory in assuming that the Lord who is provided with superexcellent limiting adjuncts rules the souls which are connected with inferior adjuncts only.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(As the soul is affected by pleasure and pain) not so the highest (Lord); as in the case of light and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We maintain that the highest Lord does not feel the pain of the saṁsāra-state in the same way as the soul does. The soul being engrossed by Nescience identifies itself as it were&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;with the body and so on, and imagines itself to be affected by the experience of pain which is due to Nescience, &amp;lsquo;I am afflicted by the pain due to the body;&amp;rsquo; the highest Lord, on the other hand, neither identifies himself with a body, nor imagines himself to be afflicted by pain. The pain of the individual soul also is not real, but imaginary only, caused by the error consisting in the non-discrimination of (the Self from) the body, senses, and other limiting adjuncts which are due to name and form, the effects of Nescience. And as a person feels the pain of a burn or cut which affects his body by erroneously identifying himself with the latter, so he feels also the pain affecting others, such as sons or friends, by erroneously identifying himself with them, entering as it were into them through love, and imagining &amp;lsquo;I am the son, I am the friend.&amp;rsquo; Wherefrom we infer with certainty that the feeling of pain is due merely to the error of false imagination. At the same conclusion we arrive on the ground of negative instances. Let us consider the case of many men, each of whom possesses sons, friends, &amp;amp;c., sitting together, some of them erroneously imagining that they are connected with their sons, friends, &amp;amp;c., while others do not. If then somebody calls out &amp;rsquo;the son has died,&amp;rsquo; &amp;rsquo;the friend has died,&amp;rsquo; grief is produced in the minds of those who are under the imagination of being connected with sons and friends, but not in the minds of religious mendicants who have freed themselves from that imagination. From this it appears that perfect knowledge is of use even to an ordinary man; of how much greater use then will it be to him (i.e. the Lord) whose nature is eternal pure intelligence, who sees nothing beside the Self for which there are no objects. Hence it follows that perfect knowledge is not purposeless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;47&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the Smr̥tis state (that).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vyāsa and others state in their smr̥tis the highest Self is not afflicted by the pain of the individual soul, &amp;lsquo;That highest Self is said to be eternal, devoid of qualities, nor is it stained by the fruits of actions any more than a lotus leaf by water. But that other Self whose essence is action is connected with bondage and release; again and again it is joined with the seventeenfold aggregate &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;48&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The possibility of) injunctions and prohibitions (results) from the connexion (of the Self) with bodies; as in the case of light and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Passages such as &amp;lsquo;He is to approach his wife at the proper time,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;he is not to approach the wife of his guru,&amp;rsquo; are examples of permissions (or injunctions) and prohibitions; or again passages such as &amp;lsquo;He is to kill the animal devoted to Agnīshomau,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;He is not to hurt any being.&amp;rsquo; Corresponding examples from ordinary life are: &amp;lsquo;A friend is to be served,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Enemies are to be shunned.&amp;rsquo; Permissions and prohibitions of this kind are possible, because the Self although one only is connected with various bodies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;49&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the non-extension (of the individual soul), there is no confusion (of the results of actions).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, let it be granted that injunctions and prohibitions, are valid, because the Self although one is joined with particular bodies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the admission, however, of the unity of the Self it follows that there must be a confusion of the fruits of actions, there being only one master (i.e. one soul to enjoy the fruits of action).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the individual soul is) an appearance (reflection) only.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And that individual soul is to be considered a mere appearance of the highest Self, like the reflection of the sun in the water; it is neither directly that (i.e. the highest Self), nor a different thing. Hence just as, when one reflected image of the sun trembles, another reflected image does not on that account tremble also; so, when one soul is connected with actions and results of actions, another soul is not on that account connected likewise. There is therefore no confusion of actions and results. And as that &amp;lsquo;appearance&amp;rsquo; is the effect of Nescience, it follows that the saṁsāra which is based on it (the appearance) is also the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;51&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the unseen principle being non-limitative.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While there are many souls, all-pervading like ether, and in equal proximity to all bodies from within as well as without, the so-called unseen principle (adr̥shṭa), which is of the nature of religious merit or demerit, is acquired through mind, speech, and body (i.e. thoughts, words, and actions).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now, according to the Sāṅkhyas, that principle inheres not in the Self, but abides in the pradhāna and cannot, on account of the pradhāna being the same (for all souls), be the limitative cause of the enjoyment of pleasure and pain for each individual Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;52&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And this is also the case in resolutions, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The objection pointed out before applies also to resolutions, &amp;amp;c., for they also are made through the non-particular conjunction of the internal organ and the Self, in proximity to all Selfs. Hence they also cannot furnish a reason for limitation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>53 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/3/53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;53&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Should it be said that distinction of pleasure, pain, &amp;amp;c., results) from (difference of) place; we say no, on account of the (Self&amp;rsquo;s) being within (all things).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here it might be objected that, although all Selfs are all-pervading, yet their conjunction with the internal organ which is seated in the body must take place in that part of each Self which is limited by the body; and that thus there may result from difference of locality a limitative distinction of resolutions, &amp;amp;c., of the adr̥shṭa, and of pleasure and pain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
