<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 fourth pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;fourth-pāda&#34;&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The purpose of man (is effected) thence (i.e. through the mere knowledge of Brahman), thus Bādarāyaṇa opines.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtrakāra at present enters on an inquiry whether the knowledge of the Self which is derived from the Upanishads, is connected with works through him who is entitled to perform the works &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or is an independent means to accomplish the purpose of man. He begins by stating the final view in the above Sūtra, &amp;lsquo;Thence&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. The teacher Bādarāyaṇa is of opinion that thence, i.e. through the independent knowledge of Brahman enjoined in the Vedānta-texts, the purpose of man is effected.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of (the Self) standing in a supplementary relation (to action), (the statements as to&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the fruits of the knowledge of the Self) are arthavādas, as in other cases, thus Jaimini opines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the Self, in consequence of its being the agent, stands in a supplementary relation to action, the knowledge of the Self also is connected with action through the mediation of its object, analogously to the case of the sprinkling of the rice-grains with water; hence as the purpose of the knowledge of the Self is understood thereby, the statements of the text about the fruits of that knowledge are mere arthavādas. Such is the opinion of the teacher Jaimini &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The case is analogous to that of other textual statements as to the fruits of certain materials, saṁskāras and works; which statements have likewise to be understood as arthavādas. Cp. the passage, &amp;lsquo;He whose sacrificial ladle is made of parṇa-wood hears no evil sound;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;By anointing his eye he wards off the eye of the enemy;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;By making the prayāja and anuyāja-oblations he makes an armour for the sacrifice, an armour for the sacrificer so that he overcomes his enemies &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of scripture showing (certain lines of) conduct.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Janaka the king of the Videhas sacrificed with a sacrifice at which many presents were given to the priests&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 1, 1); &amp;lsquo;Sirs, I am going to perform a sacrifice&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 11, 5); these and similar passages&amp;ndash;which occur in sections that have another purport&amp;ndash;show that those who know Brahman are connected with sacrificial action also. And similarly we apprehend from the fact that according to scripture Uddālaka and others taught their sons and so on, that they were connected with the condition of life of householders. If mere knowledge could effect the purpose of man, why should the persons mentioned have perforated works troublesome in many respects? &amp;lsquo;If a man would find honey in the Arka tree why should he go to the forest?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Because scripture directly states that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;What a man does with knowledge, faith and the Upanishad is more powerful&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 1, 10): this passage directly states that knowledge is subordinate to work &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and from this it follows that mere knowledge cannot effect the purpose of man.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;289:1 For the instrumental case &amp;lsquo;vidyayā&amp;rsquo; directly represents knowledge as a means of work.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the taking hold together.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Then both his knowledge and his work take hold of him&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 2); as this passage shows that knowledge and work begin together to manifest their fruits, it follows that knowledge is not independent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because scripture enjoins (works) for such (only as understand the purport of the Veda).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;He who has learnt (lit. &amp;ldquo;read&amp;rdquo;) the Veda from a family of teachers, according to the sacred injunction, in the leisure time left from the duties to be performed for the Guru; who after having received his discharge has settled in his own house, studying his sacred texts in some sacred spot&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 15); such passages also show that those who know the purport of the whole Veda are qualified for sacrificial action, and that hence knowledge does not independently bring about a result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of definite rules.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Performing works here (i.e. in this life) let a man wish to live a hundred years; thus work will not cling to thee, man; there is no other way than that&amp;rsquo; (Īśa. Up. 2); &amp;lsquo;The&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Agnihotra is a sattra lasting up to old age and death; for through old age one is freed from it or through death&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Brā. XII, 4, 1, 1); from such definite rules also it follows that knowledge is merely supplementary to works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of (scripture teaching) the additional one (i.e. the Lord), (the view) of Bādarāyaṇa (is valid); as that is seen thus (in scriptural passages).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; discards the pūrvapaksha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The assertion made in Sūtra 2 cannot be maintained &amp;lsquo;on account of the text teaching the additional one.&amp;rsquo; If the Vedānta-texts taught that the transmigrating embodied Self which is an agent and enjoyer is something different from the mere body, the statements as to the fruit of the knowledge of the Self would, for the reasons indicated above, be mere arthavādas. But what the Vedānta-texts really teach as the object of knowledge is something different from the embodied Self, viz. the non-transmigrating Lord who is free from all attributes of transmigratory existence such as agency and the like and distinguished by freedom from sin and so on, the highest Self. And the knowledge of that Self does not only not promote action but rather cuts all action short, as will be declared in Sūtra 16. Hence the view of the reverend Bādarāyaṇa which was stated in Sūtra 1 remains valid and cannot be shaken by fallacious reasoning about the subordination of knowledge to action and the like. That the Lord who is superior to the embodied Self is the Self many scriptural texts declare; compare &amp;lsquo;He who perceives all and knows all&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 9); &amp;lsquo;From terror of it the wind blows, from terror the sun rises&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 8); &amp;lsquo;It is a great terror, a raised thunderbolt&amp;rsquo; (Ka. Up. II, 6, 2); &amp;lsquo;By the command of that imperishable one, O Gārgī&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 9); &amp;lsquo;It thought, may I be many, may I grow forth. It sent forth fire&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 3). There are indeed passages in&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the declarations (of scripture) are equal (on the other side).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In reply to the averment made in Sūtra 3, we point out that there are declarations of scripture, of equal weight, in favour of the view that knowledge is not complementary to action. For there are scriptural passages such as, &amp;lsquo;Knowing this the r̥shis descended from Kavasha said: For what purpose should we study the Veda? for what purpose should we sacrifice? Knowing this indeed the Ancient ones did not offer the Agnihotra;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;When Brāhmaṇas know that Self and have risen above the desire for sons, wealth, and worlds, they wander about as mendicants&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 5). Scripture moreover shows that&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The direct statement is) non-comprehensive.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The direct scriptural statement implied in &amp;lsquo;What a man does with knowledge&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. does not refer to all knowledge, as it is connected with the knowledge forming the subject-matter of the section. And the latter is the knowledge of the udgītha only, &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the syllable Om (as) the udgītha.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is distribution (of the work and knowledge) as in the case of the hundred.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In reply to the averment (Sūtra 5) that the passage, &amp;lsquo;Then both his knowledge and his work take hold of him,&amp;rsquo; indicates the non-independence of knowledge, we point out that the passage must be understood in a distributed sense, knowledge taking hold of one man and work of another. The case is analogous to that of the &amp;lsquo;hundred.&amp;rsquo; When it is said, &amp;lsquo;Let a hundred be given to these two men,&amp;rsquo; the hundred are divided in that way that fifty are given to one man and fifty to the other.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of him who has merely read the Veda (there is qualification for works).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the clause, &amp;lsquo;Having learnt (read) the Veda from a family of teachers,&amp;rsquo; speaks only of the reading, we determine that acts are there enjoined for him who has only read the Veda.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But from this it would follow that on account of being destitute of knowledge such a person would not be qualified for works!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Never mind; we do not mean to deny that the understanding of sacrificial acts which springs from the reading of the texts is the cause of qualification for their performance; we only wish to establish that the knowledge of the Self derived from the Upanishads is seen to have an independent purpose of its own and therefore does not supply a reason of qualification for acts. Analogously a person who is qualified for one act does not require the knowledge of another act.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There being no specification (the rule does) not (specially apply to him who knows).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In passages such as &amp;lsquo;Performing works here let a man live&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., which state definite rules, there is no specification&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of him who knows, since the definite rule is enjoined without any such specification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or else the permission (of works) is for the glorification (of knowledge).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage &amp;lsquo;Performing works here&amp;rsquo; may be treated in another way also. Even if, owing to the influence of the general subject-matter, only he who knows is to be viewed as he who performs works, yet the permission to perform works must be viewed as aiming at the glorification of knowledge; as appears from the subsequent clause, &amp;rsquo;no work clings to the man.&amp;rsquo; The meaning of the entire passage thus is: To a man who knows no work will cling, should he perform works during his whole life even, owing to the power of knowledge. And this clearly glorifies knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some also by proceeding according to their liking (evince their disregard of anything but knowledge).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover some who know, having obtained the intuition of the fruit of knowledge, express, in reliance thereon, the purposelessness of the means of all other results, viz. by proceeding according to their liking (and abandoning those means). A scriptural text of the Vājasaneyins runs as follows: &amp;lsquo;Knowing this the people of old did not wish for offspring. What shall we do with offspring, they said, we who have this Self and this world&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22). And that the fruit of knowledge, being present to intuition, does not manifest itself at a later time only as the fruits of actions do, we have explained more than once. From this also it follows that knowledge is not subordinate to action, and that the scriptural statements as to the fruit of knowledge cannot be taken in any but their true sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (scripture teaches) the destruction (of the qualification for works, by knowledge).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover scripture teaches that this whole apparent world-which springs from Nescience, is characterised by&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;actions, agents and results of actions and is the cause of all qualification for works&amp;ndash;is essentially destroyed by the power of knowledge. Compare such passages as &amp;lsquo;But when all has become the Self of him, wherewith should he see another, wherewith should he smell another?&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 15). For him now who should teach that the qualification for works has for its necessary antecedent the knowledge of the Self which the Vedānta-texts teach, it would follow that the qualification for works is cut short altogether. From this also it follows that knowledge is independent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (knowledge belongs) to those who are bound to chastity; for in scripture (that condition of life is mentioned).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture shows that knowledge is valid also for those stages of life for which chastity is prescribed. Now in their case knowledge cannot be subordinate to work because work is absent; for the works prescribed by the Veda such as the Agnihotra are no longer performed by men who have reached those stages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jaimini (considers that scriptural passages mentioning those stages of life in which chastity is obligatory, contain) a reference (only to those stages);&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;they are not injunctions; for (other scriptural passages) forbid (those stages).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vedic texts which have been quoted to the end of showing the existence of the stages of life on which chastity is binding-such as &amp;lsquo;There are three branches of the law&amp;rsquo; and so on&amp;ndash;have no power to establish those stages. For the teacher Jaimini is of opinion that those passages contain only a reference to the other stages of life, not an injunction (of them).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The other stage of life) is to be accomplished, (according to) Bādarāyaṇa; on account of the scriptural statement of equality.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The teacher Bādarāyaṇa is of opinion that that other stage of life is something to be accomplished. The view that there is a contradiction because the other stage of life is stated in the Veda and, on the other hand, works such as the Agnihotra must necessarily be performed, and that, in order to remove this contradiction, that other stage of life must be entered upon by those only who are not qualified for active worship, he rejects; being of opinion that that other stage is to be entered upon, in the same way as the state of the householder, even by him who does not wish to do so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or (the passage rather is) an injunction, as in the case of the carrying (of the firewood).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or the passage is rather to be understood as containing an injunction, not a mere reference.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection is raised, if we assume it to be an injunction we thereby oppose the conception of the entire passage as a coherent whole, while yet the passage has clearly to be conceived as constituting such a whole, viz. as meaning that while the three branches of the law have for their result the world of the blessed, the condition of being grounded in Brahman has immortality for its result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (texts such as the one about the udgītha are) mere glorification, on account of their reference (to parts of sacrifices); we deny that, on account of the newness (of what they teach, if viewed as injunctions).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;That udgītha is the best of all essences, the highest, holding the highest place, the eighth&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 1, 3); &amp;lsquo;This earth is the R̥c, the fire is Sāman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 6, 1); &amp;lsquo;This world in truth is that piled-up fire-altar&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Brā. X, I, 2, 2); &amp;lsquo;That hymn is truly that earth&amp;rsquo; (Ait. Ār. II, 1, 2, 1); with reference to these and other similar passages a doubt arises whether they are meant to glorify the udgītha and so on, or to enjoin devout meditations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the words expressive of becoming.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover the text exhibits words of clearly injunctive meaning, in connexion with the passages quoted above, viz. &amp;lsquo;Let him meditate on the udgītha&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 1, 1); &amp;lsquo;Let him meditate on the Sāman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. II, 2, 1); &amp;lsquo;Let him think: I am the hymn&amp;rsquo; (Ait. Ār. II, 1, 6). Now these injunctive forms would be rendered futile by the assumption of the texts under discussion aiming at glorification only. Compare the following saying of those who know Nyāya, &amp;lsquo;Let him do, let it be done, it is to be done, let it become, let it be; these forms are in all Vedas the settled signs of injunction.&amp;rsquo; What they mean thereby is that injunction is the sense of all potential, imperative, &amp;amp;c., verbal forms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The stories told in the Upanishads) are for the purpose of the pāriplava; we deny this on account of (certain stories only) being specified.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Yājñavalkya had two wives, Maitreyī and Kātyāyani&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 1); &amp;lsquo;Pratardana, forsooth, the son of Divodāsa came to the beloved abode of Indra&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. III, 1); &amp;lsquo;There lived once upon a time Jānaśruti Pautrāyaṇa, who was a pious giver, giving much and keeping open house&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 1, 1); with regard to these and similar stories met with in the Vedānta portions of scripture there arises a doubt whether they are meant to subserve the performance of the pāriplava &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or to introduce the vidyās standing in proximity to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This follows also from the connexion (of the stories with the vidyās) in one coherent whole.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And as thus the stories do not subserve the pāriplava it&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;is appropriate to assume that they are meant to bring nearer to our understanding the approximate vidyās with which they are seen to form connected wholes; for they serve to render the latter more acceptable and facilitate their comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Maitreyī-brāhmaṇa we see that the story forms a whole with the vidyā beginning, &amp;lsquo;The Self indeed is to be seen,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.; in the account of Pratardana with the vidyā, &amp;lsquo;I am prāṇa, the conscious Self;&amp;rsquo; in the legend of Jānaśruti with the vidyā, &amp;lsquo;Air indeed is the end of all.&amp;rsquo; The case of all these stories is analogous to that of stories met with in scriptural texts referring to works, whose purpose is the glorification of injunctions standing in proximity; as e.g. &amp;lsquo;He cut out his own omentum.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For this very reason there is no need of the lighting of the fire and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The expression &amp;lsquo;For this very same reason&amp;rsquo; must be viewed as taking up Sutra III, 4, 1, because thus a satisfactory sense is established. For this very same reason, i.e. because knowledge subserves the purpose of man, the lighting of the sacrificial fire and similar works which are enjoined on the different āśramas are not to be observed, since man&amp;rsquo;s purpose is effected through knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And there is need of all (works), on account of the scriptural statement of sacrifices and the like; as in the case of the horse.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now consider whether knowledge has absolutely no need of the works enjoined on the different āśramas, or whether it has some need of them. Under the preceding Sutra we have arrived at the conclusion that as knowledge effects its own end the works enjoined on the āśramas are absolutely not required. With reference to this point the present Sutra now remarks that knowledge has regard&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But all the same he (who is desirous of knowledge) must be possessed of calmness, subjection of the senses, &amp;amp;c., since those (states) are enjoined as auxiliaries to that (viz. knowledge), and must (on that account) necessarily be accomplished.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps somebody might think that we have no right to look upon sacrifices and the like as means of knowledge because there is no injunction to that effect. For a passage like &amp;lsquo;By sacrifice they seek to know&amp;rsquo; is of the nature of an anuvāda, and therefore does not aim at enjoining sacrifices but rather at glorifying knowledge,&amp;rsquo; so glorious is knowledge that they seek to obtain it through sacrifices and the like.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And there is permission of all food, (only) in the case of danger of life; on account of this being shown (by scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the colloquy of the prāṇas the Cḥandogas record, &amp;lsquo;To him who knows this there is nothing which is not food&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 1, 2); and the Vājasaneyins,&amp;rsquo; By him nothing is eaten that is not food, nothing is received that is not food&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. VI, 1, 14). The sense of the two passages is that anything may be eaten by him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the non-sublation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And thus those scriptural passages which distinguish lawful and unlawful food, such as Cḥ. Up. VII, 26, 2, &amp;lsquo;When the food is pure the whole nature becomes pure,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;are non-sublated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And this is said in Smr̥ti also.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That in cases of need both he who knows and he who does not know may eat any food Smr̥ti also states; compare e.g. &amp;lsquo;He who being in danger of his life eats food from anywhere is stained by sin no more than the lotus leaf by water.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, many passages teach that unlawful food is to be avoided. &amp;lsquo;Intoxicating liquor the Brāhmaṇa must permanently forego;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Let them pour boiling spirits down the throat of the Brāhmaṇa who drinks spirits;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Spirit-drinking worms grow in the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And hence also a scriptural passage as to non-proceeding according to liking.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is also a scriptural passage prohibiting unlawful food, the purpose of which it is to stop procedure therein according to one&amp;rsquo;s liking, viz. in the Saṁhitā of the Kaṭḥas, &amp;lsquo;Therefore a Brāhmaṇa is not to drink spirits.&amp;rsquo; This text also is more appropriate if we take the passage, &amp;lsquo;To him who knows this,&amp;rsquo; as an arthavāda.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hence passages of that kind are arthavādas, not injunctions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The works of the āśramas (are incumbent on him) also (who does not desire release); because they are enjoined.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Under Sūtra 26 it has been proved that the work&amp;rsquo;s enjoined on the āśramas are means of knowledge. Now we will consider whether those works have to be performed also by him who does not desire final release and therefore takes his stand on his āśrama merely without wishing for knowledge&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And through the co-operativeness (of the works towards the origination of knowledge).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those works are also co-operative with knowledge just because they are enjoined as such, viz. in passages such as &amp;lsquo;Him the Brāhmaṇas seek to know by the study of the Veda,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. This has been explained under Sūtra 26. Nor must you think that the texts stating the co-operation of the works of the āśramas towards knowledge refer to the fruit of knowledge, as e.g. the offerings called prayājas co-operate towards the fruit of the darśapūrṇamāsa of which they are auxiliary members; for knowledge is not characterised by injunction, and the fruit of knowledge is not to be effected by means. Means characterised by injunctions such as the darśapūrṇamāsa-sacrifice which aim at bringing about certain fruits such as the heavenly would require other (subordinate) means co-operating towards the fruit (such as the prayājas). But not so knowledge. Compare on this point Sūtra 25. Therefore texts stating the cooperation of works (with knowledge) have to be interpreted as stating that works are means for the origination of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In any case the same (duties have to be performed) on account of the twofold indicatory marks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In any case, i.e. whether viewed as duties incumbent on the āśramas or as co-operating with knowledge, the very same agnihotra and other duties have to be performed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What, it may be asked, does the teacher wish to preclude by the emphatic expression &amp;rsquo;the very same?&#39;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The suspicion, we reply, that those works might be separate works &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In the ayana of the Kuṇḍapāyins indeed the injunctive statement,&amp;rsquo; They offer the agnihotra for a month &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;rsquo; enjoins a sacrifice different from the permanent (ordinary) agnihotra; but in our present case there is no analogous separation of works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And scripture also declares that (those performing works) are not overpowered (by passion and the like).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Sūtra points out a further indicatory mark fortifying the conclusion that works co-operate towards knowledge. Scripture also shows that he who is furnished with such means as Brahmacarya, &amp;amp;c., is not overpowered by such afflictions as passion and the like. Compare the passage, &amp;lsquo;That Self does not perish which they find out by Brahmacarya&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII,,&amp;quot;;, 3).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But also (persons standing) between (are qualified for knowledge); for that is seen (in scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt arises whether persons in want who do not possess means, &amp;amp;c., and therefore are not able to enter one or the other of the āśramas., standing between as it were, are qualified for knowledge or not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They are not qualified, the pūrvapakshin maintains. For we have ascertained that the works incumbent on the āśramas are the cause of knowledge, and those persons have no opportunity to perform those works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This is stated in Smr̥ti also.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is recorded in itihāsas also how Saṁvarta and others who paid no regard to the duties incumbent on the āśramas, in going naked and so on, became great Yogins all the same.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But the instances quoted from scripture and Smr̥ti furnish merely indicatory marks; what then is&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the final conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That conclusion is stated in the next Sūtra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the promotion (of knowledge is bestowed on them) through special acts.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also for widowers, &amp;amp;c., the favour of knowledge is possible through special acts of duty, such as praying, fasting, propitiation of divinities, &amp;amp;c., which are not opposed to their āśrama-less condition and may be performed by any man as such. Thus Smr̥ti says, &amp;lsquo;By mere prayer no doubt the Brāhmaṇa perfects himself. May he perform other works or not, the kindhearted one is called Brāhmaṇa (Manu Saṁh. II, 87), which passage shows that where the works of the āśramas are not possible prayer qualifies for knowledge. Moreover knowledge may be promoted by āśrama works performed in previous births. Thus Smr̥ti also declares, &amp;lsquo;Perfected by many births he finally goes the highest way&amp;rsquo; (Bha. Gītā VI, 45); which passage shows that the aggregate of the different purificatory ceremonies performed in former births promotes knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Better than this is the other (state of belonging to an āśrama), on account of the indicatory marks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Than this,&amp;rsquo; i.e. &amp;rsquo;than standing between,&amp;rsquo; a better means of knowledge it is to stand within one of the āśramas, since this is confirmed by Śruti and Smr̥ti. For scripture supplies an indicatory mark in the passage, &amp;lsquo;On that path goes whoever knows Brahman and who has done holy&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;works (as prescribed for the āśramas) and obtained splendour&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 9); and Smr̥ti in the passage, &amp;lsquo;Let a Brāhmaṇa stay not one day even outside the āśrama; having stayed outside for a year he goes to utter ruin.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But of him who has become that (i.e. entered on a higher āśrama) there is no becoming not that (i.e. descending to a lower one), according to Jaimini also, on account of restrictive rule, absence of such like (i.e. statements of descent), and non-existence (of good custom).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been established that there are stages of life for which chastity is obligatory. A doubt here arises whether one who has entered them may for some reason or other fall from them or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And not also (can the expiation take place) prescribed in the chapter treating of qualification, because on account of the inference of his lapse from Smr̥ti he (the Naishṭḥika) is not capable of it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If a Brahmacārin for life breaks from inattention the vow of chastity, is he to perform the expiatory sacrifice enjoined by the text, &amp;lsquo;A student who has broken the vow of chastity shall sacrifice an ass to Nirr̥ti [^sbe38251.htmfn_202]&amp;rsquo; or not?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But some (consider the sin) a minor one, (and&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;hence claim) the existence (of expiation for the Naishṭḥika also); as in the case of the eating (of unlawful food). This has been explained (in the Pūrva Mīmāṁsā).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some teachers, however, are of opinion that the transgression of the vow of chastity, even on the part of a professed Brahmacārin, is a minor sin, not a mortal one, excepting cases where the wife of the teacher and so on are concerned. For they plead that that sin is not anywhere enumerated among the deadly ones such as violating a teacher&amp;rsquo;s bed and so on. Accordingly they claim the expiatory ceremony to be valid for the Naishṭḥika as well as the Upakurvāṇa; both being alike Brahmacārins and having committed the same offence. The case is analogous to that of eating. Just as Brahmacārins (in general) who have broken their vow by eating honey, flesh, and the like may again purify themselves by a ceremony, so here also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (they are to be kept outside) in either case, on account of Smr̥ti and custom.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But whether lapses from the duties of one&amp;rsquo;s order, committed by those who are bound to chastity, be mortal sins or minor sins, in either case such persons are to be excluded by honourable men (śishṭas). For Smr̥ti refers to them in terms of the highest reproach; cp. passages such as the one quoted under Sūtra 41; and the following one, &amp;lsquo;He who touches a Brāhmaṇa that has broken his vow and fallen from his order, or a hanged man or one gnawed by worms must undergo the Cāndrāyaṇa penance.&amp;rsquo; And good custom also condemns them; for good men do not sacrifice, study, or attend weddings with such persons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To the lord (of the sacrifice) only (the agent-ship in meditations belongs), because scripture declares a fruit; this is the view of Ātreya.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to meditations on subordinate members of sacrificial actions there arises a doubt whether they are to be carried out by the sacrificer (i.e. him for whom the sacrifice is performed) or by the officiating priests.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the sacrificer, the pūrvapakshin maintains, because scripture declares fruits. For a fruit is declared in such texts as the following one, &amp;lsquo;There is rain for him, and he brings rain for others who thus knowing meditates on the fivefold Sāman as rain&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. II, 3, 2); and we must conclude that that fruit goes to the Lord of the sacrifice, because it is he who is entitled to the sacrificial performance together with its subordinate members, and because such meditations fall within the sphere of that to which he is entitled. And that the fruit belongs to him who carries out the meditations scripture states when saying, &amp;lsquo;There is rain for him who meditates.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(They are) the work of the priest, this is the view of Auḍulomi; since for that (i.e. the entire sacrificial work) he is feed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The assertion that the meditations on subordinate members of the sacrifice are the work of the sacrificer is unfounded. They rather are the work of the priest, as the teacher Auḍulomi thinks. For the priest is rewarded for the work together with its subordinate members; and the meditations on the udgītha and so on fall within the performance of the work since they belong to the sphere of that to which the person entitled (viz. the lord of the sacrifice) is entitled. Hence they are to be carried out by the priests only, the case being analogous to that of the restrictive rule as to the work to be performed by means of the godohana vessel. In agreement herewith scripture declares the udgātr̥ to be the agent in knowledge, in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;Him Vaka Dālbhya knew. He was the udgātr̥ of the Naimishīya-sacrificers&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I. 2, 13). With reference to the circumstance noted by the pūrvapakshin that scripture states the fruit to belong to the agent, we remark that this makes no difference: For with the exception of cases expressly stated the priest cannot be connected with the sacrifice since he subserves the purposes (acts for) another (viz. the lord of the sacrifice).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of scriptural statement.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Whatever blessing the priests pray for at the sacrifice, they pray for the good of the sacrificer; thus he said&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Brā. I, 3, 1, 26); &amp;lsquo;Therefore an udgātr̥ who knows this may say: what wish shall I obtain for you by my singing?&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 7, 8). These scriptural passages also declare that the fruit of meditations in which the priest is the agent goes to the sacrificer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;47&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is the injunction of something else cooperating (towards knowledge) (which is) a third thing (with regard to bālya and pāṇḍitya), (which injunction is given) for the case (of perfect knowledge not yet having arisen) to him who is such (i.e. the Saṁnyāsin possessing knowledge); as in the case of injunctions and the like.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Therefore let a Brāhmaṇa after he has done with learning wish to stand by a childlike state; and after he has done with the childlike state and learning (he is, or, may be) a Muni; and after he has done with what constitutes Muniship and non-Muniship (he is, or, may be) a Brāhmaṇa&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 5). With reference to this passage a doubt arises whether it enjoins the state of a Muni or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;48&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of his being all, however, there is winding up with the householder.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;however&amp;rsquo; is meant to lay stress on the householder&amp;rsquo;s being everything. For the performance of many works belonging to his own āśrama, such as sacrifices and the like, which involve not a little trouble, is enjoined on him by scripture; and at the same time the duties of the other āśramas&amp;ndash;such as tenderness for all living creatures, restraint of the senses and so on&amp;ndash;are incumbent on him also as far as circumstances allow. There is therefore nothing contradictory&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;49&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of there being injunction of the others also, in the same way as of the state of a Muni.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the state of the Muni (Saṁnyāsin) and the state of the householder are enjoined in scripture, so also the two other orders, viz. that of the hermit, and that of the student. For we have already pointed above to passages such as Austerity is the second, and to dwell as a student in the house of a teacher is the third.&amp;rsquo; As thus the four āśramas are equally taught by scripture, they are to be gone through equally, either in the way of option (between them) or in the way of comprehension (of all of them).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The passage enjoining bālya means that the ascetic is to live) not manifesting himself; on account of the connexion (thus gained for the passage).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage, &amp;lsquo;Therefore let a Brāhmaṇa after he has done with learning wish to stand by a childlike state,&amp;rsquo; speaks of the childlike state as something to be undertaken. Now by the &amp;lsquo;childlike state&amp;rsquo; we have to understand either the nature or the actions of a child. Childhood in so far as it means a period of life cannot be brought about at will, and we therefore must take the &amp;lsquo;childlike state&amp;rsquo; to mean either the behaviour of a child&amp;ndash;such as attending to the calls of nature without any respect of place, &amp;amp;c.&amp;ndash;or inward purity, i.e. absence of cunning, arrogance, force of the sensual passions, and so on &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;51&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In this life also (the origination of knowledge takes place) if there is no obstruction of what is ready at hand; on account of this being seen (in scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Beginning from Sūtra 26 of the present pāda we have discussed the various means of knowledge. We are now to consider whether knowledge&amp;ndash;the fruit of those means&amp;ndash;when accomplishing itself accomplishes itself only here in this life, or sometimes in the next life only,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/4/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;52&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;No such definite rule (exists) as to the fruit which is release, on account of the assertions as to that condition, on account of the assertions as to that condition.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have seen that in the case of persons desirous of release who rely upon the means of knowledge there exists a definite difference of result, in so far as the knowledge resulting springs up either in this life or a future life according to the degree of strength of the means employed. It might now be supposed that there exists a similar definite difference with regard to the fruit characterised as final release, owing to the superior or inferior qualification of the persons knowing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
