<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 first pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST PĀDA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;third-adhyāya&#34;&gt;THIRD ADHYĀYA&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-pāda&#34;&gt;FIRST PĀDA&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In obtaining a different (body) (the soul) goes enveloped (by subtle parts of the elements), (as appears from) question and explanation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the second adhyāya we have refuted the objections raised against the Vedāntic of Brahman on the ground of Smr̥ti and reasoning; we have shown that all other opinions are devoid of foundation, and that the alleged mutual contradictions of Vedic texts do not exist. Further we have demonstrated that the entities different from&amp;ndash;but subordinate to&amp;ndash;the individual soul (such as prāṇa, &amp;amp;c.) spring from Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of (water) consisting of three (elements) (the soul is enveloped not by water merely; the latter alone is, however, mentioned) on account of preponderance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; disposes of the objection raised.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Water consists of three elements, as we know from the scriptural statement regarding tripartition. If, therefore, water is admitted to originate (the new body) the other two elements also have necessarily to be admitted (as taking part in the origination). The body moreover consists of three elements, as the effects of the three, i.e. fire, water, and earth, are observed in it, and further as it contains three materials, viz. wind, bile, and phlegm &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Being such it cannot originate from mere water, the other elements being left aside. Hence the term water made use of in the scriptural question and answer refers to the fact of water preponderating,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the going of the prāṇas.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture states that, when a new body is obtained, the prāṇas also go (from the old body to the new one). Cp. &amp;lsquo;When he thus departs the (chief) prāṇa departs after him, and when the prāṇa thus departs all the other prāṇas depart after it&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 2), and similar passages. Now this going of the prāṇas is not possible without a base; hence we infer that water also&amp;ndash;mixed with parts of the other elements&amp;ndash;goes (from the old body to the new one), serving the purpose of supplying a base for the moving prāṇas. For the prāṇas cannot, without such a base, either move or abide anywhere; as we observe in living beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that the prāṇas do not go) on account of the scriptural statement as to entering into Agni, &amp;amp;c., we deny this on account of the metaphorical nature (of those statements).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, the pūrvapaksha resumes, we deny that at the time when a new body is obtained the prāṇas go with the soul, because scripture speaks of their going to Agni, &amp;amp;c. For that at the time of death speech and the other prāṇas go to Agni and the other gods the following passage expressly declares: &amp;lsquo;When the speech of the dead person&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If an objection be raised on the ground of (water) not being mentioned in the first fire, we refute it by remarking that just it (viz. water) (is meant), on the ground of fitness.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, the pūrvapakshin resumes, but how can it be ascertained that &amp;lsquo;in the fifth oblation water is called man,&amp;rsquo; considering that water is not mentioned by scripture with reference to the first fire (altar)? For the text enumerates five fires&amp;ndash;the first of which is the heavenly world&amp;ndash;as the abodes of the five oblations. With reference to the first of those fires&amp;ndash;introduced by the words &amp;lsquo;The fire is that world, O Gautama,&amp;rsquo; it is stated that śraddhā (faith) is the material constituting the oblation (&amp;lsquo;on that altar the devas offer śraddhā&amp;rsquo;); while nothing is said about water being the offered material. If, with reference to the four following fires, viz. Parjanya, &amp;amp;c., water is assumed to constitute the offering, we have no objection because in the substances stated there as forming the oblations, viz. Soma, and so on, water may preponderate. But to set aside, in the case of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Should it be said that the souls are not enveloped by water) on account of this not being stated by scripture, we refute the objection on the ground of those who perform ishṭis, &amp;amp;c., being understood.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, let it be granted that, on account of question and answer, water, passing through the forms of śraddhā, &amp;amp;c., may in the fifth oblation obtain the shape of man. But still we cannot allow that the souls when moving from one body into another are enveloped by water. For this is not directly stated by scripture, there being in the whole passage no word referring to the souls, while there are words referring to water. Hence the assertion that the soul goes enveloped by water is unfounded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or (the souls&amp;rsquo; being the food of the gods is) metaphorical, on account of their not knowing the Self. For thus (scripture) declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;or&amp;rsquo; is meant to set aside the started objection. The souls&amp;rsquo; being food has to be understood in a metaphorical, not a literal, sense, as otherwise all scriptural statements of claims (adhikāra)&amp;ndash;such as &amp;lsquo;He who is desirous of the heavenly world is to sacrifice&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;would be contradicted. If&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the passing away of the works (the soul redescends) with a remainder, according to scripture and Smr̥ti, as it went (i.e. passing through the same stations) and not thus (i.e. in the inverse order).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture states that the souls of those who perform sacrifices, and the like, rise on the road leading through smoke, and so on, to the sphere of the moon, and when they have done with the enjoyment (of the fruits of their works) again descend, &amp;lsquo;Having dwelt there, yāvatsampātam &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, they return again that way as they came,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., up to &amp;lsquo;Those whose conduct has been good obtain some good birth, the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Should it be objected that on account of conduct (the assumption of a remainder is not needed), we deny this because (the scriptural expression &amp;lsquo;conduct&amp;rsquo;) is meant to connote (the remainder); so Kārshṇājini thinks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But&amp;ndash;an objection may be raised&amp;ndash;the scriptural passage, which has been quoted for the purpose of proving that the existence of a remainder of works (&amp;rsquo;those whose conduct has been good,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.), declares that the quality of the new birth depends on caraṇa, not on anuśaya. Now caraṇa and anuśaya are different things; for caraṇa is the same as caritra, ācāra, śīla, all of which mean conduct &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while anuśaya denotes work remaining from requited work. Scripture also speaks of actions and conduct as different things, &amp;lsquo;According as he acts and according as he conducts himself so will he be&amp;rsquo; (Br̥, Up. IV, 4, 5); and &amp;lsquo;Whatever&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that purposelessness (of conduct would result therefrom), we deny this on account of the dependence (of work) on that (conduct).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That may be; but for what reason should we abandon that meaning which the term &amp;lsquo;caraṇa&amp;rsquo; directly conveys, viz. the meaning &amp;lsquo;conduct,&amp;rsquo; and accept the merely connotative meaning &amp;lsquo;remainder of the works?&amp;rsquo; Conduct, which the text directly mentions, may be supposed to have for its fruit either a good or an evil birth, according as it is enjoined or prohibited, good or evil. Some fruit will have to be allowed to it in any case; for otherwise it would follow that it is purposeless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (caraṇa means) nothing but good and evil works; thus Bādari opines.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The teacher Bādari, however, thinks that the word &amp;lsquo;caraṇa&amp;rsquo; denotes nothing else but good works and evil works. It means the same as anushṭḥāna (performance) or karman (work). For we see that the root car (to walk, to conduct oneself) is used in the general sense of acting. Of a man who performs holy works such as sacrifices, &amp;amp;c., people say in ordinary language, &amp;rsquo;that excellent man walks in righteousness.&amp;rsquo; The word ācāra also denotes only a kind of religious duty. That works and caraṇa (conduct) are sometimes spoken of as different things is analogous to the distinction sometimes made between Brāhmaṇas and Parivrājakas &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We, therefore, decide that by men of good caraṇa are meant those whose works are worthy of praise, by men of evil caraṇa those whose works are worthy of blame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of those also who do not perform sacrifices (the ascent to the moon) is stated by scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been said that those who perform sacrifices, &amp;amp;c., go to the moon. The question now arises whether those also who do not perform sacrifices go to the moon or not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that it cannot be asserted that men belonging to the former class only go to the moon,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;because scripture speaks of the moon as being resorted to by those also who have not performed sacrifices. For the Kāushītakins make the following general statement, &amp;lsquo;All who depart from this world go to the moon&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. I, 2). Moreover, the origination of a new body in the case of those who are born again is not possible without their having (previously) reached the moon, on account of the precise definition of number contained in the statement, &amp;lsquo;In the fifth oblation&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 9, 1) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Hence all men must be supposed to resort to the moon. If it be objected that it does not appear proper that those who perform sacrifices and those who do not should go to the same place, we reply that there is no real objection, because those who do not perform sacrifices do not enjoy anything in the moon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But of the others, after having enjoyed the fruits of their actions in Saṁyamana, ascent and descent take place; as such a course is declared (by scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;But&amp;rsquo; discards the pūrvapaksha. It is not true that all men go to the moon. For the ascent to the moon is for the purpose of enjoyment only; it is neither without a special purpose nor for the mere purpose of subsequent re-descent. Just as a man climbs on a tree for the purpose of breaking fruit or blossoms, not either without any aim or for the mere purpose of coming down again. Now it has been admitted already that for those who do not offer sacrifices there is not any enjoyment in the moon; hence those only who perform sacrifices rise to the moon, not any other persons. The latter descend to Saṁyamana, the abode of Yama, suffer there the torments of Yama corresponding to their evil deeds, and then again re-ascend to this world. Such is their ascent and descent; as we maintain on the ground of such a course being declared by scripture. For a scriptural passage embodying Yama&amp;rsquo;s own words declares that those who die without having offered sacrifices fall into Yama&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Smr̥tis also declare this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, authorities like Manu, Vyāsa, &amp;amp;c., declare that in the city Saṁyamana evil works are requited under Yama&amp;rsquo;s rule; cp. the legend of Nāciketa and others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moreover there are seven (hells).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the purāṇa-writers record that there are seven hells, Raurava, &amp;amp;c., by name, which serve as abodes of enjoyment of the fruits of evil deeds. As those who do not sacrifice, &amp;amp;c. go there, how should they reach the moon?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection is raised, the assertion that evil doers suffer punishments allotted by Yama is contradicted by the circumstance that Smr̥ti mentions different other beings, such as Citragupta, &amp;amp;c., who act as superintendents in Raurava and the other hells.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of his activity there also no contradiction exists.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is no contradiction, as the same Yama is admitted to act as chief ruler in those seven hells. Of Kitragupta and others Smr̥ti merely speaks as superintendents employed by Yama.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on (the two roads) of knowledge and works, those two being under discussion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In that place of the knowledge of the five fires, where the answer is expected to the question, &amp;lsquo;Do you know why that world never becomes full?&amp;rsquo; the text runs as follows: &amp;lsquo;On neither of these two ways are those small creatures continually returning, of whom it may be said, Live and die. Theirs is a third place. Therefore that world never becomes full.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not in (the case of) the third place, as it is thus perceived.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to third place, the rule of the oblations being five in number need not be attended to for the purpose of obtaining a new body.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of it being perceived thus. That means; because it is seen that the third place is reached in the manner described without any reference to the oblations being limited to the number five, &amp;lsquo;Live and die. That is the third place.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It is, moreover, recorded in the (ordinary) world.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are, moreover, traditions, apart from the Veda, that certain persons like Droṇa, Dhr̥shṭadyumna, Sītā, Draupadī, &amp;amp;c., were not born in the ordinary way from&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mothers. In the case of Droṇa and others there was absent the oblation which is made into the woman; while in the case of Dhr̥shṭadyumna and others, even two of the oblations, viz. the one offered into woman and the one offered into man, were absent. Hence in other cases also birth may be supposed to take place independently of the number of oblations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of observation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is, moreover, observed that out of the four classes of organic beings&amp;ndash;viviparous animals, oviparous animals, animals springing from heat, and beings springing from germs (plants)&amp;ndash;the two latter classes are produced without sexual intercourse, so that in their case no regard is had to the number of oblations. The same may therefore take place in other cases also.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection may here be raised, scripture speaks of those beings as belonging to three classes only, because there are three modes of origin only; &amp;lsquo;That which springs from an egg, that which springs from a living being, that which springs from a germ&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 3, 1). How then can it be maintained that there are four classes?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The third term comprises that which springs from heat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The third term in the scriptural passage quoted, i.e. &amp;rsquo;that which springs from a germ,&amp;rsquo; must be understood as implying those beings also which spring from heat; the two classes having in common that they spring from earth or water, i.e. from something stable. Different from their origin is the origin of those beings which spring from moving things (viz. animals).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(On the part of the soul&amp;rsquo;s descending from the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;moon) there is entering into similarity of being (with ether and so on); as this (only) is possible.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been explained that the souls of those who perform sacrifices, &amp;amp;c., after having reached the moon dwell there as long as their works last and then re-descend with a remainder of their works. We now have to inquire into the mode of that descent. On this point scripture makes the following statement: &amp;lsquo;They return again the way they came, to the ether, from the ether to the air. Then the sacrificer having become air becomes smoke, having become smoke he becomes mist, having become mist he becomes a cloud, having become a cloud he rains down.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The soul passes through the stages of its descent) in a not very long time; on account of the special statement.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt arises with reference to the period beginning with the soul&amp;rsquo;s becoming ether and extending up to its entering into rice, &amp;amp;c., viz. whether the soul remains a long time in the state of similarity to each of the stages of its way before it enters into similarity to the next one, or only a short time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The descending souls enter) into (plants) animated by other (souls), as in the previous cases, on account of scriptural declaration.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the description of the souls&amp;rsquo; descent we read, after their coming down in raindrops has been mentioned, &amp;lsquo;Then they are born as rice and corn, herbs and trees, sesamum and beans.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here a doubt arises whether, at this stage of their descent, the souls to which a remainder of their works continues to cling really pass over into the different species of those immoveable things (plants) and enjoy their pleasures and pains, or if they enter merely into a state of conjunction with the bodies of those plants which are animated by different souls.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Should it be said that (sacrificial work is) unholy; we deny this on the ground of scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We proceed to refute the remark made by the pūrvapakshin that sacrificial works are unholy because involving harm done to animals, &amp;amp;c., that they may therefore lead to unpleasant results, and that hence the statement as to the souls being born as plants, &amp;amp;c., may be taken in its&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;literal sense; in consequence of which it would be uncalled-for to assume a derived sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;After that (there takes place) conjunction (of the soul) with him who performs the act of generation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conclusion arrived at under the preceding Sūtra is confirmed also by scripture stating that the souls, after having entered into plants, &amp;lsquo;become&amp;rsquo; beings performing the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;act of generation, &amp;lsquo;for whoever eats the food, whoever performs the act of generation, that again he (the soul) becomes.&amp;rsquo; Here again the soul&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;becoming&amp;rsquo; he who performs the act of generation cannot be taken in its literal sense; for a person becomes capable of generation a long time after his birth only, viz. when he reaches puberty. How then should the soul contained in the food eaten enter into that condition in its true sense? Hence we must interpret the passage to mean only that the soul enters into conjunction with one who performs the act of generation; and from this we again infer that the soul&amp;rsquo;s becoming a plant merely means its entering into conjunction with a plant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/1/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;From the yoni a (new) body (springs).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then, subsequently to the soul having been in conjunction with a person of generative power, generation takes place, and a body is produced in which the soul can enjoy the fruits of that remainder of works which still attaches to it. This scripture declares in the passage, &amp;lsquo;Those whose conduct has been good,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. From this, also, it appears that the souls to which a remainder clings, when descending and becoming rice plants, and so on, do not enter into the state of forming the body of those plants with its attendant pleasure and pain, but are &amp;lsquo;born as plants&amp;rsquo; in so far only as they enter into conjunction with them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
