<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 second pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-pāda&#34;&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the first pāda Brahman has been shown to be the cause of the origin, subsistence, and reabsorption of the entire world, comprising the ether and the other elements. Moreover, of this Brahman, which is the cause of the entire world, certain qualities have (implicitly) been declared, such as all-pervadingness, eternity, omniscience, its being the Self of all, and so on. Further, by producing reasons showing that some words which are generally used in a different sense denote Brahman also, we have been able to determine that some passages about whose sense doubts are entertained refer to Brahman. Now certain other passages present themselves which because containing only obscure indications of Brahman give rise to the doubt whether they refer to the highest Self or to something else. We therefore begin the second and third pādas in order to settle those doubtful points.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because the qualities desired to be expressed are possible (in Brahman; therefore the passage refers to Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although in the Veda which is not the work of man no wish in the strict sense can be expressed &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, there being no speaker, still such phrases as &amp;lsquo;desired to be expressed,&amp;rsquo; may be figuratively used on account of the result, viz. (mental) comprehension. For just as in ordinary language we speak of something which is intimated by a word and is to be received (by the hearer as the meaning of the word), as &amp;lsquo;desired to be expressed;&amp;rsquo; so in the Veda also whatever is denoted as that which is to be received is &amp;lsquo;desired to be expressed,&amp;rsquo; everything else &amp;rsquo;not desired to be expressed.&amp;rsquo; What is to be received as the meaning of a Vedic sentence, and what not, is inferred from the general purport of the passage. Those qualities which are here desired to be expressed, i.e. intimated as qualities to be dwelt on in meditation, viz. the qualities of having true purposes, &amp;amp;c. are possible in the highest Brahman; for the quality of having true purposes may be ascribed to the highest Self which possesses unimpeded power over the creation, subsistence, and reabsorption of this world. Similarly the qualities of having true desires and true purposes are attributed to the highest Self in another passage, viz. the one beginning, &amp;lsquo;The Self which is free from sin&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 7, 1). The clause, &amp;lsquo;He whose Self is the ether,&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;he whose Self is like the ether;&amp;rsquo; for Brahman may be said to be like the ether on account of its omnipresence and other qualities. This is also expressed by the clause, &amp;lsquo;Greater than the earth.&amp;rsquo; And the other explanation also, according to which the passage means &amp;lsquo;he whose Self is the ether&amp;rsquo; is possible, since Brahman which as the cause of the whole world is the Self of everything is also the Self of the ether. For the same reasons he is called &amp;lsquo;he to whom all works belong, and so on.&amp;rsquo; Thus the qualities here intimated as topics of meditation agree with the nature of Brahman. We further maintain that the terms &amp;lsquo;consisting of mind,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;having breath for its body,&amp;rsquo; which the pūrvapakshin asserts&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the other hand, as (those qualities) are not possible (in it), the embodied (soul is) not (denoted by manomaya, &amp;amp;c.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The preceding Sūtra has declared that the qualities mentioned are possible in Brahman; the present Sūtra states that they are not possible in the embodied Self. Brahman only possesses, in the manner explained, the qualities of consisting of mind, and so on; not the embodied individual soul. For qualities such as expressed in the words, &amp;lsquo;He whose purposes are true, whose Self is the ether, who has no speech, who is not disturbed, who is greater than the earth,&amp;rsquo; cannot easily be attributed to the embodied Self. By the term &amp;rsquo;embodied&amp;rsquo; (śārīra) we have to understand &amp;lsquo;residing&amp;rsquo; in a body. If it be objected that the Lord also resides in the body &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, we reply, True, he does reside in the body, but not in the body only; for śruti declares him to be all-pervading; compare, &amp;lsquo;He is greater than the earth; greater than the atmosphere, omnipresent like the ether, eternal.&amp;rsquo; The individual soul, on the other&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because there is a (separate) denotation of the object of activity and of the agent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The attributes of consisting of mind, and so on, cannot belong to the embodied Self for that reason also, that there is a (separate) denotation of the object of activity and of the agent. In the passage, &amp;lsquo;When I shall have departed from hence I shall obtain him&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 14, 4), the word &amp;lsquo;him&amp;rsquo; refers to that which is the topic of discussion, viz. the Self which is to be meditated upon as possessing the attributes of consisting of mind, &amp;amp;c., as the object of an activity, viz. as something to be obtained; while the words, &amp;lsquo;I shall obtain,&amp;rsquo; represent the meditating individual Self as the agent, i.e. the obtainer. Now, wherever it can be helped, we must not assume that one and the same being is spoken of as the agent and the object of the activity at the same time. The relation existing between a person meditating and the thing meditated upon requires, moreover, different abodes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the difference of words.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That which possesses the attributes of consisting of mind, and so on, cannot be the individual soul, for that reason also that there is a difference of words.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That is to say, we meet with another scriptural passage of kindred subject-matter (Śat. Brā. X, 6, 3, 2), &amp;lsquo;Like a rice grain, or a barley grain, or a canary seed or the kernel of a canary seed, thus that golden person is in the Self.&amp;rsquo; There one word, i.e. the locative &amp;lsquo;in the Self,&amp;rsquo; denotes the embodied Self, and a different word, viz. the nominative &amp;lsquo;person,&amp;rsquo; denotes the Self distinguished by the qualities of consisting of mind, &amp;amp;c. We therefrom conclude that the two are different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Smr̥ti also declares the difference of the embodied Self&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and the highest Self, viz. Bha. Gītā XVIII, 61, &amp;lsquo;The Lord, O Arjuna, is seated in the heart of all beings, driving round by his magical power all beings (as if they were) mounted on a machine.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But what, it may be asked, is that so-called embodied Self different from the highest Self which is to be set aside according to the preceding Sūtras? Śruti passages, as well as Smr̥ti, expressly deny that there is any Self apart from the highest Self; compare, for instance, Br̥. Up. 111, 7, 23, &amp;lsquo;There is no other seer but he; there is no other hearer but he;&amp;rsquo; and Bha. Gītā XIII, 2, &amp;lsquo;And know me also, O Bhārata, to be the kshetrajña in all kshetras.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (the passage does) not (refer to Brahman) on account of the smallness of the abode (mentioned), and on account of the denotations of that (i.e. of minuteness); we say, no; because (Brahman) has thus to be contemplated, and because the case is analogous to that of ether.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of the limitation of its abode, which is mentioned in the clause, &amp;lsquo;He is my Self within the heart,&amp;rsquo; and on account of the declaration as to its minuteness contained in the direct statement, &amp;lsquo;He is smaller than a grain of rice,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.; the embodied soul only, which is of the size of an awl&amp;rsquo;s point, is spoken of in the passage under discussion, and not&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it is said that (from the circumstance of Brahman and the individual soul being one) there follows fruition (on the part of Brahman); we say, no; on account of the difference of nature (of the two).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, it may be said, as Brahman is omnipresent like ether, and therefore connected with the hearts of all living beings, and as it is of the nature of intelligence and therefore not different from the individual soul, it follows that Brahman also has the same fruition of pleasure, pain, and so on (as the individual soul). The same result follows from its unity. For in reality there exists no transmigratory Self different from the highest Self; as appears from the text, &amp;lsquo;There is no other knower but he&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 23), and similar passages. Hence the highest Self is subject to the fruition connected with transmigratory existence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The eater (is the highest Self) since what is movable and what is immovable is mentioned (as his food).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Kaṭḥavallī (I, 2, 25), &amp;lsquo;Who then knows where He is, He to whom the Brahmans and Kshattriyas are but food, and death itself a condiment?&amp;rsquo; This passage intimates, by means of the words &amp;lsquo;food&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;condiment,&amp;rsquo; that there is some eater. A doubt then arises whether the eater be Agni or the individual soul or the highest Self; for no distinguishing characteristic is stated, and Agni as well as the individual soul and the highest Self is observed to form, in that Upanishad, the subjects of questions &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the topic under discussion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the highest Self only can be the eater referred to&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;is moreover evident from the passage (Ka. Up. I, 2, 18), (&amp;lsquo;The knowing Self is not born, it dies not&amp;rsquo;), which shows that the highest Self is the general topic. And to adhere to the general topic is the proper proceeding. Further, the clause, &amp;lsquo;Who then knows where he is,&amp;rsquo; shows that the cognition is connected with difficulties; which circumstance again points to the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The &amp;rsquo;two entered into the cave&amp;rsquo; (are the individual soul and the highest Self), for the two are (intelligent) Selfs (and therefore of the same nature), as it is seen (that numerals denote beings of the same nature).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the same Kaṭḥavallī we read (I, 3, 1), &amp;lsquo;There are the two drinking the reward of their works in the world, (i.e. the body,) entered into the cave, dwelling on the highest summit. Those who know Brahman call them shade and light; likewise those householders who perform the Triṇāciketa sacrifice.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the distinctive qualities (mentioned).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the distinctive qualities mentioned in the text agree only with the individual Self and the highest Self. For in a subsequent passage (I, 3, 3), &amp;lsquo;Know the Self to be the charioteer, the body to be the chariot,&amp;rsquo; which contains the simile of the chariot, the individual soul is represented as a charioteer driving on through transmigratory existence and final release, while the passage (9), &amp;lsquo;He reaches the end of his journey, and that is the highest place of Vishṇu,&amp;rsquo; represents the highest Self as the goal of the driver&amp;rsquo;s course. And in a preceding passage also, (I, 2, 12, &amp;lsquo;The wise, who by means of meditation on his Self, recognises the Ancient who is difficult to be seen, who has entered into the dark, who is hidden in the cave, who dwells in the abyss, as God, he indeed leaves joy and sorrow far behind,&amp;rsquo;) the same two beings are distinguished as thinker and as object of thought. The highest Self is, moreover, the general topic. And further, the clause, &amp;lsquo;Those who know Brahman call them,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., which brings forward a special class of speakers, is in its place only if the highest Self is accepted (as one of the two beings spoken of). It is therefore evident that the passage under discussion refers to the individual soul and the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The person within (the eye) (is Brahman) on account of the agreement (of the attributes of that person with the nature of Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture says, &amp;lsquo;He spoke: The person that is seen in the eye that is the Self. This is the immortal, the fearless, this is Brahman. Even though they drop melted butter or water on it (the eye) it runs away on both sides,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Cḥ. Up. IV, 15, 1).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the statement of place, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how does the confined locality of the eye agree with Brahman which is omnipresent like the ether?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To this question we reply that there would indeed be a want of agreement if that one locality only were assigned to the Lord. For other localities also, viz. the earth and so on, are attributed to him in the passage, &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in the earth,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 3). And among those the eye also is mentioned, viz. in the clause, &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in the eye,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. The phrase &amp;lsquo;and so on,&amp;rsquo; which forms part of the Sūtra, intimates that not only locality is assigned to Brahman, although not (really) appropriate to it, but that also such things as name and form, although not appropriate to Brahman which is devoid of name and form, are yet seen to be attributed to it. That, in such passages as &amp;lsquo;His name is ut, he with the golden beard&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 6, 7, 6), Brahman although devoid of qualities is spoken of, for the purposes of devotion, as possessing qualities depending on name and form, we have already shown. And we have, moreover, shown that to attribute to Brahman&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the passage referring to that which is distinguished by pleasure (i.e. Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is, moreover, really no room for dispute whether Brahman be meant in the passage under discussion or not, because the fact of Brahman being meant is established &amp;lsquo;by the reference to that which is distinguished by pleasure.&amp;rsquo; For the same Brahman which is spoken of as characterised by pleasure in the beginning of the chapter &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, viz. in the clauses, &amp;lsquo;Breath is Brahman, Ka is Brahman, Kha is Brahman,&amp;rsquo; that same Brahman we must suppose to be referred to in the present passage also, it being proper to adhere to the subject-matter under discussion; the clause, &amp;lsquo;The teacher will tell you the way &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;rsquo; merely announcing that the way will be proclaimed [by the teacher; not that a new subject will be started].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the statement of the way of him who has heard the Upanishads.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The person placed in the eye is the highest lord for the following reason also. From śruti as well as smr̥ti we are acquainted with the way of him who has heard the Upanishads or the secret knowledge, i. e. who knows Brahman. That way, called the path of the gods, is described (Pra. Up. I, 10), &amp;lsquo;Those who have sought the Self by penance, abstinence, faith, and knowledge gain by the northern path the sun. This is the home of the spirits, the immortal, free from fear, the highest. From thence they do not return;&amp;rsquo; and also (Bha. Gītā VIII, 24), &amp;lsquo;Fire, light, the bright fortnight, the six months of the northern progress of the sun, on that way those who know Brahman go, when they have died, to Brahman.&amp;rsquo; Now that very same way is seen to be stated, in our text, for him who knows the person within the eye. For we read (Cḥ. Up. IV, 15, 5), &amp;lsquo;Now whether people perform obsequies for him or no he goes to light;&amp;rsquo; and later on, &amp;lsquo;From the sun (he goes) to the moon, from the moon to lightning. There is a person not human, he leads them to Brahman. This is the path of the gods, the path that leads to Brahman. Those who proceed on that path do not return to the life of man.&amp;rsquo; From this description of the way which is known to be the way of him who knows Brahman we ascertain that the person within the eye is Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;/&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The internal ruler over the devas and so on (is Brahman), because the attributes of that (Brahman) are designated.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Br̥. Up. III, 7, 1 ff. we read, &amp;lsquo;He who within rules this world and the other world and all beings,&amp;rsquo; and later on, &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in the earth and within the earth, whom&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the earth does not know, whose body the earth is, who rules the earth within, he is thy Self, the ruler within, the immortal,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. The entire chapter (to sum up its contents) speaks of a being, called the antaryāmin (the internal ruler), who, dwelling within, rules with reference to the gods, the world, the Veda, the sacrifice, the beings, the Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the internal ruler is) not that which the Smr̥ti assumes, (viz. the pradhāna,) on account of the statement of qualities not belonging to it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Good so far, a Sānkhya opponent resumes. The attributes, however, of not being seen, &amp;amp;c., belong also to the pradhāna assumed by the Sānkhya-smr̥ti, which is acknowledged to be devoid of form and other sensible qualities. For their&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Smr̥ti says, &amp;lsquo;Undiscoverable, unknowable, as if wholly in sleep&amp;rsquo; (Manu I, 5). To this pradhāna also the attribute of rulership belongs, as it is the cause of all effects. Therefore the internal ruler may be understood to denote the pradhāna. The pradhāna has, indeed, been set aside already by the Sūtra I, 1, 5, but we bring it forward again, because we find that attributes belonging to it, such as not being seen and the like, are mentioned in Scripture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the embodied soul (also cannot be understood by the internal ruler), for both also (i. e. both&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;recensions of the Br̥had Āraṇyaka) speak of it as different (from the internal ruler).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;rsquo;not&amp;rsquo; (in the Sūtra) has to be supplied from the preceding Sūtra. Although the attributes of seeing, &amp;amp;c., belong to the individual soul, still as the soul is limited by its adjuncts, as the ether is by a jar, it is not capable of dwelling completely within the earth and the other beings mentioned, and to rule them. Moreover, the followers of both śākhās, i.e. the Kāṇvas as well as the Mādhyandinas, speak in their texts of the individual soul as different from the internal ruler, viz. as constituting, like the earth, and so on, his abode and the object of his rule. The Kāṇvas read (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 22), &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in knowledge;&amp;rsquo; the Mādhyandinas, &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in the Self.&amp;rsquo; If the latter reading is adopted, the word &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo; denotes the individual soul; if the former, the individual soul is denoted by the word &amp;lsquo;knowledge;&amp;rsquo; for the individual soul consists of knowledge. It is therefore a settled matter that some being different from the individual soul, viz. the lord, is denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;internal ruler.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That which possesses the attributes of invisibility and so on (is Brahman), on account of the declaration of attributes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture says, &amp;lsquo;The higher knowledge is this by which the Indestructible is apprehended. That which cannot be seen nor seized, which is without origin and qualities, without eyes and ears, without hands and feet, the eternal, all-pervading, omnipresent, infinitesimal, that which is imperishable, that it is which the wise regard as the source of all beings&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 5; 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The two others (i.e. the individual soul and the pradhāna) are not (the source of all beings) because there are stated distinctive attributes and difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The source of all beings is the highest Lord, not either of the two others, viz. the pradhāna and the individual soul, on account of the following reason also. In the first place, the text distinguishes the source of all beings from the embodied soul, as something of a different nature; compare the passage (II, i, 2), &amp;lsquo;That heavenly person is without body, he is both without and within, not produced, without breath and without mind, pure.&amp;rsquo; The distinctive attributes mentioned here, such as being of a heavenly nature, and so on, can in no way belong to the individual soul,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of its form being mentioned.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently to the passage, &amp;lsquo;Higher than the high Imperishable,&amp;rsquo; we meet (in the passage, &amp;lsquo;From him is born breath,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.) with a description of the creation of all things, from breath down to earth, and then with a statement of the form of this same source of beings as consisting of all created beings, &amp;lsquo;Fire is his head, his eyes the sun and the moon, the quarters his ears, his speech the Vedas disclosed, the wind his breath, his heart the universe; from his feet came the earth; he is indeed the inner Self of all things.&amp;rsquo; This statement of form can refer only to the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vaiśvānara (is the highest Lord) on account of the distinction qualifying the common terms (Vaiśvānara and Self).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(In Cḥ. Up. V, 11 ff.) a discussion begins with the words, &amp;lsquo;What is our Self, what is Brahman?&amp;rsquo; and is carried on in the passage, &amp;lsquo;You know at present that Vaiśvānara Self, tell us that;&amp;rsquo; after that it is declared with reference to Heaven, sun, air, ether, water, and earth, that they are connected with the qualities of having good light, &amp;amp;c., and, in order to disparage devout meditation on them singly, that they stand to the Vaiśvānara in the relation of being his head, &amp;amp;c., merely; and then finally (V, 18) it is said, &amp;lsquo;But he who meditates on the Vaiśvānara Self as measured by a span, as abhivimāna &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, he eats food in all worlds, in all beings, in all Selfs. Of that Vaiśvānara Self the head is Sutejas (having good light), the eye Viśvarūpa (multiform), the breath Pr̥thagvartman (moving in various courses), the trunk Bahula (full), the bladder Rayi (wealth), the feet the earth, the chest the altar, the hairs the grass on the altar, the heart the Gārhapatya fire, the mind the Anvāhārya fire, the mouth the Āhavanīya fire.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(And) because that which is stated by Smr̥ti (i.e. the shape of the highest Lord as described by Smr̥ti) is an inference (i.e. an indicatory mark from which we infer the meaning of Śruti).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The highest Lord only is Vaiśvānara, for that reason also that Smr̥ti ascribes to the highest Lord only a shape consisting of the threefold world, the fire constituting his mouth, the heavenly world his head, &amp;amp;c. So, for instance, in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;He whose mouth is fire, whose head the heavenly world, whose navel the ether, whose feet the earth, whose eye the sun, whose ears the regions, reverence to him the Self of the world.&amp;rsquo; The shape described here in Smr̥ti allows us to infer a Śruti passage on which the Smr̥ti rests, and thus constitutes an inference, i.e. a sign indicatory of the word &amp;lsquo;Vaiśvānara&amp;rsquo; denoting the highest Lord. For, although the quoted Smr̥ti passage contains a glorification &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be maintained that (Vaiśvānara is) not (the highest Lord) on account of the term (viz. Vaiśvānara, having a settled different meaning), &amp;amp;c., and on account of his abiding within (which is a characteristic of the gastric fire); (we say) no, on account of the perception (of the highest Lord), being taught thus (viz. in the gastric fire), and on account of the impossibility (of the heavenly world, &amp;amp;c. being the head, &amp;amp;c. of the gastric fire), and because they (the Vājasaneyins) read of him (viz. the Vaiśvānara) as man (which term cannot apply to the gastric fire).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the following objection is raised.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For the same reasons (the Vaiśvānara) cannot be the divinity (of fire), or the element (of fire).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The averment that the fanciful attribution of members contained in the passage &amp;lsquo;His head is Sutejas,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. may apply to the elemental fire also which from the mantras is seen to be connected with the heavenly world, &amp;amp;c., or else to the divinity whose body is fire, on account of its power, is refuted by the following remark: For the reasons&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jaimini (declares that there is) no contradiction even on the assumption of a direct (worship of the highest Lord as Vaiśvānara).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Above (Sūtra 26) it has been said that Vaiśvānara is the highest Lord, to be meditated upon as having the gastric fire either for his outward manifestation or for his limiting condition; which interpretation was accepted in deference to the circumstance that he is spoken of as abiding within&amp;ndash;and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the manifestation, so Āśmarathya opines.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The circumstance of the highest Lord who transcends all measure being spoken of as measured by a span has for its reason &amp;lsquo;manifestation.&amp;rsquo; The highest Lord manifests&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;himself as measured by a span, i.e. he specially manifests himself for the benefit of his worshippers in some special places, such as the heart and the like, where he may be perceived. Hence, according to the opinion of the teacher Āśmarathya, the scriptural passage which speaks of him who is measured by a span may refer to the highest Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of remembrance; so Bādari opines.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else the highest Lord may be called &amp;lsquo;measured by a span&amp;rsquo; because he is remembered by means of the mind which is seated in the heart which is measured by a span. Similarly, barley-corns which are measured by means of prasthas are themselves called prasthas. It must be admitted that barley-grains themselves have a certain size which is merely rendered manifest through their being connected with a prastha measure; while the highest Lord himself does not possess a size to be rendered manifest by his connexion with the heart. Still the remembrance (of the Lord by means of the mind) may be accepted as offering a certain foundation for the Śruti passage concerning him who is measured by a span.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the ground of imaginative identification (the highest Lord may be called prādeśamātra), Jaimini thinks; for thus (Scripture) declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else the passage about him who is measured by a span may be considered to rest on imaginative combination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the passage of the Vājasaneyi-brāhmaṇa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;which treats of the same topic identifies heaven, earth, and so on&amp;ndash;which are the members of Vaiśvānara viewed as the Self of the threefold world&amp;ndash;with certain parts of the human frame, viz. the parts comprised between the upper part of the head and the chin, and thus declares the imaginative identity of Vaiśvānara with something whose measure is a span. There we read, &amp;lsquo;The Gods indeed reached him, knowing him as measured by a span as it were. Now I will declare them (his members) to you so as to identify him (the Vaiśvānara) with that whose measure is a span; thus he said. Pointing to the upper part of the head he said: This is what stands above (i.e. the heavenly world) as Vaiśvānara (i.e. the head of Vaiśvānara &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). Pointing to the eyes he said: This is he with good light (i.e. the sun) as Vaiśvānara (i.e. the eye of V.). Pointing to the nose he said: This is he who moves on manifold paths (i.e. the air) as Vaiśvānara (i.e. the breath of V.). Pointing to the space (ether) within his mouth he said: This is the full one (i.e. the ether) as Vaiśvānara. Pointing to the saliva within his mouth he said: This is wealth as Vaiśvānara (i.e. the water in the bladder of V.). Pointing to the chin he said: This is the base as Vaiśvānara (i.e. the feet of V.).&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moreover they (the Jābālas) speak of him&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(the highest Lord) in that (i.e. the interstice between the top of the head and the chin which is measured by a span).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover the Jābālas speak in their text of the highest Lord as being in the interstice between the top of the head and the chin. &amp;lsquo;The unevolved infinite Self abides in the avimukta (i.e. the non-released soul). Where does that avimukta abide? It abides in the Varaṇā and the Nāsī, in the middle. What is that Varaṇā, what is that Nāsī?&amp;rsquo; The text thereupon etymologises the term Varaṇā as that which wards off (vārayati) all evil done by the senses, and the term Nāsī as that which destroys (nāśayati) all evil done by the senses; and then continues, &amp;lsquo;And what is its place?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the impossibility (of contradictory attributes) in one thing, (the Jaina doctrine is) not (to be accepted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having disposed of the Bauddha doctrine we now turn to the system of the Gymnosophists (Jainas).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Jainas acknowledge seven categories (tattvas), viz. soul (jīva), non-soul (ajīva), the issuing outward (āsrava), restraint (saṁvara), destruction (nirjara), bondage (bandha), and release (moksha) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Shortly it may be said that they acknowledge two categories, viz. soul and non-soul, since the five other categories may be subsumed under these two.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And likewise (there results from the Jaina, doctrine) non-universality of the Self.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have hitherto urged against the Jaina doctrine an objection resulting from the syādvāda, viz. that one thing cannot have contradictory attributes. We now turn to the objection that from their doctrine it would follow that the individual Self is not universal, i.e. not omnipresent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Jainas are of opinion that the soul has the same size as the body. From this it would follow that the soul is not of infinite extension, but limited, and hence non-eternal like jars and similar things. Further, as the bodies of different classes of creatures are of different size, it might happen that the soul of a man&amp;ndash;which is of the size of the human body&amp;ndash;when entering, in consequence of its former deeds, on a new state of existence in the body of an elephant would not be able to fill the whole of it; or else that a human soul being relegated to the body of an ant would not be able to find sufficient room in it. The same difficulty would, moreover, arise with regard to the successive stages of one state of existence, infancy, youth, and old age.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nor is non-contradiction to be derived from the succession (of parts acceding to and departing from the soul), on account of the change, &amp;amp;c. (of the soul).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nor can the doctrine of the soul having the same size as the body be satisfactorily established by means of the hypothesis of the successive accession and withdrawal of particles. For this hypothesis would involve the soul&amp;rsquo;s undergoing changes and the like. If the soul is continually being repleted and depleted by the successive addition and withdrawal of parts, it of course follows that it undergoes change, and if it is liable to change it follows that it is non-permanent, like the skin and similar substances. From that, again, it follows that the Jaina doctrine of bondage and release is untenable; according to which doctrine &amp;rsquo;the soul, which in the state of bondage is encompassed by the ogdoad of works and sunk in the ocean of saṁsāra, rises when its bonds are sundered, as the gourd rises to the surface of the water when it is freed from the encumbering clay &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the permanency of the final (size of the soul) and the resulting permanency of the two (preceding sizes) there is no difference (of size, at any time).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the Jainas themselves admit the permanency of the final size of the soul which it has in the state of release. From this it follows also that its initial size and its intervening sizes must be permanent  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and that hence&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Lord (cannot be the cause of the world), on account of the inappropriateness (of that doctrine).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtrakāra now applies himself to the refutation of that doctrine, according to which the Lord is the cause of the world only in so far as he is the general ruler.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how do you know that that is the purport of the Sūtra (which speaks of the Lord &amp;lsquo;without any qualification&amp;rsquo;)?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the impossibility of the connexion (of the Lord with the souls and the pradhāna).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Against the doctrine which we are at present discussing there lies the further objection that a Lord distinct from the pradhāna and the souls cannot be the ruler of the latter without being connected with them in a certain way. But of what nature is that connexion to be? It cannot be conjunction (saṁyoga), because the Lord, as well as the pradhāna and the souls, is of infinite extent and devoid of parts. Nor can it be inherence, since it would be impossible to define who should be the abode and who the abiding thing. Nor is it possible to assume some other connexion, the special nature of which would have to be inferred from the effect, because the relation of cause and effect is just what is not settled as yet &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the impossibility of rulership (on the part of the Lord).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Lord of the argumentative philosophers is an untenable hypothesis, for the following reason also.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those philosophers are obliged to assume that by his influence the Lord produces action in the pradhāna, &amp;amp;c. just as the potter produces motion in the clay, &amp;amp;c. But this cannot be admitted; for the pradhāna, which is devoid of colour and other qualities, and therefore not an object of perception, is on that account of an altogether different nature from clay and the like, and hence cannot be looked upon as the object of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If you say that as the organs (are ruled by the soul so the pradhāna is ruled by the Lord), we deny that on account of the enjoyment, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, the opponent might reply, let us suppose that the Lord rules the pradhāna in the same way as the soul rules the organ of sight and the other organs which are devoid of colour, and so on, and hence not objects of perception.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (there would follow from that doctrine) either finite duration or absence of omniscience (on the Lord&amp;rsquo;s part).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis of the argumentative philosophers is invalid, for the following reason also.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They teach that the Lord is omniscient and of infinite duration, and likewise that the pradhāna, as well as the individual souls, is of infinite duration. Now, the omniscient Lord either defines the measure of the pradhāna, the souls, and himself, or does not define it. Both alternatives subvert the doctrine under discussion. For, on the former alternative, the pradhāna, the souls, and the Lord, being all of them of definite measure, must necessarily be of finite duration; since ordinary experience teaches that all things of definite extent, such as jars and the like, at some time cease to exist. The numerical measure of pradhāna, souls, and Lord is defined by their constituting a triad, and the individual measure of each of them must likewise be considered as defined by the Lord (because he is omniscient). The number of the souls is a high one &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. From among this limited number of souls some obtain release from the saṁsāra, that means their saṁsāra comes to an end, and their subjection to the samsāra comes to an end. Gradually all souls obtain release, and so there will finally be an end of the entire saṁsāra and the saṁsāra state of all souls. But the pradhāna which is ruled by the Lord and which modifies itself for the purposes of the soul is what is meant by saṁsāra. Hence, when the latter no longer exists, nothing is left for the Lord to rule, and his omniscience and ruling power have no longer any objects. But if the pradhāna, the souls, and the Lord, all have an end, it follows that they also have a beginning, and if they have a beginning as well as an end, we are driven to the doctrine of a general void.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the impossibility of the origination (of the individual soul from the highest Lord, the doctrine of the Bhāgavatas cannot be accepted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have, in what precedes, refuted the opinion of those who think that the Lord is not the material cause but only the ruler, the operative cause of the world. We are now going to refute the doctrine of those according to whom he is the material as well as the operative cause.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (it is) not (observed that) the instrument is produced from the agent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Bhāgavata hypothesis is to be rejected for that reason also, that observation never shows us an instrument, such as a hatchet and the like, to spring from an agent such as Devadatta, or any other workman. But the Bhāgavatas teach that from an agent, viz. the individual soul termed Sankarshaṇa, there springs its instrument, viz. the internal organ termed Pradyumna, and again from this offspring of the agent another instrument, viz. the ahankāra termed Aniruddha. Such doctrines cannot be settled without observed instances. And we do not meet with any scriptural passage in their favour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or (if) in consequence of the existence of knowledge, &amp;amp;c. (Vāsudeva, &amp;amp;c. be taken as Lords), yet there is non-exclusion of that (i.e. the objection raised in Sūtra 42).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us then&amp;ndash;the Bhāgavatas may say&amp;ndash;understand by Sankarshaṇa, and so on, not the individual soul, the mind, &amp;amp;c., but rather Lords, i.e. powerful beings distinguished by all the qualities characteristic of rulers, such as pre-eminence of knowledge and ruling capacity, strength, valour, glory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/2/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of contradictions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, manifold contradictions are met with in the Bhāgavata system, with reference to the assumption of qualities and their bearers. Eminence of knowledge and ruling capacity, strength, valour, and glory are enumerated as qualities, and then they are in some other place spoken of as Selfs, holy Vāsudevas, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we meet with passages contradictory of the Veda. The following passage, for instance, blames the Veda, &amp;lsquo;Not having found the highest bliss in the Vedas Śāṇḍilya. studied this śāstra.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
