<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Talks on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Talks on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/01_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/01_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>Shastriji always used to tell his followers that, it was difficult for him to put into words whatever thought that flowed in his mind while going through Yōgavāsiṣṭha as every word or a phrase or a sloka would push him to non doing state. Due to repeated requests from his close associates, he agreed to speak on a few topics in Yōgavāsiṣṭha. The recorded talks which were highly disjointed have been put into a readable format after much deliberation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE INWARD JOURNEY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/02_THE_INWARD_JOURNEY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/02_THE_INWARD_JOURNEY/</guid>
      <description>I HAVE DRAWN LESSONS FROM YŌGAVĀSIṢṬHA. Whatever is detailed out in the Upanishads is repeated here, as you must have seen by now. It is not possible for me to see anything other than what is in Upanishads. There is a huge repetition. Every second line in Yōgavāsiṣṭha talks about cetya versus cit. Any chapter, any sloka you see it is:
चेत्योनुसंधान रहितम् चिन्मात्रम्
cētyōnusaṁdhāna rahitam cinmātram.
चेत्यानुपात रहितम् चिन्मात्रम्</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 LAVAṆŌPĀKHYĀNAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/03_lavaNopAkhyAnam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/03_lavaNopAkhyAnam/</guid>
      <description>After dealing on the aspect of attaining a state of vairagya Yōgavāsiṣṭha opens with the idea of the importance of sravana and manana and goes on to describe the aspect of creation. Sage Vasishta however asserts that a true saadhaka has to concentrate more on the ways and means of getting out of the cycle of birth and death rather than think about the how and why of creation.
Shastriji opens his talk on the need to do manana and dwells very briefly on the aspect of creation as to how we are capable of creation when we are in the dream phase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 SAPTA-PADAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/04_SAPTA-PADAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/04_SAPTA-PADAM/</guid>
      <description>(SEVEN DESCENDING STEPS OF IGNORANCE)
After a detailed account on the play and control of the mind, sage Vasishta explains the seven states of ignorance, Saptapadām and also the seven states of ascent to wisdom, Saptabhūmikām. The first seven attempts are to clearly define the path to be avoided and the next seven are ascending paths to be nurtured leading one to the attainment of liberation from the shackles of life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 SAPTA-BHŪMIKĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/05_sapta-bhUmikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/05_sapta-bhUmikA/</guid>
      <description>(SEVEN ASCENDING STATES OF WISDOM)
AFTER GIVING DETAILED ACCOUNT OF SWAROOPA IN different ways Yogavasishta takes up the discussion on the aspect of sapta bhoomika, the seven steps or stages of evolvement of a peson. We will try to know about these seven steps in the path of yoga sadhana or svaroopa praapti, knowing ourselves. How these steps can be identified and adopted in the process of saadhana is the subject matter of discussion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 PRAHLĀDŌPĀKHYĀNAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/06_prahlAdopAkhyAnam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/06_prahlAdopAkhyAnam/</guid>
      <description>WE WILL TAKE UP A CHAPTER FROM UPASHAMA prakarana from Yōgavāsiṣṭha for our discussion and deliberate. The chapter is that of Prahlada.The purpose of our study is limited to the saadhana part and we are not interested in the story as such. How the text deliberates on the aspect of liberation and search for ‘Self’ is more important.
There is an interesting story of Prahlaada who is an established Vishnu bhakta and his bhakti, devotion was of that order that whenever he thought of the Lord, the Lord would appear before him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 BHUŚUṆḌŌPĀKHYĀNAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/07_bhushuNDopAkhyAnam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/07_bhushuNDopAkhyAnam/</guid>
      <description>HERE IS A CHAPTER WHICH SHOWS THE GROWTH OF spiritual level until one touches nirvana levels in the path of sadhana or even attain the state of jeevanmukti. Jeevanmukti is a concession to the position of nirvana. When a jeevanmukta winds up, whatever is the state of self or soul is nirvana, or liberation, never to get into the cycle of birth and death as sampradaya puts it. Of course I have an extreme view of mukti, being daring and radical.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 CONCLUSION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/08_CONCLUSION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/yoga-vAsiShTha-shAstram/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/talks/08_CONCLUSION/</guid>
      <description>To attain purushaartha, one has to give up ahankaara. The only way to do that is to control the chattering and outgoing mind which is solely responsible for all the misery.Shastriji concludes his lecture series, by dwelling on this aspect.
Editor अस्य संसार दुःखस्य सर्वोपद्रवकारिण:,
उपाय एक एव अस्ति मनसः स्वस्थ निग्रहः.
asya saṁsāra duḥkhasya sarvōpadravakāriṇaḥ,
upāya ēka ēva asti manasaḥ svastha nigrahaḥ.
(Y.V.4-4-1)
F
OR THE SORROW CAUSED BY THE TORMENTING worldly life, there is only one cure and that is the control of one’s mind.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
