<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 second pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-pāda&#34;&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Speech (is merged) in mind, on account of this being seen, and of the scriptural statement.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Being about to describe the path of the gods which leads those who possess the lower kind of knowledge towards the attainment of their reward, the Sūtrakāra begins by explaining, on the basis of scriptural statements, the successive steps by which the soul passes out of the body; for, as will be stated later on, the departure of the soul is the same in the case of him who possesses the (lower) knowledge and of him who is devoid of all knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And for the same reason all (sense-organs) (follow) after (mind).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Therefore he whose light has gone out comes to a new birth with his senses merged in the mind&amp;rsquo; (Pr. Up. III, 9); this passage states that all senses without difference are merged in the mind. &amp;lsquo;For the same reason,&amp;rsquo; i.e. because there also as in the case of speech, it is observed that the eye and so on discontinue their functions, while the mind together with its functions persists, and because the organs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That mind (is merged) in breath, owing to the subsequent clause.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been shown that the passage, &amp;lsquo;Speech is merged in mind,&amp;rsquo; means a merging of the function only.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt here arises whether the subsequent clause, &amp;lsquo;mind in breath,&amp;rsquo; also means to intimate a merging of the function only or of that to which the function belongs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains the latter alternative. For that, he says, agrees with scripture, and moreover breath may be viewed as the causal substance of mind. For scripture&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Mind is made of earth, breath of water&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 6, 5)&amp;ndash;states that mind comes from earth and breath from water, and scripture further states that &amp;lsquo;Water sent forth earth&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 4). When mind therefore is merged in breath, it is the same as earth being merged in water; for mind is earth and breath is water, causal substance and effect being non-different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That (viz. breath) (is merged) in the ruler (i.e. the individual soul), on account of the (statements as to the prāṇas) coming to it and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have ascertained that a thing which has not originated from another is not itself merged in the latter, but only through its functions. A doubt now arises whether, according to the word of scripture, the function of breath is merged in heat, or in the individual soul which is the ruler of the body and senses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To the elements (the soul, with prāṇa, goes), on account of the subsequent scriptural clause.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The soul joined by the prāṇa takes up its abode within the subtle elements which accompany heat and form the seed of the (gross) body. This we conclude from the clause, &amp;lsquo;Breath in heat.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But this passage declares, not that the soul together with the prāṇa takes up its abode in heat, but only that the prāṇa takes up its abode!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not to one (element) (the soul goes); for both (i.e. scripture and Smr̥ti) declare this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the time of passing over into another body the individual soul does not abide in the one element of heat only; for we see that the new body consists of various elements. This matter is declared in the question and answer about the waters called man (Cḥ. Up. V, 3, 3); as explained by us in III, 1, 2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And common (to him who knows and him who does not know) (is the departure) up to the beginning of the way; and the immortality (of him who knows) (is relative only) without having burned (nescience and so on).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question here arises whether the departure of the soul, as described hitherto, is the same in the case of him who knows and him who is destitute of knowledge; or whether there is any difference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This (aggregate of the elements) (continues to exist) up to the (final absolute) union (with Brahman); on account of the declarations of the saṁsāra state (made by scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to the final clause, &amp;lsquo;Heat in the highest deity,&amp;rsquo; the force of its connexion with what precedes shows that the meaning is &amp;rsquo;the heat of the dying man is&amp;ndash;together with the individual soul, the prāṇa, the aggregate of the organs and the other elements&amp;ndash;merged in Brahman.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (heat is) subtle in measure; as this is thus observed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The elementary matter of heat and the other elements&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;which form the substratum for the soul when passing out of this body, must be subtle in its nature and extent. This follows from the scriptural passages, which declare that it passes out by the veins and so on. Their thinness renders them capable of passing out, and their transparency (permeability) is the cause of their not being stopped by any gross substance. For these reasons they, when passing out of the body, are not perceived by bystanders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For this reason (it is) not (destroyed) by the destruction (of the gross body).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of this very subtlety the subtle body is not destroyed by what destroys the gross body, viz. burning and the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And to that same (subtle body) that warmth (belongs), on account of the proof (which observation furnishes).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To that same subtle body belongs the warmth which we perceive in the living body by means of touch. That warmth is not felt in the body after death, while such qualities as form, colour and so on continue to be perceived; it is on the other hand, observed as long as there is life. From this it follows that the warmth resides in something different from the body as ordinarily known. Scripture also says, &amp;lsquo;He is warm if going to live, cold if going to die.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Should you say that on account of the denial (made by scripture) (the soul of him who knows Brahman does not depart); we deny this, (because scripture means to say that the prāṇas do not depart) from the embodied soul.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the distinction conveyed by the clause, &amp;lsquo;and (relative) immortality without having burned&amp;rsquo; (Sūtra 7), it follows that in the case of absolute immortality being reached there is no going and no departure of the soul from the body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For (in the text) of some (the denial of the soul&amp;rsquo;s departure) is clear.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The assertion that also the soul of him who knows Brahman departs from the body, because the denial states the soul (not the body) to be the point of departure, cannot be upheld. For we observe that in the sacred text of some there is a clear denial of a departure, the starting-point of which is the body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And Smr̥ti also says that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Mahābhārata also it is said that those who know do not go or depart, &amp;lsquo;He who has become the Self of all beings and has a complete intuition of all, at his way the gods themselves are perplexed, seeking for the path of him who has no path.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection is raised, other passages speak of men knowing Brahman as going, so e.g. &amp;lsquo;Śuka the son of Vyāsa being desirous of release travelled to the sphere of the sun; being called by his father who had followed him, he gave an answering shout.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Those (elements, &amp;amp;c.) (are merged) in the highest Brahman; for thus (scripture) says.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those, i.e. the sense organs&amp;ndash;denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;prāṇa&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;and the elements of him who knows the highest Brahman, are merged in that same highest Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because scripture declares that &amp;lsquo;Thus these sixteen parts of the spectator that go towards the person, when they have reached the person, sink into him&amp;rsquo; (Pr. Up. VI, 5).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But another text which refers to him who knows teaches that the parts also are merged in something different from the highest Self, &amp;lsquo;The fifteen parts enter into their elements&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, 2, 7).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(There is absolute) non-division (from Brahman, of the parts merged in it); according to scriptural declaration.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the parts of him who knows are merged in Brahman, is there a remainder (which is not so merged), as in the case of other men; or is there no such remainder? As the merging of him also who knows falls under the general heading of merging, it might be assumed that of him also there remains a potential body, and the Sūtrakāra therefore teaches expressly that the elements, &amp;amp;c., of him who knows enter into the relation of (absolute) non-division from Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(There takes place) a lighting up of the point of its (the soul&amp;rsquo;s) abode (viz. the heart); the door (of its egress) being illuminated thereby; owing to the power of knowledge and the application of meditation to the way which is part of that (knowledge); (the soul) favoured by him in the heart (viz. Brahman) (passes upwards) by the one that exceeds a hundred (i.e. by the hundred and first vein).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having absolved the inquiry into a point of the higher knowledge into which we were led by a special occasion, we now continue the discussion connected with the lower knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The soul after having passed forth from the body) follows the rays.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is the vidyā of him within the heart, which begins, &amp;lsquo;There is this city of Brahman and in it the palace, the small lotus, and in it that small ether&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 1, 1). A subsequent section of that chapter&amp;ndash;beginning with the words, &amp;lsquo;Now these veins of the heart&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;describes at length the connexion of the veins and the rays, and the text then continues, &amp;lsquo;When he departs from this body, he departs upwards by those very rays,&amp;rsquo; and further on, &amp;lsquo;By that&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Should it be said that the soul does) not (follow the rays) by night; (we reply) not so, because the connexion (of veins and rays) exists as long as the body; and (scripture) also declares this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It might perhaps be said that the veins and rays are connected during the day, so that the soul of a person who dies during the day may follow those rays; but not the soul of one who dies by night when the connexion of the veins and rays is broken.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And for the same reason (the departed soul follows the rays) also during the southern progress of the sun.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the same reason, viz. because waiting is impossible, and because the fruit of knowledge is not a merely eventual one, and because the time of death is not fixed, also that possessor of true knowledge who dies during the southern progress of the sun obtains the fruit of his knowledge. Because dying during the northern progress of the sun is more excellent, and because Bhīshma is known to have waited for that period, and because scripture says, &amp;lsquo;From the light half of the month (they go) to the six months when the sun goes to the north,&amp;rsquo; it might be thought that the northern progress of the sun is needful for dying. This notion the Sūtra refutes. The greater excellence of the sun&amp;rsquo;s northern progress applies to those only who do not possess the highest knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/2/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(These details) are recorded by Smr̥ti with reference to the Yogins; and both (Sāṅkhya and Yoga) are Smr̥ti (only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rules as to dying by day and so on in order not to return are given by Smr̥ti for the Yogins only. And those two, viz. Yoga and Sāṅkhya are mere Smr̥ti, not of scriptural character. As thus it has a different sphere of application and is based on a special kind of authority, the Smr̥ti rule as to the time of dying has no influence on knowledge based on scripture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
