<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 third pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-pāda&#34;&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the road beginning with light (the departed soul proceeds), on account of that being widely known.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been explained that up to the beginning of the way, the departure is the same. About the way itself, however, different texts make different declarations. One passage describes it as constituted by the junction of the veins and rays, &amp;lsquo;Then he mounts upwards by just those rays&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 6, 5), Another passage describes it as beginning with light, &amp;lsquo;They go to the light, from light to day&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 10, 1). Another way is described, Kau. Up. I, 3, &amp;lsquo;Having reached the path of the gods, he comes to the world of Agni.&amp;rsquo; Another, Br̥. Up. V, 10, 1, &amp;lsquo;When the person goes away from this world, he comes to the wind.&amp;rsquo; Another again. Mu. Up. I, 2, 11, &amp;lsquo;Free from passions they depart through the gate of the sun.&amp;rsquo; A doubt here arises whether these ways are different from each other, or whether there is only one road of which the different texts mention different particulars.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;From the year to Vāyu; on account of the absence and presence of specification.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But by what special combination can we establish between&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the different attributes of the road the relation of what is determined by attributes and of determining attributes? The teacher out of kindness to us connects them as follows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Kaushītakins describe the road of the gods as follows, &amp;lsquo;Having reached the path of the gods he comes to the world of Agni, to the world of Vāyu, to the world of Varuṇa, to the world of Indra, to the world of Prajāpati, to the world of Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. I, 3). Now the world of Agni means the same as light, since both terms denote burning, and we therefore need not, with regard to them, search for the order in which they are to be combined. Vāyu, on the other hand, is not mentioned in the road beginning with light; in what place then is he to be inserted?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Beyond lightning (there is) Varuṇa, on account of the connexion (of the two).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Cḥāndogya continues, &amp;lsquo;From Āditya to the moon, from the moon to lightning.&amp;rsquo; Here Varuṇa (mentioned in the Kaushītaki-upan.) has to be brought in so that above that lightning he goes to the world of Varuṇa. For there is a connexion between lightning and Varuṇa; the broad lightnings dance forth from the womb of the clouds with the sound of deep thunder, and then water falls down. And a Brāhmaṇa also says, &amp;lsquo;It lightens, it thunders, it will rain&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 11, 1). But the lord of all water is Varuṇa, as known from Śruti and Smr̥ti.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(They are) conductors, this being indicated.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to those beginning with light a doubt arises whether they are marks of the road, or places of enjoyment, or leaders of the travelling souls.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first possible view of the question is that light and so on are marks of the road, because the instruction has that character. For as in ordinary life a man wishing to go to a village or a town is told, &amp;lsquo;Go from here to that hill, from there to a fig-tree, from that to a river, from that to a village; after that you will reach the town;&amp;rsquo; so here the text also says, &amp;lsquo;from light to day, from day to the waxing half of the month,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(There are personal conductors) because that is established on the ground of both (i.e. road and travellers) being bewildered (i.e. unconscious).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As, owing to their separation from a body, the organs of those who go on the road beginning with light are wrapped up, they are incapable of ruling themselves; and the light &amp;amp;c., as they are without intelligence, are equally incapable. Hence it follows that the particular intelligent deities who represent light and the rest are appointed to the conductorship. For in ordinary life also drunken or senseless people whose sense-organs are wrapped up follow a road as commanded by others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;From thence (the souls are led) by him only who belongs to the lightning; the sacred text stating that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From thence, i.e. after they have come to the lightning they go to the world of Brahman, being led through the worlds of Varuṇa and the rest by the person, not a man, who follows immediately after the lightning. For that that person leads them is stated in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;When they have reached the place of lightning a person, not a man, leads them to the world of Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. VI, 2, 15). Varuṇa and the rest, we must understand, favour them either by not hindering or somehow assisting them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To the effected (Brahman) (the souls are led); (thus opines) Bādari; because going to him is possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to the passage, &amp;lsquo;He leads them to Brahman.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the doubt arises whether that person leads the souls to the effected, lower, Brahman, or to the highest, non-modified, chief Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whence the doubt?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the (ambiguous) word Brahman is used, and because scripture speaks of going.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The opinion of the teacher Bādari is that the person, who is not a man, leads them to the lower, qualified, effected Brahman; because it is possible to go to that. For the effected Brahman which occupies a definite place can be the goal of a journey. With the highest Brahman, on the other hand, we cannot connect the ideas of one who goes, or object of going, or act of going; for that Brahman is present everywhere and is the inner Self of all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (the Brahman to which the Souls are led) being qualified (in another passage).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the soul&amp;rsquo;s going has for its object the effected Brahman, we conclude from another scriptural passage also which qualifies Brahman in a certain way, &amp;lsquo;He leads them to the worlds of Brahman; in these worlds of Brahman they live for ever and ever&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. VI, 2, 15). For it would be impossible to qualify the highest Brahman by means of the plural number (&amp;lsquo;worlds&amp;rsquo;); while the plural number may be applied to the lower Brahman which may abide in different conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of its proximity (to the higher Brahman) there is designation (of the lower Brahman) as that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; indicates the setting aside of the doubt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the lower Brahman is in proximity to the higher one, there is nothing unreasonable in the word &amp;lsquo;Brahman&amp;rsquo; being applied to the former also. For when the higher Brahman is, for the purposes of pious meditation, described as possessing certain effected qualities&amp;ndash;such as consisting of mind and the rest&amp;ndash;which qualities depend on its connexion with certain pure limiting adjuncts; then it is what we call the lower Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the passing away of the effected (world of Brahman) (the souls go) together with the ruler of that (world) to what is higher than that; on account of scriptural declaration.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the reabsorption of the effected Brahman world draws near, the souls in which meanwhile perfect knowledge has sprung up proceed, together with Hiraṇyagarbha the ruler of that world, to &amp;lsquo;what is higher than that i.e. to the pure highest place of Vishnu. This is the release by successive steps which we have to accept on the basis of the scriptural declarations about the non-return of the souls. For we have shown that the Highest cannot be directly reached by the act of going.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Smr̥ti also agrees with this view; cp. the following passage, &amp;lsquo;When the pralaya has come and the end of the highest (i.e. Hiraṇyagarbha), then they all, together with Brahman, with purified minds enter the highest place.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The final conclusion (siddhānta) therefore is that the going of the souls, of which scripture speaks, has for its goal the effected Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But what is the primā facie view, with regard to which this final conclusion has been established in Sutras 7-11?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To the highest (Brahman) (the souls are led); Jaimini (opines); owing to this being the principal sense (of the word &amp;lsquo;Brahman&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The teacher Jaimini is of opinion that the passage, &amp;lsquo;He leads them to Brahman,&amp;rsquo; refers to the highest Brahman. For the highest Brahman constitutes the principal, primary sense, of the word &amp;lsquo;Brahman,&amp;rsquo; which denotes the lower Brahman only in a secondary, metaphorical way. And where both senses are possible, the primary sense has to be preferred.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because scripture declares that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The text, &amp;lsquo;Going upwards by that he reaches immortality,&amp;rsquo; declares that immortality is reached by going. But immortality is possible only in the highest Brahman, not in the effected one, because the latter is transitory. So scripture says, &amp;lsquo;Where one sees something else, that is little, that is mortal&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 24, 1). According to the text of the Kaṭḥa-upanishad also the going of the soul is towards the highest Brahman; for after the highest Brahman has been introduced there as general subject-matter&amp;ndash;in the passage, &amp;lsquo;That which thou seest,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., I, 2, 14, no other kind of knowledge is taken up later on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the intention of entering (can) not (be referred) to the effected (Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover the intention of entering into which is expressed&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in the passage, &amp;lsquo;I enter the hall of Prajāpati, the house&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 14, 1), cannot have the lower Brahman for its object. For the immediately preceding passage, &amp;lsquo;That within which these forms and names are contained is the Brahman,&amp;rsquo; shows that the highest Brahman, different in nature from the effected one, is the general subject-matter; and the subsequent passage, &amp;lsquo;I am the glory of the Brāhmans,&amp;rsquo; represents the soul as the Self of all; it being known from another scriptural passage that &amp;lsquo;Glory&amp;rsquo; is a name of the highest Brahman, &amp;lsquo;There is no likeness of him whose name is great glory&amp;rsquo; (Vāj. Saṁh. XXXII, 3). And in the vidyā of Brahman within the heart it is said of this same entering the house that it is preceded by going &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &amp;lsquo;There is the city of Brahman Aparājitā, and the golden hall built by Prabhu&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 5, 3). And that the performing of a journey is intended follows also from the use of the verb &amp;lsquo;pad,&amp;rsquo; which denotes going (prapadye, I enter).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Those who do not take their stand on symbols he leads, thus Bādarāyaṇa (opines); there being no fault in the twofold relation (resulting from this opinion); and the meditation on that (i.e. Brahman) (is the reason of this twofold relation).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is a settled conclusion that all going has reference to the effected Brahman, not to the highest Brahman. Another doubt now arises here. Does that person who is not a man lead to the world of Brahman all those who take their stand on the effected Brahman, without any difference; or only some of them?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/3/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And scripture declares a difference (in the case of meditations on symbols).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reference to the meditations on symbols, such as name and so on, scripture declares that each following meditation has a different result from the preceding one, &amp;lsquo;As far as name reaches he is lord and master;&amp;ndash;speech is greater than name;&amp;ndash;as far as speech reaches he is lord and master;&amp;ndash;mind is greater than speech&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 1, ff.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
