<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 SUKHA-DUḤKHA PARĪKṣA on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 SUKHA-DUḤKHA PARĪKṣA on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 DUḤKHA PARĪKṣA (EXAMINATION OF SUFFERING)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/01_dukha_parIxa_EXAMINATION_OF_SUFFERING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/01_dukha_parIxa_EXAMINATION_OF_SUFFERING/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us take up duḥkha parīkṣa to start with and later on go to sukha parīkṣa. What is Duḥkha parīkṣa? Take any duḥkha moment and see what the cittasthiti is. That’s all. Every day we have many moments of duḥkha. Observe what is the state of the mind at that time? Take the case of the day previous to the examination results of a student. The parents of the person are anxious and the student is anxious. The student’s interest is either to get into the computer science course or to get into the medical course, because they are the highest paying jobs. Just imagine the state of parent’s mind or the student’s mind and identify yourself with that situation. Oh! Would I get my first class? Will I lose that? All my plans will be broken if I don’t get it. Would it be a donation seat? Or would it be a seat earned on merit? What then? What are the alternatives? I have such high expectations about the result.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 SUKHA PARĪKṣA (HAPPINESS ANALYSED)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/02_SUKHA_parIxa_HAPPINESS_ANALYSED/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/03_sukha-dukha_parIxa/02_SUKHA_parIxa_HAPPINESS_ANALYSED/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now let us examine the concept of Sukha as understood by our R̥ṣi-s. One may say that Duḥkharāhitya or absence of Duḥkha is not Sukha. It is the general notion that Sukha is positive and comes from:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Objects of enjoyment – Bhogasukha- Enjoyment derived through the five senses – sense of vision, hearing, smell, taste and touch.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Social Service – serving the poor, disabled, economically challenged etc. It may be any activity – either trivial or profound.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Job satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Satisfaction in one’s profession.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Achieving name and fame in society.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All the above give you positive feeling. So, what is there to examine? Why at all we should bother about investigating Sukha? The experience of almost all of us, especially the persons who are internally sensitive, is that there is saturation in every kind of worldly Sukha/happiness. Everything becomes stale at some point of time or the other. Hence, the search for everlasting happiness or pure ānanda or śāśvatasukha becomes necessary. Unfortunately we are all searching for this in the outside world. Here comes Vedānta to our rescue and asks us to investigate any moment of happiness, &lt;u&gt;content wise and not agency wise.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
