<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 second pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-pāda&#34;&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the intermediate place there is (a real) creation; for (scripture) says (that).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding pāda we have set forth, with reference to the knowledge of the five fires, the various stages of the soul&amp;rsquo;s passing through the saṁsāra. We shall now set forth the soul&amp;rsquo;s different states (waking, dreaming, &amp;amp;c.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture says (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 9; 10), &amp;lsquo;When he falls asleep&amp;ndash;; there are no chariots in that state, no horses, no roads, but he himself creates chariots, horses, and roads,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And some (state the Self to be) the shaper (creator); sons and so on (being the lovely things which he shapes).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover the members of one śākhā state that the Self is, in that intermediate state, the shaper of lovely things, &amp;lsquo;He, the person who is awake in us while we are asleep, shaping one lovely thing after another&amp;rsquo; (Ka. Up. II, 5, 8).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kāma (lovely things) in this passage means sons, &amp;amp;c., that are so called because they are beloved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But it (viz. the dream world) is mere illusion (māyā), on account of its nature not manifesting itself with the totality (of the attributes of reality).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; discards the pūrvapaksha. It is not true that the world of dreams is real; it is mere illusion and there is not a particle of reality in it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;On account of its nature not manifesting itself with the totality,&amp;rsquo; i.e. because the nature of the dream world does not manifest itself with the totality of the attributes of real things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Not altogether) for it (the dream) is indicative (of the future), according to null; the experts also declare this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well then, as dreams are mere illusion, they do not contain a particle of reality?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Not so, we reply; for dreams are prophetic of future good and bad fortune. For scripture teaches as follows, &amp;lsquo;When a man engaged in some work undertaken for a special wish sees in his dreams a woman, he may infer success from that dream-vision.&amp;rsquo; Other scriptural passages declare that certain dreams indicate speedy death, so, e.g. &amp;lsquo;If he sees a black man with black teeth, that man will kill him.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But by the meditation on the highest that which is hidden (viz. the equality of the Lord and&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the soul, becomes manifest); for from him (the Lord) are its (the soul&amp;rsquo;s) bondage and release.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, but the individual soul is a part of the highest Self as the spark is a part of the fire. And as fire and spark have in common the powers of burning and giving light, so the individual soul and the Lord have in common the powers of knowledge and rulership; hence the individual soul may, by means of its lordship, effect in the dreaming state a creation of chariots and the like, springing from its wishes (saṁkalpa).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or that (viz. the concealment of the soul&amp;rsquo;s powers springs) from its connexion with the body.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But if the soul is a part of the highest Self, why should its knowledge and lordship be hidden? We should rather&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;expect them to be as manifest as the light and the heat of the spark.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;True, we reply; but the state of concealment of the soul&amp;rsquo;s knowledge and lordship is due to its being joined to a body, i.e. to a body, sense-organs, mind, buddhi, sense-objects, sensations, &amp;amp;c. And to this state of things there applies the simile: As the heat and light of the fire are hidden as long as the fire is still hidden in the wood from which it will be produced by friction, or as long as it is covered by ashes; so, in consequence of the soul being connected with limiting adjuncts in the form of a body, &amp;amp;c., founded on name and form as presented by Nescience, its knowledge and lordship remain hidden as long as it is possessed by the erroneous notion of not being distinct from those adjuncts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The absence of that (i.e. of dreams, i.e. dreamless sleep) takes place in the nāḍīs and in the Self; according to scriptural statement.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The state of dream has been discussed; we are now going to enquire into the state of deep sleep. A number of scriptural passages refer to that state. In one place we read, &amp;lsquo;When a man is asleep, reposing and at perfect rest so that he sees no dream, then he has entered into those nāḍīs&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 6, 3). In another place it is said with reference to the nāḍīs, &amp;lsquo;Through them he moves forth and rests in the surrounding body&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 1, 19). So also in another place, &amp;lsquo;In these the person is when sleeping he sees no dream. Then he becomes one with the prāṇa alone&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. IV, 20). Again in another place, &amp;lsquo;That ether which is within the heart in that he reposes&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22). Again, &amp;lsquo;Then he becomes united with that which is; he is gone to his Self (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, i). And, &amp;lsquo;Embraced by the highest Self (prājña) he knows nothing that is without, nothing that is within&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 21). Here the doubt arises whether the nāḍīs, &amp;amp;c., mentioned in the above passages are independent from each other and constitute various places for the soul in the state of deep sleep, or if they stand in mutual relation so as to constitute one such place only. The pūrvapakshin takes the former view on account of the various places mentioned serving one and the same purpose. Things serving the same purpose, as, e.g. rice and barley &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, are never seen to be dependent&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hence the awaking from that (viz. Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And because the Self only is the place of deep sleep, on that account the scriptural chapters treating of sleep invariably teach that the awaking takes place from that Self. In the Br̥. Up. when the time comes for the answer to the question, &amp;lsquo;Whence did he come back?&amp;rsquo; (II, 1, 16) the text&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;says, &amp;lsquo;As small sparks come forth from fire, thus all prāṇas come forth from that Self (II, 1, 20). And Cḥ. Up. VI, 10, 2, we read: &amp;lsquo;When they have come back from the True they do not know that they have come back from the True.&amp;rsquo; If there were optional places to which the soul might resort in deep sleep, scripture would teach us that it awakes sometimes from the nāḍīs, sometimes from the pericardium, sometimes from the Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the same (soul returns from Brahman); on account of work, remembrance, text, and precept.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here we have to enquire whether the soul when awaking from the union with Brahman is the same which entered into union with Brahman, or another one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that there is no fixed rule on that point. For just as a drop of water, when poured into a large quantity of water, becomes one with the latter, so that when we again take out a drop it would be hard to manage that it should be the very same drop: thus the sleeping soul, when it has become united with Brahman, is merged in bliss and not able again to rise from it the same. Hence what actually awakes is either the Lord or some other soul.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In him who is senseless (in a swoon, &amp;amp;c.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there is half-union; on account of this remaining (as the only possible hypothesis).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There now arises the question of what kind that state is which ordinarily is called a swoon or being stunned. Here the pūrvapakshin maintains that we know only of three states of the soul as long as it abides in a body, viz. the waking state, dreaming, and deep dreamless sleep; to which may be added, as a fourth state, the soul&amp;rsquo;s passing out of the body. A fifth state is known neither from Śruti nor Smr̥ti; hence what is called fainting must be one of the four states mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not on account of (difference of) place also twofold characteristics can belong to the highest; for everywhere (scripture teaches it to be without any difference).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now attempt to ascertain, on the ground of Śruti, the nature of that Brahman with which the individual soul becomes united in the state of deep sleep and so on, in consequence of the cessation of the limiting adjuncts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The scriptural passages which refer to Brahman are of a double character; some indicate that Brahman is affected by difference, so, e.g. &amp;lsquo;He to whom belong all works, all desires, all sweet odours and tastes&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 14,2); others, that it is without difference, so, e.g. &amp;lsquo;It is neither coarse nor fine, neither short nor long,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 8). Have we, on the ground of these passages, to assume that Brahman&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be objected that it is not so, on account of the difference (taught by the Veda); we reply that it is not so on account of the declaration of (Brahman)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;being not such, with reference to each (declaration of difference).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let this be, but nevertheless it cannot be maintained that Brahman is devoid of difference and attributes, and does not possess double attributes either in itself or on account of difference of station.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some also (teach) thus.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The members of one śākhā also make a statement about the cognition of non-difference which is preceded by a censure of the perception of difference, &amp;lsquo;By the mind alone it is to be perceived, there is in it no diversity. He who perceives therein any diversity goes from death to death&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 19). Others also (&amp;lsquo;By knowing the enjoyer, the enjoyed, and the ruler, everything has been declared to be threefold, and this is Brahman,&amp;rsquo; Svet. Up. I, 12)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For (Brahman) is merely devoid of form, on account of this being the main purport of scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahman, we must definitively assert, is devoid of all form, colour, and so on, and does not in any way possess form, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;On account of this being the main purport (of scripture).&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo; It is neither coarse nor fine, neither short nor long&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 8); &amp;lsquo;That which is without sound, without touch, without form, without decay&amp;rsquo; (Ka. Up. I, 3, 15); &amp;lsquo;He who is called ether is the revealer of all forms and names. That within which forms and names are, that is Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 14, 1); &amp;lsquo;That heavenly person is without body, he is both without and within, not produced&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 1, 2); &amp;lsquo;That Brahman is without cause and without effect, without anything inside or outside, this Self is Brahman, omnipresent and omniscient&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 5, 19). These and similar passages have for their purport the true nature of Brahman as non-connected with any world, and have not any other purport, as we have proved under I, 1, 4. On the ground of such passages we therefore must definitively conclude that Brahman is devoid of form. Those other passages, on the other hand, which refer to a Brahman qualified by form do not aim at setting forth the nature of Brahman, but rather at enjoining the worship of Brahman. As long as those latter texts do not contradict those of the former class, they are to be accepted as they stand; where, however, contradictions occur, the passages whose main subject is Brahman must be viewed as having greater force than those of the other kind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And as light (assumes forms as it were by its contact with things possessing form, so does Brahman;) since (the texts ascribing form to Brahman) are not devoid of meaning.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Just as the light of the sun or the moon after having passed through space enters into contact with a finger or some other limiting adjunct, and, according as the latter is straight or bent, itself becomes straight or bent as it were; so Brahman also assumes, as it were, the form of the earth and the other limiting adjuncts with which it enters into connexion. Hence there is no reason why certain texts should not teach, with a view to meditative worship, that Brahman has that and that form. We thus escape the conclusion that those Vedic passages which ascribe form to Brahman are devoid of sense; a conclusion altogether unacceptable since all parts of the Veda are equally authoritative, and hence must all be assumed to have a meaning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (scripture) declares (Brahman) to consist of that (i.e. intelligence).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And scripture declares that Brahman consists of intelligence, is devoid of any other characteristics, and is altogether without difference; &amp;lsquo;As a mass of salt has neither inside nor outside, but is altogether a mass of taste, thus, indeed, has that Self neither inside nor outside, but is altogether&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a mass of knowledge&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 13). That means: That Self has neither inside nor outside any characteristic form but intelligence; simple non-differentiated intelligence constitutes its nature; just as a lump of salt has inside as well as outside one and the same saltish taste, not any other taste.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(This scripture) also shows, and it is likewise stated in Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That Brahman is without any difference is proved by those scriptural passages also which expressly deny that it possesses any other characteristics; so, e.g. &amp;lsquo;Next follows the teaching by No, no&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 3, 6); &amp;lsquo;It is different from the known, it is also above the unknown&amp;rsquo; (Ke. Up. I, 4); &amp;lsquo;From whence all speech, with the mind, turns away unable to reach it&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 9). Of a similar purport is that scriptural passage which relates how Bāhva, being questioned about Brahman by Vashkalin, explained it to him by silence, &amp;lsquo;He said to him, &amp;ldquo;Learn Brahman, O friend,&amp;rdquo; and became silent. Then, on a second and third question, he replied, &amp;ldquo;I am teaching you indeed, but you do not understand. Silent is that Self.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rsquo; The same teaching is conveyed by those Smr̥ti-texts which deny of Brahman all other characteristics; so, e.g. &amp;lsquo;I will proclaim that which is the object of knowledge, knowing which one reaches immortality; the highest Brahman without either beginning or end, which cannot be said either to be or not to be&amp;rsquo; (Bha. Gītā XIII, 12). Of a similar purport is another Smr̥ti-passage, according to which the omniform Nārāyaṇa instructed Nārada, &amp;lsquo;The cause, O Nārada, of your seeing me endowed with the qualities of all beings is the Māyā emitted by me; do not cognize me as being such (in reality).&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For this very reason (there are applied to Brahman) comparisons such as that of the images of the sun and the like.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because that Self is of the nature of intelligence, devoid of all difference, transcending speech and mind, to be&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;described only by denying of it all other characteristics, therefore the Moksha Śāstras compare it to the images of the sun reflected in the water and the like, meaning thereby that all difference in Brahman is unreal, only due to its limiting conditions. Compare, e.g. out of many, the two following passages: &amp;lsquo;As the one luminous sun when entering into relation to many different waters is himself rendered multiform by his limiting adjuncts; so also the one divine unborn Self;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;The one Self of all beings separately abides in all the individual beings; hence it appears one and many at the same time, just as the one moon is multiplied by its reflections in the water.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But there is no parallelism (of the two things compared), since (in the case of Brahman) there is not apprehended (any separate substance) comparable to the water.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since no substance comparable to the water is apprehended in the case of Brahman, a parallelism between Brahman and the reflected images of the sun cannot be established. In the case of the sun and other material luminous bodies, there exists a separate material substance occupying a different place, viz. water; hence the light of the sun, &amp;amp;c., may be reflected. The Self, on the other hand, is not a material thing, and, as it is present everywhere and all is identical with it, there are no limiting adjuncts different from it and occupying a different place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Since (the highest Brahman) is inside (of the limiting adjuncts), it participates in their increase and decrease; owing to the appropriateness (thus resulting) of the two (things compared) it is thus (i.e. the comparison holds good).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The parallel instance (of the sun&amp;rsquo;s reflection in the water) is unobjectionable, since a common feature&amp;ndash;with reference to which alone the comparison is instituted&amp;ndash;does exist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whenever two things are compared, they are so only with reference to some particular point they have in common. Entire equality of the two can never be demonstrated; indeed if it could be demonstrated there would be an end of that particular relation which gives rise to the comparison. Nor does the sūtrakāra institute the comparison objected to on his own account; he merely sets forth the purport of a comparison actually met with in scripture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the declaration (of scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture moreover declares that the highest Brahman enters into the body and the other limiting adjuncts, &amp;lsquo;He made bodies with two feet, he made bodies with four feet. Having first become a bird he entered the bodies as purusha&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 5, 18); and &amp;lsquo;Having entered into them with this living (individual) Self&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 3, 2).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For all these reasons the comparison set forth in Sutra 18 is unobjectionable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For (the clause &amp;lsquo;Not so, not so&amp;rsquo;) denies (of Brahman) the suchness which forms the topic of&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;discussion; and (the text) enounces something more than that.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read, Br̥. Up. II, 3, &amp;lsquo;Two forms of Brahman there are indeed, the material and the immaterial, the mortal and the immortal, the solid and the fluid, sat and tya.&amp;rsquo; The text thereupon divides the five elements into two classes, predicates of the essence of that which is immaterial&amp;ndash;which it calls purusha&amp;ndash;saffron-colour, and so on, and then goes on to say, &amp;lsquo;Now then the teaching by Not so, not so! For there is nothing else higher than this (if one says): It is not so.&amp;rsquo; Here we have to enquire what the object of the negative statement is. We do not observe any definite thing indicated by words such as &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;that;&amp;rsquo; we merely have the word &amp;lsquo;so&amp;rsquo; in &amp;lsquo;Not so, not so!&amp;rsquo; to which the word &amp;rsquo;not&amp;rsquo; refers, and which on that account indicates something meant to be denied. Now we know that the word &amp;lsquo;so&amp;rsquo; (iti) is used with reference to approximate things, in the same way as the particle &amp;rsquo;evam&amp;rsquo; is used; compare, e.g. the sentence &amp;lsquo;so (iti) indeed the teacher said&amp;rsquo; (where the &amp;lsquo;so&amp;rsquo; refers to his immediately preceding speech). And, in our passage, the context points out what has to be considered as proximate, viz. the two cosmic forms of Brahman, and that Brahman itself to which the two forms belong. Hence there arises a doubt whether the phrase, &amp;lsquo;Not so, not so!&amp;rsquo; negatives both Brahman and its two forms, or only either; and if the latter, whether it negatives Brahman and leaves its two forms, or if it negatives the two forms and leaves Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That (Brahman) is unevolved; for (thus scripture) says.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If that highest Brahman which is different from the world that is negatived in the passage discussed above really exists, why then is it not apprehended?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because, the Sūtrakāra replies, it is unevolved, not to be apprehended by the senses; for it is the witness of whatever is apprehended (i.e. the subject in all apprehension). Thus Śruti says, &amp;lsquo;He is not apprehended by the eye, nor by speech, nor by the other senses, not by penance or good works&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, 1, 8); &amp;lsquo;That Self is to be described by No, no! He is incomprehensible, for he cannot be comprehended&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 9, 26); &amp;lsquo;That which cannot be seen nor apprehended&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 6); &amp;lsquo;When in that which is invisible, incorporeal, undefined, unsupported&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Taitt. Up. II, 7). Similar statements are made in Smr̥ti-passages; so e.g. &amp;lsquo;He is called unevolved, not to be fathomed by thought, unchangeable.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And in the state of perfect conciliation also (the Yogins apprehend the highest Brahman), according to Śruti and Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the time of perfect conciliation the Yogins see the unevolved Self free from all plurality. By &amp;lsquo;perfect conciliation&amp;rsquo; we understand the presentation before the mind (of the highest Self), which is effected through meditation and devotion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is vouched for by Śruti as well as&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Smr̥ti. So, e.g. Ka. Up. IV, 1, &amp;lsquo;The Self-existent pierced the openings of the senses so that they turn outward; therefore man looks without, not within himself. Some wise man, however, with his eyes closed and wishing for immortality, saw the Self within.&amp;rsquo; And Mu. Up. III, 1, 8, &amp;lsquo;When a man&amp;rsquo;s mind has become purified by the serene light of knowledge then he sees him, meditating on him as without parts.&amp;rsquo; Smr̥ti-passages of the same tendency are the following ones, &amp;lsquo;He who is seen as light by the Yogins meditating on him sleepless, with suspended breath, with contented minds, with subdued senses; reverence be to him &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;!&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;The Yogins see him, the august, eternal one.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And as in the case of (physical) light and the like, there is non-distinction (of the two Selfs), the light (i.e. the intelligent Self) (being divided) by its activity; according to the repeated declarations of scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As light, ether, the sun and so on appear differentiated as it were through their objects such as fingers, vessels, water and so on which constitute limiting adjuncts &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while in reality they preserve their essential non-differentiatedness; so the distinction of different Selfs is due to limiting adjuncts only, while the unity of all Selfs is natural and original. For on the doctrine of the non-difference of the individual soul and the highest Self the Vedānta-texts insist again and again. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hence (the soul enters into unity) with the infinite (i.e. the highest Self); for this scripture indicates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hence i.e. because the non-difference of all Selfs is essential and their difference due to Nescience only, the individual soul after having dispelled Nescience by true knowledge passes over into unity with the highest Self. For this is indicated by scripture, cp. e.g. Mu. Up. III, 2, 9, &amp;lsquo;He who knows that highest Brahman becomes even Brahman;&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 6, &amp;lsquo;Being Brahman he goes to Brahman.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of twofold designation, (the relation of the highest Self to the individual soul has to be viewed) like that of the snake to its coils.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to justify his own view as to the relation of the conciliating individual soul and the conciliated highest Self, the Sūtrakāra mentions a different view of the same matter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some scriptural passages refer to the highest Self and the individual soul as distinct entities, cp. e.g. Mu. Up. III, 1, 8,&amp;rsquo; Then he sees him meditating on him as without parts,&amp;rsquo; where the highest Self appears as the object of the soul&amp;rsquo;s vision and meditation; Mu. Up. III, 2, 8, &amp;lsquo;He goes to the divine Person who is greater than the great;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Br̥. Up. III, 7, 15, &amp;lsquo;Who rules all beings within;&amp;rsquo; in which passages the highest Self is represented as the object of approach and as the ruler of the individual soul. In other places again the two are spoken of as non-different, so e.g. Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 7, &amp;lsquo;Thou art that;&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. I, 4, 10, &amp;lsquo;I am Brahman;&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. III, 4, 1, &amp;lsquo;This is thy Self who is within all;&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. III, 7, 15, &amp;lsquo;He is thy Self, the ruler within, the immortal.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or else like that of light to its substratum, both being fire.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else the relation of the two may be viewed as follows. Just as the light of the sun and its substratum, i.e. the sun himself, are not absolutely different&amp;ndash;for they both consist of fire&amp;ndash;and yet are spoken of as different, so also the soul and the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or else (the relation of the two is to be conceived) in the manner stated above.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else the relation of the two has to be conceived in the manner suggested by Sūtra 25. For if the bondage of the soul is due to Nescience only, final release is possible. But if the soul is really and truly bound&amp;ndash;whether the soul be considered as a certain condition or state of the highest Self as suggested in Sūtra 27, or as a part of the highest Self as suggested in Sūtra 28&amp;ndash;its real bondage cannot be done away with, and thus the scriptural doctrine of final release becomes absurd.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the denial.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conclusion arrived at above is confirmed by the fact of scripture expressly denying that there exists any intelligent being apart from the highest Self. Cp. &amp;lsquo;There is no other seer but he&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 23). And the same&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;conclusion follows from those passages which deny the existence of a world apart from Brahman and thus leave Brahman alone remaining, viz. &amp;lsquo;Now then the teaching, Not so, not so!&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 3, 6); &amp;lsquo;That Brahman is without cause and without effect, without anything inside or outside&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 5, 19).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Beyond (Brahman, there is something) further, on account of the designations of bank, measure, connexion, separation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reference to this Brahman which we have ascertained to be free from all plurality there now arises the doubt&amp;ndash;due to the conflicting nature of various scriptural statements&amp;ndash;whether something exists beyond it or not. We therefore enter on the task of explaining the true meaning of those scriptural passages which seem to indicate that there is some entity beyond, i.e. apart from Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (Brahman is called a bank &amp;amp;c.) on account of (a certain) equality.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; is meant to set aside the previously established conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There can exist nothing different from Brahman, since we are unable to observe a proof for such existence. That all existences which have a beginning spring from, subsist through, and return into Brahman we have already ascertained, and have shown that the effect is non-different from the cause.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The statement as to Brahman having size) subserves the purpose of the mind; in the manner of the four feet (quarters).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In reply to the pūrvapakshin&amp;rsquo;s contention that the statements as to Brahman&amp;rsquo;s size, prove that there exists something different from Brahman, we remark that those statements merely serve the purposes of the mind, i.e. of devout meditation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how can the cognition of something consisting&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of four, or eight, or sixteen parts be referred to Brahman?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The statements concerning connexion and difference) are due to difference of place; in the manner of light and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The present Sūtra refutes the allegation that something different from Brahman exists, firstly, because things are said to be connected with Brahman, and secondly, because things are said to be separate from it. The fact is, that all those statements regarding connexion and difference are made with a view to difference of place. When the cognition of difference which is produced by the Selfs connexion with different places, i.e. with the buddhi and the other limiting adjuncts, ceases on account of the cessation of those limiting adjuncts themselves, connexion with the highest Self is metaphorically said to take place; but that is done with a view to the limiting adjuncts only, not with a view to any limitation on the part of the Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because (only such a connexion) is possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, only such a connexion as described above is possible. For scriptural passages, such as &amp;lsquo;He is gone to his Self (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 1), declare that the connexion of the soul with the highest Self is one of essential nature. But as the essential nature of a thing is imperishable, the connexion cannot be analogous to that of the inhabitants with the town, but can only be explained with reference to an obscuration, owing to Nescience, of the soul&amp;rsquo;s true nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The same thing follows) from the express denial of other (existences).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having thus refuted the arguments of the pūrvapakshin, the Sūtrakāra in conclusion strengthens his view by a further reason. A great number of Vedic passages&amp;ndash;which, considering the context in which they stand, cannot be explained otherwise&amp;ndash;distinctly deny that there exists anything apart from Brahman; &amp;lsquo;He indeed is below; I am below; the Self is below&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 25, 1; 2); &amp;lsquo;Whosoever looks for anything elsewhere than in the Self was abandoned by everything&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 4, 6); &amp;lsquo;Brahman&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thereby the omnipresence (of Brahman is established), in accordance with the statements about (Brahman&amp;rsquo;s) extent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The preceding demonstration that the texts calling Brahman a bank, and so on, are not to be taken literally, and that, on the other hand, the texts denying all plurality must be accepted as they stand., moreover, serves to prove that the Self is omnipresent. If the former texts were taken literally, banks and the like would have to be looked upon as belonging to the Self, and thence it would follow that the Self is limited. And if the texts of the latter class were not accepted as valid, there would be substances exclusive of each other, and thus the Self would again be limited.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;From him (i.e. the Lord, there comes) the fruit (of works); for (that only) is possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now turn to another characteristic belonging to Brahman, in so far as it is connected with the every-day world in which we distinguish a ruler and the objects of his rule.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There arises the question whether the threefold fruits of action which are enjoyed by the creatures in their&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;saṁsāra-state&amp;ndash;viz. pain, pleasure, and a mixture of the two-spring from the actions themselves or come from the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because it is declared by scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We assume the Lord to bring about the fruits of actions, not only because no other assumption appears plausible, but also because we have direct scriptural statement on our side. Cp. e.g. the passage, &amp;lsquo;This indeed is the great, unborn Self, the giver of food, the giver of wealth&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV. 4, 24).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/2/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Jaimini (thinks) for the same reasons that religious merit (is what brings about the fruits of actions).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Jaimini bases a contrary opinion on the reasons specified in the last two Sūtras. Scripture, he argues, proclaims injunctions such as the following one, &amp;lsquo;He who is desirous of the heavenly world is to sacrifice.&amp;rsquo; Now as it is admitted that such scriptural injunctions must have an object, we conclude that the sacrifice itself brings about the result, i.e. the obtainment of the heavenly world; for if this were not so, nobody would perform sacrifices and thereby scriptural injunctions would be rendered purposeless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
