<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;२ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 second pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-pāda&#34;&gt;SECOND PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That which is inferred (by the Sānkhyas, viz. the pradhāna) cannot be the cause (of the world), on account of the orderly arrangement (of the world) being impossible (on that hypothesis).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although it is the object of this system to define the true meaning of the Vedānta-texts and not, like the science of Logic, to establish or refute some tenet by mere ratiocination, still it is incumbent on thorough students of the Vedānta to refute the Sānkhya and other systems which are obstacles in the way of perfect knowledge. For this purpose a new chapter is begun. (Nor must it be said that the refutation of the other systems ought to have preceded the establishment of the Vedānta position; for) as the determination of the sense of the Vedānta-passages directly subserves perfect knowledge, we have at first, by means of such a determination, established our own position, since this is a task more important than the refutation of the views entertained by others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (the impossibility of) activity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Leaving the arrangement of the world, we now pass on to the activity by which it is produced.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The three guṇas, passing out of the state of equipoise and entering into the condition of mutual subordination and superordination, originate activities tending towards the production of particular effects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now these activities also cannot be ascribed to a non-intelligent pradhāna left to itself, as no such activity is seen in clay and similar substances, or in chariots and the like. For we observe that clay and the like, and chariots&amp;ndash;which are in their own nature non-intelligent&amp;ndash;enter on activities tending towards particular effects only when they are acted upon by intelligent beings such as potters, &amp;amp;c. in the one case, and horses and the like in the other case. From what is seen we determine what is not seen. Hence a non-intelligent cause of the world is not to be inferred because, on that hypothesis, the activity without which the world cannot be produced would be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that the pradhāna moves) like milk or water, (we reply that) there also (the motion is due to intelligence).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, the Sānkhya resumes, listen then to the following instances.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As non-sentient milk flows forth from its own nature merely for the nourishment of the young animal, and as non-sentient water, from its own nature, flows along for the benefit of mankind, so the pradhāna also, although non-intelligent, may be supposed to move from its own nature merely for the purpose of effecting the highest end of man.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because (the pradhāna), on account of there existing nothing beyond it, stands in no relation; (it cannot be active.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The three guṇas of the Sānkhyas when in a state of equipoise form the pradhāna. Beyond the pradhāna there exists no external principle which could either impel the pradhāna to activity or restrain it from activity. The soul (purusha), as we know, is indifferent, neither moves to&amp;ndash;nor restrains from&amp;ndash;action. As therefore the pradhāna stands in no relation, it is impossible to see why it should sometimes modify itself into the great principle (mahat) and sometimes not. The activity and non-activity (by turns) of the Lord,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nor (can it be said that the pradhāna modifies itself spontaneously) like grass, &amp;amp;c. (which turn into milk); for (milk) does not exist elsewhere (but in the female animal).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let this be (the Sānkhya resumes). Just as grass, herbs, water, &amp;amp;c. independently of any other instrumental cause transform themselves, by their own nature, into milk; so, we assume, the pradhāna also transforms itself into the great principle, and so on. And, if you ask how we know that grass transforms itself independently of any instrumental cause; we reply, &amp;lsquo;Because no such cause is observed.&amp;rsquo; For if we did perceive some such cause, we certainly should apply it to grass, &amp;amp;c. according to our liking, and thereby produce milk. But as a matter of fact we do no such thing. Hence the transformation of grass and the like must be considered to be due to its own nature merely; and we may infer therefrom that the transformation of the pradhāna is of the same kind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Even if we admit (the Sānkhya position refuted in what precedes, it is invalidated by other objections) on account of the absence of a purpose (on the part of the pradhāna).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even if we, accommodating ourselves to your (the Sānkhya&amp;rsquo;s) belief, should admit what has been disproved in the preceding Sūtra, viz. that the pradhāna is spontaneously active, still your opinion would lie open to an objection &amp;lsquo;on account of the absence of a purpose.&amp;rsquo; For if the spontaneous activity of the pradhāna has, as you say, no reference to anything else, it will have no reference not only to any aiding principle, but also to any purpose or motive, and consequently your doctrine that the pradhāna is active in order to effect the purpose of man will become untenable. If you reply that the pradhāna does not indeed regard any aiding principle, but does regard a purpose, we remark that in that case we must distinguish between the different possible purposes, viz. either enjoyment (on the part of the soul), or final release, or both. If enjoyment, what enjoyment, we ask, can belong to the soul which is naturally incapable of any accretion (of pleasure or pain) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;? Moreover, there would in that case be no opportunity for release &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And if you say (that the soul may move the pradhāna) as the (lame) man (moves the blind one) or as the magnet (moves the iron); thus also (the difficulty is not overcome).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well then&amp;ndash;the Sānkhya resumes, endeavouring to defend his position by parallel instances&amp;ndash;let us say that, as some lame man devoid of the power of motion, but possessing the power of sight, having mounted the back of a blind man who is able to move but not to see, makes the latter move; or as the magnet not moving itself, moves the iron, so the soul moves the pradhāna.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And, again, (the pradhāna cannot be active) because the relation of principal (and subordinate matter) is impossible (between the three guṇas).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the following reason also activity on the part of the pradhāna is not possible.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The condition of the pradhāna&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;consists in the three guṇas, viz. goodness, passion, and darkness, abiding in themselves in a state of equipoise without standing to one another in the relation of mutual superiority or inferiority. In that state the guṇas cannot possibly enter into the relation of mutual subserviency because thereby they would forfeit their essential characteristic, viz. absolute independence. And as there exists no extraneous principle to stir up the guṇas, the production of the great principle and the other effects&amp;ndash;which would acquire for its operative cause a non-balanced state of the guṇas&amp;ndash;is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And although another inference be made, (the objections remain in force) on account of the (pradhāna) being devoid of the power of intelligence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But&amp;ndash;the Sānkhya resumes&amp;ndash;we draw another inference, so as to leave no room for the objection just stated. We do not acknowledge the guṇas to be characterised by absolute irrelativity and unchangeableness, since there is no proof for such an assumption. We rather infer the characteristics of the guṇas from those of their effects, presuming that their nature must be such as to render the production of the effects possible. Now the guṇas are admitted to be of an unsteady nature; hence the guṇas themselves are able to enter into the relation of mutual inequality, even while they are in a state of equipoise.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And moreover (the Sānkhya doctrine) is objectionable on account of its contradictions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The doctrine of the Sānkhyas, moreover, is full of contradictions. Sometimes they enumerate seven senses, sometimes eleven &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In some places they teach that the subtle elements of material things proceed from the great principle, in other places again that they proceed from self-consciousness. Sometimes they speak of three internal organs, sometimes of one only &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That their doctrine, moreover, contradicts Śruti, which teaches that the Lord is the cause of the world, and Smr̥ti, based on Śruti, is well known.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/2/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or (the world may originate from Brahman)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;as the great and the long originate from the short and the atomic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The system of the Vaiśeshikas is the following;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The atoms which possess, according to their special kind  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the qualities of colour, &amp;amp;c., and which are of spherical form  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, subsist during a certain period  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; without producing any effects  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After that, the unseen principle (adr̥shṭa), &amp;amp;c.  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, acting as operative causes and conjunction constituting the non-inherent cause  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, they produce the entire aggregate of effected things, beginning with binary atomic compounds. At the same time the qualities of the causes (i.e. of the simple atoms) produce corresponding qualities in the effects. Thus, when two atoms produce a binary atomic compound, the special qualities belonging to the simple atoms, such as white colour, &amp;amp;c., produce a corresponding white colour in the binary compound. One special quality, however, of the simple atoms, viz. atomic sphericity, does not produce corresponding sphericity in the binary compound; for the forms of extension belonging to the latter arc said to be minuteness (aṇutva) and shortness. And, again, when two binary compounds combining produce a quaternary atomic compound, the qualities, such as whiteness, &amp;amp;c., inherent in the binary compounds produce corresponding qualities in the quaternary compounds; with the exception, however, of the two qualities of minuteness and shortness. For it is&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
