<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 third pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-pāda&#34;&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The cognitions) intimated by all the Vedānta-texts (are identical), on account of the non-difference of injunction and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding part of this work we have explained the nature of the object of cognition, i.e. Brahman. We now enter on the discussion of the question whether the cognitions of Brahman, which form the subject of the different Vedānta-texts, are separate cognitions or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(If it be said that the vidyās are separate) on account of the difference (of secondary matters), we deny that, since even in one and the same vidyā (different secondary matters may find place).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In spite of the preceding argumentation we cannot admit that the different cognitions of Brahman are equally intimated by all Vedānta-texts, because we meet with differences in secondary matters (guṇa). Thus the Vājasaneyins mention in their text of the knowledge of the five fires a sixth fire (&amp;lsquo;And then the fire is indeed fire,&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. VI, 2, 14), while the Cḥandogas mention no sixth fire but conclude their text of the pañcāgnividyā with the express mention of five fires (&amp;lsquo;But he who thus knows the five fires,&amp;rsquo; Cḥ. Up. V, 10, 10).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The rite of carrying fire on the head is an attribute) of the study of the Veda (of the Ātharvaṇikas); because in the Samācāra (it is mentioned) as being such. (This also follows) from the general subject-matter, and the limitation (of the rite to the Ātharvaṇikas) is analogous to that of the libations,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reference to the pūrvapakshin&amp;rsquo;s averment that the rite of carrying fire on the head is connected with the vidyā of the followers of the Atharva-veda only, not with any other vidyā, and that thereby the vidyā of the Ātharvaṇikas is separated from all other vidyās, the following remarks have to be made.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Scripture) also declares this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Veda also declares the identity of the vidyās; for all Vedānta-texts represent the object of knowledge as one; cp. e.g. Kā. Up. I, 2, 15, &amp;lsquo;That word which all the Vedas record;&amp;rsquo; Ait. Ār. Ill, 2,3,12, &amp;lsquo;Him only the Bahvr̥kas consider in the great hymn, the Adhvaryus in the sacrificial fire, the Cḥandogas in the Mahāvrata ceremony.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To quote some other instances proving the unity of the vidyās: Kā. Up. I, 6, 2, mentions as one of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s qualities that he&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the case of (a devout meditation) common (to several Śākhās) (the particulars mentioned in each Śākhā) have to be combined, since there is no difference of essential matter; just as in the case of what is complementary to injunctions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[This Sūtra states the practical outcome of the discussion carried on in the first four Sūtras.] It having been determined that the cognitions of Brahman are equally intimated by all Vedānta-texts, it follows that as long as the cognition is one and the same its specific determinations mentioned in one text are to be introduced into other texts also where they are not mentioned. For if the matter of these determinations subserves some particular cognition in one place, it subserves it in another place also, since in both places we have to do with one and the same cognition. The case is analogous to that of the things subordinate to some sacrificial performance, as, e g. the agnihotra. The agnihotra also is one performance, and therefore its subordinate members, although they may be mentioned in different texts, have to be combined into one whole.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (the udgītha vidyā of the Br̥. Up. and that of the Cḥānd. Up.) are separate on account (of the difference) of the texts; we deny this on the ground of their (essential) non-difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Vājasaneyaka I, 3, 1, &amp;lsquo;The Devas said, well, let us overcome the Asuras at the sacrifices by means of the Udgītha. They said to speech: Do thou sing out for us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or rather there is no (unity of the vidyās), owing to the difference of subject-matter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Setting aside the view maintained by the pūrvapakshin, we have rather to say that, owing to the difference &amp;ldquo;of subject-matter, the two vidyās are separate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Cḥāndogya the introductory sentence (I, 1, 1), &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the syllable Om (as) the udgītha,&amp;rsquo; represents as the object of meditation the syllable Om which is a part of the udgītha; thereupon proceeds to give an account of its qualities such as being the inmost essence of all (&amp;lsquo;The full account, however, of Om is this,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.); and later on tells, with reference to the same syllable Om which is a part of the udgītha, a story about the Gods and Asuras in which there occurs the statement,&amp;rsquo; They meditated on the udgītha&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that the vidyās are one) on account of (the identity of) name; (we reply that) that is explained (already); moreover that (identity of name) is (found in the case of admittedly separate vidyās).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here it might be said that after all the unity of the two vidyās discussed must be admitted, since they are called by one and the same name, viz. &amp;rsquo;the science of the udgītha.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the (omkāra) extending over the whole (Veda), (the view that the term udgītha expresses a specialisation) is appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the passage, &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the syllable Om (as) the udgītha,&amp;rsquo; the two words &amp;lsquo;omkāra&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;udgītha&amp;rsquo; are placed in co-ordination. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The question then arises&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The two words are shown to stand in that relation by their being exhibited in the same case.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;whether the relation in which the ideas conveyed by these two words stand to each other is the relation of super-imposition (adhyāsa) or sublation (apavāda) or unity (ekatva) or specification (viśeshaṇa); for primā facie each of these relations may present itself to the mind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Those (qualities which are attributed to the subject of a vidyā in one Śākhā only) (are to be inserted) in other places (also), since (the vidyās) are non-different on the whole.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the colloquy of the prāṇas recorded by the Vājasaneyins and the Cḥandogas the prāṇa, endowed with various qualities such as being the best and so on, is represented as the object of meditation, and various qualities such as being the richest and the like are ascribed to speech and the other organs. And these latter qualities are in the end attributed to the prāṇa also, &amp;lsquo;If I am the richest thou art the richest,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. Now in other Śākhās also, as e.g. that of the Kaushītakins, the former set of qualities such as being the best and so on is ascribed to the prāṇa (cp. Kau. Up. II, 14, &amp;lsquo;Now follows the Niḥśreyasādāna,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.), but at the same time the latter set of attributes, viz. being the richest and so on, is not mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bliss and other (qualities) as belonging to the subject of the qualities (have to be attributed to Brahman everywhere).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those scriptural texts which aim at intimating the characteristics of Brahman separately ascribe to it various qualities, such as having bliss for its nature, being one mass of knowledge, being omnipresent, being the Self of all and so on. Now the doubt here presents itself whether in each place where Brahman is spoken of we have to understand only those qualities which actually are mentioned there, or whether we have to combine all qualities of Brahman mentioned anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Such qualities as) joy being its head and so on have no force (for other passages); for increase and decrease belong to plurality (only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attributes such as having joy for its head and so on, which are recorded in the Taittirīyaka, are not to be viewed as having force with regard to other passages treating of Brahman, because the successive terms, &amp;lsquo;Joy,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Satisfaction,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Great Satisfaction,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Bliss,&amp;rsquo; indicate qualities possessing lower and higher degrees with regard to each other and to other enjoyers. Now for higher and lower degrees there is room only where there is plurality; and Brahman is without all plurality, as we know from many scriptural passages (&amp;lsquo;One only, without a Second&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But other (attributes are valid for all passages relative to Brahman), the purport being the same.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other attributes, however, such as bliss and so on which scripture sets forth for the purpose of teaching the true nature of Brahman are to be viewed as valid for all passages referring to Brahman; for their purport, i.e. the Brahman&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;whose nature is to be taught, is one. Those attributes are mentioned with a view to knowledge only, not to meditation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The passage, Kāṭḥaka I, 3, 10, gives information about the person) for the purpose of pious meditation, as there is no use (of the knowledge of the objects being higher than the senses and so on).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Kāṭḥaka (I, 3, 10), &amp;lsquo;Higher than the senses are the objects, higher than the objects there is the mind, &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c.; higher than the person there is nothing&amp;ndash;this is the goal, the highest road.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the word &amp;lsquo;Self.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above conclusion is confirmed by the circumstance that the person under discussion is called the Self in I, 3, 12, &amp;lsquo;That Self is hidden in all beings and does not shine forth, but it is seen by subtle seers through their sharp and subtle intellect.&amp;rsquo; From this we conclude that the text wishes to represent the other beings enumerated as the Non-Self. The passage quoted, moreover, indicates that the person is hard to know, and to be reached by sharp minds only.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The (highest) Self has to be understood (in Ait. Ār. II, 4, i), as in other places; on account of the subsequent (qualification).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Aitareyaka (II, 4, i), &amp;lsquo;Verily, in the beginning all this was Self, one only; there was nothing&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;else blinking whatsoever. He thought, shall I send forth worlds? He sent forth these worlds, the (heavenly) waters, the rays, the mortal (earth), and water.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the doubt presents itself whether the term &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo; denotes the highest Self or some other being.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Should it be said that on account of the connected meaning (of the whole passage) (the highest Self cannot be meant); (we reply that) it is so, on account of the assertion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now have to refute the objection, made above by the pūrvapakshin, that the highest Self cannot be meant &amp;lsquo;on account of the connected meaning of the passage.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtrakāra remarks, &amp;lsquo;It is so, on account of the assertion.&amp;rsquo; That means: It is appropriate to understand the passage as referring to the highest Self, because thus the assertion that the Self, previously to the creation, was one only, gives a fully satisfactory sense, while on the other interpretation it would be far from doing so. The creation of the worlds recorded in the Aitareyaka we connect with the creation of the elements recorded in other Vedic texts, in that way that we understand the worlds to have been created subsequently to the elements; just as we showed above (II, 4, 1) that the passage, &amp;lsquo;It sent forth fire,&amp;rsquo; must be understood to say that the creation of fire followed on the creation of ether&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As (scripture where speaking of the rinsing of the mouth with water) makes a reference to an act (established by Smr̥ti), (that act is not enjoined by Śruti, but rather) the new (act of meditation on the water viewed as the dress of prāṇa).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Cḥandogas as well as the Vājasaneyins record, in the colloquy of the prāṇas, that the food of Breath comprizes everything even unto dogs and birds, and that water is its dress. To this the Cḥandogas add, &amp;lsquo;Therefore when going to eat food they surround it before and after with water&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 2, 2). And the Vājasaneyins add (Br̥. Up. VI, 1, 14), &amp;lsquo;Śrotriyas who know this rinse the mouth with water when they are going to eat and rinse the mouth with water after they have eaten, thinking that thereby they make the breath dressed. Therefore a man knowing this is to rinse the mouth with water when going to eat and after having eaten; he thereby makes that breath dressed.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the same (Śākhā also) it is thus (i.e. there is unity of vidyā), on account of the non-difference (of the object of meditation).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Agnirahasya forming part of the Vājasaneyi-śākhā there is a vidyā called the Sāṇḍilya-vidyā, in which we meet with the following statement of particulars, &amp;lsquo;Let him meditate on the Self which consists of mind, which has the prāṇa for its body and light for its form,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thus in other cases also, on account of the connexion (of particulars with one and the same vidyā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Br̥had-āraṇyaka (V, 5), &amp;lsquo;The true is Brahman,&amp;rsquo; and, further on, &amp;lsquo;Now what is the true, that is the Āditya, the person that dwells in yonder orb, and the person in the right eye.&amp;rsquo; Having thus declared the different abodes of that true Brahman with reference to the gods and with reference to the body, and having, in what follows, identified its body with the sacred syllables (bhūḥ, &amp;amp;c.), the text teaches its two secret names (upanishad), &amp;lsquo;Its secret name is ahar&amp;rsquo; with reference to the gods; and &amp;lsquo;its secret name is aham&amp;rsquo; with reference to the body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or this is not so, on account of the difference (of place).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The two secret names do not apply quite equally to the two persons mentioned, because they are connected with different places in the vidyā. For the clause, &amp;lsquo;Its secret name is ahar,&amp;rsquo; the text exhibits in connexion with the person in the solar orb, while the clause, &amp;lsquo;Its secret name is aham,&amp;rsquo; occurs in connexion with the person in the eye. Now the pronoun &amp;lsquo;its&amp;rsquo; always refers to something mentioned close by; we therefore conclude that the text teaches each secret name as belonging to one special abode of Brahman only. How then can both names be valid for both?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Scripture) also declares that.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture moreover contains a distinct intimation that the attributes under discussion are to be held apart. We read, Cḥ. Up. I, 8, 5, &amp;lsquo;The form of that person is the same as the form of the other person, the joints of the one are the joints of the other, the name of the one is the name of the other.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how does this passage convey the desired intimation?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And for the same reason the holding together and the pervading the sky (attributed to Brahman in the Rāṇāyanīya-khila) (are not to be inserted in other vidyās).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the khilas (supplementary writings) of the Rāṇāyanīyas we meet with a passage, &amp;lsquo;Held together are the powers among which Brahman is the best; the best Brahman in the beginning stretched out the sky &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;rsquo; which mentions certain energies of Brahman, such as holding together its powers, entering into the sky, &amp;amp;c. And in the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And as the record of others (viz. the Taittirīyaka) is not such as in the purusha-vidyā (of the Cḥāndogya), (the two purusha-vidyās are not to be combined).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Rahasya-brāhmaṇa of the Tāṇḍins and the Paiṅgins (the Cḥāndogya) there is a vidyā treating of man, in which man is fancifully identified with the sacrifice, the three periods of his life with the three libations, his hunger and so on, with the dīkshā, &amp;amp;c. And other particulars also are mentioned there, such as formulas of prayer, use of mantras and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Because the matter (of certain mantras) such as piercing and so on is different (from the matter of the approximate vidyās) (the former have not to be combined with the latter).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of an Upanishad of the Ātharvaṇikas the following mantra is recorded, &amp;lsquo;Pierce him (the enemy) whole, pierce his heart: crush his veins, crush his head; thrice crushed,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. At the beginning of the Upanishad of the Tāṇḍins we have the mantra, &amp;lsquo;O God Savitar, produce the sacrifice.&amp;rsquo; At the beginning of that of the Sāṭyāyanins, &amp;lsquo;Thou hast a white horse and art green as grass,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.; at the beginning of that of the Kaṭḥas and the Taittirīyakas, &amp;lsquo;May Mitra be propitious to us and Varuṇa,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. At the beginning of the Upanishad of the Vājasaneyins we have a Brāhmaṇa-passage about the pravargya-ceremony, &amp;lsquo;The gods indeed sat down to a sattra;&amp;rsquo; and at the beginning of that of the Kaushītakins there is a Brāhmaṇa-passage about the agnishṭoma, &amp;lsquo;Brahman indeed is the Agnishṭoma, Brahman is that day; through Brahman they pass into&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Where the getting rid (of good and evil) is mentioned (the obtaining of this good and evil by others has to be added) because the statement about the obtaining is supplementary (to the statement about the getting rid of), as in the case of the kuśās, the metres, the praise and the singing. This (i.e. the reason for this) has been stated (in the Pūrva Mīmāṁsā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the text of the Tāṇḍins we meet with the following passage: &amp;lsquo;Shaking off all evil as a horse shakes his hair, and shaking off the body as the moon frees herself from the mouth of Rāhu, I obtain self made and satisfied the uncreated world of Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 13). Again, in the text of the Ātharvaṇikas, we read, &amp;lsquo;Then knowing, shaking off good and evil he reaches the highest oneness, free from passion&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III. 1, 3). The Sāṭyāyanins read, &amp;lsquo;His sons obtain his inheritance, his friends the good, his enemies the evil he has done.&amp;rsquo; And the Kaushītakins, &amp;lsquo;He shakes off his good and his evil deeds. His beloved relatives obtain the good, his unbeloved relatives the evil he has done&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. I, 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At the (moment of) departing (he frees himself from his works), there being nothing to be reached (by him, on the way to Brahman, through those works); for thus others (declare, in their sacred texts).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Kaushītakins record in the paryaṅka-vidyā how the man (who possesses true knowledge) when approaching Brahman seated on the couch frees himself on the way from his good and evil deeds, &amp;lsquo;He having reached the path of the gods comes to the world of Agni,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Kau. Up. I, 3), and later on (I, 4), &amp;lsquo;He comes to the river Vijarā and crosses it by the mind alone and there shakes off his good and evil deeds.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because (on the above interpretation)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there is no contradiction to both (i.e. man&amp;rsquo;s making an effort to free himself from his deeds and actually freeing himself) according to his liking.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover if we assumed that the man frees himself from his good and evil deeds on the way&amp;ndash;after having departed from the body and having entered on the path of the gods&amp;ndash;we should implicate ourselves in impossibilities; for after the body has been left behind, man can no longer accomplish, according to his liking, that effort which consists in self-restraint and pursuit of knowledge, and which is the cause of the obliteration of all his good and evil deeds, and consequently that obliteration also cannot take place. We therefore must assume that the requisite effort is made&amp;ndash;and its result takes place&amp;ndash;at an earlier moment, viz. in the state in which man is able to effect it, and that in consequence thereof man rids himself of his good and evil deeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A purpose has to be attributed to the going (on the path of the gods) in a twofold manner; otherwise there would be contradiction of scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In some scriptural texts the (dead man&amp;rsquo;s) going on the path of the gods is mentioned in connexion with his freeing himself from good and evil; in other texts it is not mentioned. The doubt then arises whether the two things go together in all cases or only in certain cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The twofold view taken above) is justified because we observe a purpose characterised thereby (i.e. a purpose of the going); as in ordinary life.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our view of the matter, viz. that a man&amp;rsquo;s proceeding on the path of the gods has a meaning in certain cases but not in others, is justified by the following consideration. In meditations on the qualified Brahman such as the paryaṅka-vidyā we see a reason for the man&amp;rsquo;s proceeding on the path of the gods; for the text mentions certain results which can be reached only by the man going to different places, such as his mounting a couch, his holding a colloquy with Brahman seated on the couch, his perceiving various odours and so on. On the other hand we do not see that going on the path of the gods has anything to do with perfect knowledge. For those who have risen to the intuition of the Self&amp;rsquo;s unity, whose every wish is fulfilled, in whom the potentiality of all suffering is already destroyed here below, have nothing further to look for but the dissolution of the abode of activity and enjoyment of former deeds, i.e. the body; in their case therefore to proceed on the road of the gods would be purposeless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is no restriction (as to the going on the path of the gods) for any vidyā; nor any contradiction&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(of the general subject-matter), according to scripture and inference (i.e. Smr̥ti).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have shown that the going on the path of the gods is valid only for the vidyās of the qualified Brahman, not for the knowledge of the highest Brahman which is destitute of all qualities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now we observe that the going on the path of the gods is mentioned only in some of the qualified vidyās such as the paryaṅka-vidyā, the pañcāgni-vidyā, the upakośala-vidyā, the dahara-vidyā; while it is not mentioned in others, such as the madhu-vidyā, the sāṇḍilya-vidyā, the shoḍaśakala-vidyā, the vaiśvānara-vidyā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of those who have a certain office there is subsistence (of the body) as long as the office lasts.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question here is whether for him who has reached true knowledge a new body originates after he has parted with the old one or not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But an objection is here raised at the outset there is really no occasion for inquiring whether knowledge when reaching its perfection brings about its due effect, viz. complete isolation of the Self from all bodies or not; not any more than there is room for an inquiry whether there is cooked rice or not, after the process of cooking has reached its due termination; or, for an inquiry whether a man is satisfied by eating or not. Not so, we reply. There is indeed room for the inquiry proposed, as we know from itihāsa and purāṇa that some persons although knowing Brahman yet obtained new bodies. Tradition informs us, e.g. that Apāntaratamas, an ancient r̥shi and teacher of the Vedas, was, by the order of Vishnu, born on this earth as Krishna Dvaipāyana at the time when the Dvāparayuga was succeeded by the Kaliyuga. Similarly Vasishṭḥa, the son of Brahman&amp;rsquo;s mind, having parted from his former body in consequence of the curse of Nimi, was, on the order of Brahman, again procreated by Mitra and Varuṇa. Smr̥ti further relates that Bhr̥gu and other sons of Brahman&amp;rsquo;s mind were again born at the sacrifice of Varuṇa. Sanatkumāra also, who likewise was a son of Brahman&amp;rsquo;s mind, was, in consequence of a boon being granted to Rudra, born again as Skanda. And there are similar tales about Daksha, Nārada, and others having, for various reasons, assumed new bodies. Stories of the same kind are met with in the mantras and arthavādas of Śruti. Of some of the persons mentioned it is said that they assumed a new body after the old body had perished; of others that they assumed, through their&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the (denials of) conceptions concerning the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;akshara are to be comprehended (in all meditations on the akshara), on account of the equality and of the object being the same, as in the case of the upasad; this has been explained (in the Pūrva Mīmāṁsā).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Vājasaneyaka, &amp;lsquo;O Gārgī, the Brāhmaṇas call this the Akshara. It is neither coarse, nor fine, nor short, nor long,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 8). Similarly the Ātharvaṇa says, &amp;lsquo;The higher knowledge is that by which the Indestructible is apprehended. That which cannot be seen nor seized, which has no family and no caste,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Mu. Up. I, 1, 5; 6). In other places also the highest Brahman, under the name of Akshara, is described as that of which all qualities are to be denied. Now in some places qualities are denied of Brahman which are not denied in other places, and hence a doubt arises whether the mental conception of these particular denials is to form part of all those passages or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of (the same) number being recorded.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Ātharvaṇikas exhibit, with reference to the Self, the following mantra, &amp;lsquo;Two birds, inseparable friends, cling to the same tree. One of them eats the sweet fruit, the other looks on without eating&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, 1, i). The same mantra is found in the text of the Śvetāśvataras (IV, 6). The Kaṭḥas again read, &amp;lsquo;There are the two drinking their reward in the world of their own works, entered into the cave, dwelling on the highest summit. Those who know Brahman call them shade and light, likewise those householders who perform the Triṇaciketa-sacrifice.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As the Self is within all, as in the case of the aggregate of the elements, (there is oneness of vidyā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vājasaneyins record, in the questions asked by Ushasta and by Kahola, the same passage twice in succession, &amp;lsquo;Tell me the Brahman which is present to intuition, not hidden; the Self who is within all&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 4, 1; 5, 1).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question here presents itself whether the two sections introduced by the questions constitute one vidyā only or two separate vidyās.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that otherwise the separation (of the statements) cannot be accounted for; we reply that it is (here) as in the case of other instructions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We yet have to refute the remark made by the pūrvapakshin that, unless the separateness of the two vidyās be admitted, the separation of the two statements cannot be accounted for. We do this by pointing to analogous cases. In the sixth prapāṭḥaka of the upanishad of the Tāṇḍins the instruction conveyed in the words, &amp;lsquo;That is the Self, thou art that, O Śvetaketu,&amp;rsquo; is repeated nine times, and yet the one vidyā is not thereby split into many. Similarly in our case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is exchange (of meditation), for the texts distinguish (two meditations); as in other cases.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Aitareyins declare with reference to the person in the sun, &amp;lsquo;What I am, that is he; what he is, that am I&amp;rsquo; (Ait. Ār. II, 2, 4, 6). And the Jābālas say, &amp;lsquo;I am thou indeed, O reverend divinity, and thou art I indeed.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The doubt here arises whether the reflection founded upon this text is to be a double one &amp;lsquo;by means of exchange&amp;rsquo; (i.e. whether the soul is to be meditated upon as āditya and āditya as the soul), or a simple one (the soul only being meditated upon as āditya).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For the True and so on are one and the same (vidyā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The text of the Vājasaneyaka, after having enjoined the knowledge of the True, together with a meditation on the syllables of its name (&amp;lsquo;Whosoever knows this great glorious first-born as the true Brahman,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., Br̥. Up. V, 4, 1), continues, &amp;lsquo;Now what is the True, that is the Āditya, the person that dwells in yonder orb, and the person in the right eye&amp;rsquo; (V, 5, 2).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Having true) wishes and other (qualities) (have to be combined) there and here, on account of the abode and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the chapter of the Cḥāndogya which begins with the passage, &amp;lsquo;There is this city of Brahman and in it the palace, the small lotus, and in it that small ether&amp;rsquo; (VIII, 1, 1), we read, &amp;lsquo;That is the Self free from sin, free from old age, from death and grief, from hunger and thirst, whose desires are true, whose imaginations are true.&amp;rsquo; A similar passage is found in the text of the Vājasaneyins, &amp;lsquo;He is that great unborn Self who consists of knowledge, is surrounded by the Prāṇas, the ether within the heart. In it there reposes the ruler of all&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of (the passage showing) respect, there is non-omission (of the prāṇāgnihotra) (even when the eating of food is omitted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Cḥāndogya under the heading of the Vaiśvānara-vidyā, &amp;lsquo;Therefore the first food which comes is in the place of Homa. And he who offers that first oblation should offer it to Prāṇa, saying Svāhā&amp;rsquo; (Kh., Up. V, 19, i). The text thereupon enjoins five oblations, and later on applies to them the term &amp;lsquo;Agnihotra;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;He who thus knowing this offers the agnihotra,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;As hungry children here on earth sit round their mother, so do all beings sit round the agnihotra&amp;rsquo; (V, 24, 2; 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When (eating) is taking place, (the prāṇāgnihotra has to be performed) from that (i.e. the food first eaten); on the ground of the passage declaring this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When eating is actually taking place, &amp;lsquo;from that,&amp;rsquo; i.e. with that material of food which first presents itself, the agnihotra offered to the prāṇas is to be effected.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On what&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ground?&amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo; On the ground of the passage declaring this.&amp;rsquo; For the clause, &amp;lsquo;The first food which a man may take is in the place of a homa,&amp;rsquo; enjoins the circumstance of the oblations to the prāṇas being effected by means of a material (primarily) subserving another purpose (viz. eating), as appears from its referring to the presentation of food as something accomplished (i.e. accomplished independently of the oblations; not tending to accomplish the oblations). How then should these oblations&amp;ndash;which are characterised as not having any motive power with regard to the employment of the food&amp;ndash;be capable of causing us to substitute, in the absence of eating, some other material (than food)?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is non-restriction of the assertions concerning them (i.e. the assertions made concerning certain sacrificial acts are not permanently connected with those acts), because this is seen (in scripture); for a separate fruit, viz. non-obstruction (of the success of the sacrifice), (belongs to them).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We meet in the Vedānta-texts with certain vidyās which are founded on matters subordinate to sacrificial acts. To this class belongs, e.g. the first vidyā of the Cḥāndogya Upanishad, &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the syllable Om as udgītha.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As in the case of the offerings, (Vāyu and Prāṇa. must be held apart). This has been explained (in the Pūrva Mīmāṁsā-sūtra).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The section of the Vājasaneyaka which begins, &amp;lsquo;Voice held, I shall speak&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I. 5, 21). determines Prāṇa to be the best among the organs of the body, viz. speech and so on, and Vāyu to be the best among the Devas, viz. Agni and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the majority of indicatory marks (the fire-altars built of mind, &amp;amp;c. do not form elements of any act); for this (i.e. the indicatory&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;mark) is stronger (than the general subject-matter); this also (has been explained in the Pū. Mī. Sūtras).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Agnirahasya of the Vājasaneyins, in the Brāhmaṇa beginning &amp;lsquo;for in the beginning indeed this was not existent,&amp;rsquo; we read with reference to mind (manas),&amp;rsquo; It saw thirty-six thousand shining fire-altars, belonging to itself, made of mind, built of mind.&amp;rsquo; And, further on, the text makes similar statements about other fanciful fire-altars built of speech, built of breath, built of sight, built of hearing, built of work, built of fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The agni built of mind, &amp;amp;c.) is a particular form of the preceding one (i.e. the agni built of bricks), on account of the leading subject-matter; it is (part of) the act; as in the case of the mānasa cup.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Your supposition, the pūrvapakshin objects, as to those fire-altars being not supplementary to the sacrificial act,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;but altogether independent of it, is untenable. The influence of the leading subject-matter rather compels us to conclude that the instruction given by the text about the agni made of mind and so on, enjoins some particular mode of the same agni which the preceding sections describe as the outcome of a real act &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the transfer (of particulars).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That those agnis enter into the sacrificial action follows&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;moreover from the fact that the text extends to them (the injunctions given about the agni made of bricks). Compare the passage, &amp;lsquo;Thirty-six thousand shining Agnis; each one of them is as large as the previously mentioned Agni.&amp;rsquo; Such extension of injunctions is possible only where there is general equality. The text therefore by extending the determinations relative to the previous agni, i.e. the agni built of bricks, which forms a constituent element of the sacrificial action, to the fanciful agnis, intimates thereby that they also form part of the sacrificial performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;47&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (the agnis rather constitute) a vidyā, on account of the assertion (made by the text).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; sets aside the pūrvapaksha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The agnis built of mind and so on are to be viewed not as complementary to a sacrificial action, but as independent and constituting a vidyā of their own. For the text expressly asserts that &amp;rsquo;they are built of knowledge (vidyā) only,&amp;rsquo; and that &amp;lsquo;by knowledge they are built for him who thus knows.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;48&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because (indicatory marks of that) are seen (in the text).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And that there are to be observed indicatory marks leading to the same conclusion, has already been declared in Sūtra 44.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, under Sūtra 45, it was shown that indicatory marks unaided by other reasons cannot be admitted as proving anything, and it was consequently determined that, owing to the influence of the leading subject-matter, the Agnis form part of the sacrificial action!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;49&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The view that the agnis constitute an independent vidyā) cannot be refuted, owing to the greater force of direct enunciation and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our opponent has no right to determine, on the ground of prakaraṇa, that the agnis are subordinate to the sacrificial action, and so to set aside our view according to which they are independent. For we know from the Pūrvā Mīmāṁsā that direct enunciation (Śruti), indicatory mark&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the connexion and so on (the agnis built, of mind, &amp;amp;c. are independent); in the same way as other cognitions are separate. And there is seen (another case of something having to be withdrawn from the leading subject-matter); this has been explained (in the Pūrva Mīmāṁsā-sūtras).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Independence has, against the general subject-matter, to be assumed for the fire-altars built of mind and so on, for that reason also that the text connects the constituent&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;51&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not also on account of its resembling (the mānasa cup) (can the fires constitute parts of an action); for it is observed (on the ground of Śruti, &amp;amp;c., that they are independent); as in the case of death; for the world does not become (a fire) (because it resembles a fire in some points).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Against the allegation made by the pūrvapakshin that the present case is analogous to that of the mānasa cup, we&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;52&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And from the subsequent (Brāhmaṇa) it follows that being of that kind (i.e. injunction of a mere vidyā) (is the aim) of the text. The connexion (of the fanciful agnis with the real one) is due to the plurality (of details of the real agni which are imaginatively connected with the vidyā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to a subsequent Brāhmaṇa also, viz. the one beginning, &amp;lsquo;That piled agni is this world indeed,&amp;rsquo; we apprehend that what is the purpose of the text is &amp;lsquo;being of that kind,&amp;rsquo; i.e. injunction of a mere vidyā, not injunction of the member of a mere action. For we meet there with the following śloka,&amp;rsquo; By knowledge they ascend there where all wishes are attained. Those skilled in works do not go there, nor those who destitute of knowledge do penance.&amp;rsquo; This verse blames mere works and praises knowledge. A former Brāhmaṇa also, viz. the one beginning, &amp;lsquo;What that orb leads&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Brā. X, 5, 2, 23), concludes with a statement of the fruit of knowledge (&amp;lsquo;Immortal becomes he whose Self is death&amp;rsquo;), and thereby indicates that works are not the chief thing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>53 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;53&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some (maintain the non-existence) of a (separate) Self, on account of the existence (of the Self) where a body is (only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At present we will prove the existence of a Self different from the body in order to establish thereby the qualification (of the Self) for bondage and release. For if there were no Self different from the body, there would be no room for injunctions that have the other world for their result; nor could it be taught of anybody that Brahman is his Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>54 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;54&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is separation (of the Self from the body) because its existence does not depend on the existence of that (viz. the body), but there is not (non-separation); as in the case of perceptive consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The assertion that the Self is not separate from the body cannot be maintained. The Self rather must be something separate from the body, &amp;lsquo;because the existence (of the Self) does not depend on the existence of that (i.e. the body).&amp;rsquo; For if from the circumstance that they are where the body is you conclude that the qualities of the Self are qualities of the body, you also must conclude from the fact that they are not where the body is that they are not qualities of the body, because thereby they show themselves to be different in character from the qualities of the body. Now the (real) qualities of the body, such as form and so on, may be viewed as existing as long as the body exists; life, movement, &amp;amp;c., on the other hand, do not exist even when the body exists, viz. in the state of death. The qualities of the body, again, such as form and so on, are perceived by others; not so the qualities of the Self, such as consciousness, remembrance, and so on. Moreover, we can indeed ascertain the presence of those latter qualities as long as the body exists in the state of life, but we cannot ascertain their non-existence when the body does not exist; for it is possible that even after this body has died the qualities of the Self should continue to exist by passing over into another body. The opposite opinion is thus precluded also for the reason of its being a mere hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>55 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/55/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;55&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the (meditations) connected with members (of sacrificial acts are) not (restricted) to (particular) Śākhās, according to the Veda (to which they belong).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above occasional discussion being terminated, we return to the discussion of the matter in hand.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We meet in the different Śākhās of each Veda with injunctions of vidyās connected with certain members of sacrificial acts, such as the udgītha and the like. Cp. e.g. &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the syllable Om (as) the udgītha&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 1, 1); &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the fivefold Sāman as the five worlds&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. II, 2, I); &amp;lsquo;People say: &amp;ldquo;Hymns, hymns!&amp;rdquo; the hymn is truly this earth&amp;rsquo; (Ait. Ār. II, 1, 2, 1); &amp;lsquo;The piled up fire-altar truly is this world&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Brā. X, 5, 4, 1). A doubt here arises whether the vidyās are enjoined with reference to the udgītha and so on as belonging to a certain Śākhā only or as belonging to all Śākhās. The doubt is raised on the supposition that the udgītha and so on differ in the different Śākhās because the accents, &amp;amp;c. differ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>56 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/56/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/56/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;56&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Or else there is no contradiction (implied in our opinion); as in the case of mantras and the like.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else we may put the matter as follows. There is no reason whatever to suspect a contradiction if we declare certain vidyās enjoined in one Śākhā to be valid for the udgītha and so on belonging to other Śākhās also; for there is no more room for contradiction than in the case of mantras. We observe that mantras, acts, and qualities of acts which are enjoined in one Śākhā are taken over by other Śākhās also. So e.g. the members of certain Yajur-veda Śākhās do not exhibit in their text the mantra, &amp;lsquo;Thou art the kuṭaru &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;rsquo;, which accompanies the taking of the stone (with which the rice-grains are ground); all the same we meet in their text with the following injunction of application, &amp;lsquo;Thou art the cock, with this mantra he takes the stone; or else with the mantra, Thou art the kuṭaru.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>57 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/57/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/57/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;57&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is pre-eminence of the (meditation on) plenitude (i.e. Agni Vaiśvānara in his aggregate form), as in the case of sacrifices; for thus scripture shows.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the legend beginning &amp;lsquo;Prācīnaśāla Aupamanyava,&amp;rsquo; the text speaks of meditations on Vaiśvānara in his distributed&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;as well as his aggregate condition. References to him in his distributed state are made in the passage, &amp;lsquo;Aupamanyava, whom do you meditate on as the Self? He replied: Heaven only, venerable king. He said: The Self which you meditate on is the Vaiśvānara Self called Sutejas;&amp;rsquo; and in the following passages (Cḥ. Up. V, 12-17). A meditation on him in his aggregate state, on the other hand, is referred to in the passage (V, 18), &amp;lsquo;Of that Vaiśvānara Self the head is Sutejas, the eye Viśvarūpa, the breath Pr̥thagvartman, the trunk Bahula, the bladder Rayi, the feet the earth&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>58 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/58/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/58/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;58&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The vidyās are) separate, on account of the difference of words and the like.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding adhikaraṇa we have arrived at the conclusion that a meditation on Vaiśvānara as a whole is the pre-eminent meaning of the text, although special results are stated for meditations on Sutejas and so on. On the ground of this it may be presumed that other meditations also which are enjoined by separate scriptural texts have to be combined into more general meditations. Moreover, we cannot acknowledge a separation of vidyās (acts of cognition; meditations) as long as the object of cognition is the same; for the object constitutes the character of a cognition in the same way as the material offered and the divinity to which the offering is made constitute the character of a sacrifice. Now we understand that the Lord forms the only object of cognition in a number of scriptural passages, although the latter are separate in enunciation; cp. e.g. &amp;lsquo;He consisting of mind, whose body is prāṇa&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 14, 2); &amp;lsquo;Brahman is Ka, Brahman is Kha&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 10, 5); &amp;lsquo;He whose wishes are true, whose purposes are true&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 7, 3). Analogously one and the same Prāṇa is referred to in different texts; cp. &amp;lsquo;Prāṇa indeed is the end of all&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 3, 3); &amp;lsquo;Prāṇa indeed is the oldest and the best&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. V, 1, 1); &amp;lsquo;Prāṇa is father, Prāṇa is mother&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 15, 1). And from the unity of the object of cognition there follows unity of cognition. Nor&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>59 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/59/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/59/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;59&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is (restriction to) option (between the vidyās), on account of their having non-differing results.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The difference of the vidyās having been determined, we now enter on an inquiry whether, according to one&amp;rsquo;s liking, there should be cumulation of the different vidyās or option between them; or else restriction to an optional proceeding (to the exclusion of cumulation). For restriction to cumulation (which might be mentioned as a third alternative) there is no reason, because the separation of the vidyās has been established.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>60 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/60/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/60/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;60&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (vidyās) connected with wishes may, according to one&amp;rsquo;s liking, be cumulated or not; on account of the absence of the former reason.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above Sūtra supplies a counter-instance to the preceding Sūtra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have, on the other hand, vidyās connected with definite wishes; as e.g. Cḥ. Up. III, 15, 2, &amp;lsquo;He who knows that the wind is the child of the regions never weeps for his sons;&amp;rsquo; Cḥ. Up. VII, 1, 5, &amp;lsquo;He who meditates on name as Brahman, walks at will as far as name reaches.&amp;rsquo; In these vidyās which, like actions, effect their own special results by means of their &amp;lsquo;unseen&amp;rsquo; Self, there is no reference to any intuition, and one therefore may, according to one&amp;rsquo;s liking, either cumulate them or not cumulate them; &amp;lsquo;on account of the absence of the former reason,&amp;rsquo; i.e. because there is not the reason for option which was stated in the preceding Sūtra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>61 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/61/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/61/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;61&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;With the (meditations on) members (of sacrificial acts) it is as with their abodes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Are those meditations&amp;ndash;enjoined in the three Vedas&amp;ndash;which rest on members of sacrificial actions such as the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;udgītha to be superadded to each other, or may we proceed with regard to them as we like?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To this doubt the Sūtra replies, &amp;lsquo;it is according to the abodes.&amp;rsquo; As the abiding-places of those meditations, viz. the Stotra and so on, are combined (for the performance of the sacrifice), so those meditations also. For a meditation is subject to what it rests on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>62 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/62/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/62/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;62&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the teaching.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the Stotra and the other members of the sacrifice on which the meditations under discussion rest are taught in the three Vedas, so also the meditations resting on them. The meaning of this remark is that also as far as the mode of information is concerned there is no difference between the members of a sacrificial act and the meditations referring to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>63 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/63/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/63/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;63&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the rectification.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage, &amp;lsquo;From the seat of the Hotr̥ he sets right any mistake committed in the udgītha&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 5, 5), declares that, owing to the might of the meditation on the unity of praṇava and udgītha, the Hotr̥ sets right any mistake he may commit in his work, by means of the work of the Hotr̥.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now, as a meditation mentioned in one Veda is connected (with what is mentioned in another Veda) in the same way as a thing mentioned in another Veda, the above passage suggests the conclusion that all meditations on members of sacrificial acts&amp;ndash;in whatever Veda they may be mentioned&amp;ndash;have to be combined &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>64 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/64/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/64/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;64&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because the text states a quality (of the vidyā) to be common (to the three Vedas).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The text states that the syllable Om which is a quality,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;i.e. the abode of a meditation, is common to the three Vedas, &amp;lsquo;By that syllable the threefold knowledge proceeds. With Om the Adhvaryu gives orders, with Om the Hotr̥ recites, with Om the Udgātr̥ sings.&amp;rsquo; This suggests that, as the abode of the vidyā (viz. the Oṁkāra) is common, the vidyās which abide in it are common also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>65 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/65/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/65/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;65&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The meditations on members of sacrificial actions are) rather not (to be combined), as the text does not state their going together.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The words &amp;lsquo;rather not&amp;rsquo; discard the pūrvapaksha. The meditations resting on members of actions are not to be treated like what they rest on, because scripture does not state their going together. Scripture actually states the going together of the Stotras and other subordinate members of sacrificial action which are enjoined in the three Vedas; cp. passages such as &amp;lsquo;After the taking of the graha or the raising of the camasa he performs the Stotra;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;After the Stotra he recites;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Prastotr̥ sing the Sāman;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Hotr̥ recite the Yājyā for this; &amp;lsquo;and so on. But, on the other hand, there are no analogous texts expressly teaching the going together of the meditations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>66 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/66/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/3/3/66/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;66&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because (scripture) shows it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture moreover shows that the meditations do not go together, viz. in the following passage, &amp;lsquo;A Brahman priest who knows this saves the sacrifice, the sacrificer, and all the priests&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 17, 10). For if all meditations were to be combined, all priests would know them all, and the text could not specially announce that the Brahman priest possessing a certain knowledge thereby saves the others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
