<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 SIDDHĀNTA - THEORY on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 SIDDHĀNTA - THEORY on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/01_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/01_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having been trained in the ways of science, I was simply drawn to Upaniṣad-s when I started reading them in view of the meticulous way the subject is dealt with. The more and more I read the Upaniṣad-s along with commentories of Adi Shankara, an extremely powerful commentary on the original text of Upaniṣad-s, I as a scientist could not but wonder and appreciate them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A scientific approach to any matter/ problem demands the following:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 IN SEARCH OF OUR TRUE NATURE - AN OVERVIEW</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/02_IN_SEARCH_OF_OUR_TRUE_NATURE_-_AN_OVERVIEW/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/02_IN_SEARCH_OF_OUR_TRUE_NATURE_-_AN_OVERVIEW/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our last talk we tried to bring out the differences between karmakāṇḍa and jñānakāṇḍa. It is possible that I have spoken lightly of karmakāṇḍa, but karmakāṇḍa is a very valuable part of Vedas. I was just showing the differences in the content, rather than emphasising the superior ways in which jñānakāṇḍa takes us in the realm of spiritual study. Whosoever has that śraddhā and devotion to karmakāṇḍa details is certainly a superior person. Please do not slacken that śraddhā, as it pays in the long run. All religious activities conceived by the Indian&lt;strong&gt;R̥ṣi-s  - ऋषि&lt;/strong&gt;- have a very big significance in creating peace in our minds.&lt;strong&gt;Śankara - शङ्कर&lt;/strong&gt;makes a conclusive statement about it, calling that all the religious activities are aimed at&lt;strong&gt;Cittaśuddhi - चित्तशुद्धि -&lt;strong&gt;cleansing of the mind. The whole of karmakāṇḍa is highly valuable because it purifies the mind and very soon we come to the realization that purified mind is&lt;/strong&gt;ātmā - आत्मा or Brahma - ब्रह्म.&lt;/strong&gt; I will be wrong if I underrate karmakāṇḍa rituals. The worship, the &lt;strong&gt;pūjā - पूजा&lt;/strong&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;prārthanā - प्रार्थना&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;vrata - व्रत&lt;/strong&gt;that every Indian home does, is equally important in the attainment of peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 AVASTHĀ-TRAYA-PARĪKṣĀ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/04_avasthA-traya-parIxA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/04_avasthA-traya-parIxA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(EXAMINATION OF THREE STATES OF EXISTANCE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We shall do a revision on whatever we discussed in these lectures so that they remain fresh in your minds. Recapitulation is fine as it strengthens the thought pattern and sets deep rooted in your minds.We have found that Vedānta can give a solvable approach to the problems of various facets of our life. We found that there are two sides. One is the ritualistic side. Distinguished from this, you have the Parīkṣa side or the investigation side. Two routes of investigation were suggested - one is Sukha-Duḥkha-parīkṣa and the other is ātmāparīkṣa. In the first one, you do the investigation on the involved question or the involved issue which we covered exhaustively. Equally productive is the other method- ātmaparīkṣa - suggestion to examine the self, to understand one’s true nature. In fact śāstra recommends this parīkṣa more often. Most of the scholars or most of the traditional Vedāntic literature emphasises on ātmaparīkṣa. In my previous lecture I had mentioned about the discussion found in Bṛhahadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad between Yajñavalkya and his two wives Kātyāyani and Maitrēyi. When Maitrēyi asks the husband to show her the way for everlasting happiness, he says that the only way is to find out one’s true nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 PANCA KOŚA VIVĒKA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/05_PANCA_kosha_vivka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/01_siddhAnta_-_THEORY/05_PANCA_kosha_vivka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(KNOWLEDGE OF FIVE SHEATHS OF EXISTANCE)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another equally important prakriya about understanding the ‘self’ isbeautifully explained in Taittirīya Upaniṣad and it is quite interesting. We will now deliberate on this prakriya as it is called as Pañca-kośa-viveka which is contained in the Bhṛguvalli (2) of the said Upaniṣad.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;भृगुर्वै वारुणिः वरुणं पितरं उपससार अधीहि भगवो ब्रह्मेति ॥&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bhr̥gurvai vāruṇiḥ varuṇaṁ pitaraṁ upasasāra adhīhi bhagavō brahmēti.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is seeker called Bhṛgu. He goes to his teacher who is also his father by name Varuṇa.What question he goes with? Master, give me the wisdom of the self; tell me about the self or the causal stuff of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
