<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 LECTURES ON MĀNḌŪKYA UPANIṣAD on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 LECTURES ON MĀNḌŪKYA UPANIṣAD on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 OMKĀRA UPĀSANA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/01_omkAra_upAsana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/01_omkAra_upAsana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(MEDITATION ON OMKĀRA)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad is one of the ten major Upaniṣad-s admitted by Sampradāya. Sampradāya holds this Upaniṣad very high. In fact there is a śloka to show what status this Upaniṣad earns in the eyes of sampradāya. Muktikopaniṣad declares that the study of only Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad is sufficient to liberate an ardent student of Vedānta:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;एकं माण्डूक्यमेव अलं मुमुक्षूणाम् विमुक्तये ।&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ēkaṁ māṇḍūkyam-ēva alaṁ mumukṣūṇām vimuktayē.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That means you can bypass all other details enumerated in other Upaniṣad -s and go straight to Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad and that is the right thing to do. Mumukṣu is a sādhaka who is after liberation. For his liberation, study of this Upaniṣad will give him the necessary guide lines and there is no need to waste time going through other vedāntic texts- says the axiom. Such a point of view on this Upaniṣad is reasonable because as I see there is no waste of time at all here- not a syllable, not a word which is extra is stated in this text than what is required. It is as straight as the flight of an arrow. There are no stories told in this Upaniṣad, no ākhyāyika and no dialogue between the master and the disciple as found in other Upaniṣad-s. Brevity of this order or an accuracy of this order is not seen elsewhere. That is why it is remarkable. People have rightly called it the best. Let us study the aspect of Omkāra as described in First Mantra of Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 STATES OF EXISTANCE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/02_STATES_OF_EXISTANCE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/03_LECTURES_ON_mAnDUkya_upaniShad/02_STATES_OF_EXISTANCE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will discuss now as to what clue a sādhaka gets from the study of the different states of existence of man as enumerated in Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad.The first state is- (Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad 3)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;जागरितस्थानः बहिष्प्रज्ञः सप्ताङ्ग एकोनविंशतिमुखः स्थूलभुग्वैश्वानरः प्रथमः पादः॥&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jāgarita-sthānaḥ bahiḥ-prajñaḥ saptāṅga ēkōnaviṁśati-mukhaḥ sthūla-bhuk vaiśvānaraḥ prathamaḥ pādaḥ.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The waking state outwardly conscious, having seven limbs and nineteen doors, enjoying gross objects common to all, is the first State.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You are in a capacity of cognizing the world outside of you. Bahiṣprajñaḥ–your cognising capacity is outward. Then – saptāńgaḥ –You are seven limbed. Ekonavimśati mukhaḥ –You have one less than twenty that is nineteen faces. These are the ventilators or the outlets by which you contact the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
