<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 first pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;fourth-adhyāya&#34;&gt;FOURTH ADHYĀYA&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-pāda&#34;&gt;FIRST PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Repetition (of the mental functions of knowing, meditating, &amp;amp;c., is required) on account of the text giving instruction more than once.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The third adhyāya was taken up chiefly with a discussion of the means of knowledge as related to the higher and lower vidyās. In the fourth adhyāya we shall now discuss the fruits of knowledge, and as occasion suggests some other topics also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of an indicatory mark.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An indicatory mark also gives to understand that repetition is required. For, in the section treating of meditation&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;on the udgītha, the text rejects the meditation on the udgītha viewed as the sun, because its result is one sun only, and (in the clause &amp;lsquo;Do thou resolve his rays,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.) enjoins a meditation on his manifold rays as leading to the possession of many suns (Cḥ. Up. I, 5, 1; 2); which shows that the repetition of meditations is something well known. Now as other meditations are meditations no less than the one referred to, it follows that repetition holds good for all of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nor is it true that the doctrine of identity would imply that nobody is entitled to works, &amp;amp;c., and is contrary to perception and so on. For we admit that before true knowledge springs up, the soul is implicated in the transmigratory state, and that this state constitutes the sphere of the operation of perception and so on. On the other hand texts such as &amp;lsquo;But when the Self only has become all this, how should he see another?&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., teach that as soon as true knowledge springs up, perception, &amp;amp;c., are no longer valid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not in the symbol (is the Self to be contemplated); for he (the meditating person) (may) not (view symbols as being the Self).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on mind as Brahman; this is said with reference to the body. Let a man meditate on ether as Brahman; this is said with reference to the Devas&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 18, 1); &amp;lsquo;Āditya is Brahman, this is the doctrine&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Cḥ. Up. III, 19, 1); &amp;lsquo;He who meditates on name as Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 1, 5). With regard to these and similar meditations on symbols a doubt arises whether the Self is to be apprehended in them also, or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A contemplation of Brahman (is to be superinduced on symbols of Brahman), on account of the exaltation (thereby bestowed on the symbols).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With regard to the texts quoted above there arises another doubt, viz. whether the contemplation of Āditya and so on is to be superimposed on Brahman, or the contemplation of Brahman on Āditya and so on &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But whence does this doubt arise?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the absence of a decisive reason, owing to the grammatical co-ordination. For we observe in the sentences quoted a co-ordination of the term &amp;lsquo;Brahman&amp;rsquo; with the terms &amp;lsquo;Āditya,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. &amp;lsquo;Āditya is Brahman,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Prāṇa is Brahman,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Lightning is Brahman;&amp;rsquo; the text exhibiting the two members of each clause in the same case. And here there is no obvious occasion for co-ordination because the words &amp;lsquo;Brahman&amp;rsquo; on the one hand, and &amp;lsquo;Āditya&amp;rsquo; and so on on the other hand, denote different things; not any more than there exists a relation of co-ordination which could be expressed by the sentence &amp;lsquo;The ox is a horse.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the ideas of Āditya and so on (are to be superimposed) on the members (of the sacrificial action); owing to the effectuation (of the result of the sacrifice).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;He who burns up these, let a man meditate upon him as udgītha&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 3, i); &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the fivefold Sāman in the worlds&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. II, 2, i); &amp;lsquo;Let a man meditate on the sevenfold Sāman in speech&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. II, 8, i); &amp;lsquo;This earth is the R̥c, fire is Sāman&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 6, i).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sitting (a man is to meditate), on account of the possibility.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As meditations connected with members of sacrificial action depend on action, we need not raise the question whether they are to be carried on in a sitting, or any other posture. The same holds good in the case of perfect intuition, since knowledge depends on its object only. With regard to all other meditations, on the other hand, the author of the Sūtras raises the question whether they may be undertaken indifferently by a person standing, sitting, or lying down, or only by a person sitting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of thoughtfulness.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover also the word &amp;rsquo;thoughtfulness&amp;rsquo; denotes a lengthened carrying on of the same train of ideas. Now &amp;rsquo;thoughtfulness&amp;rsquo; we ascribe to those whose mind is concentrated on one and the same object, while their look is fixed and their limbs move only very slightly. We say e.g. that the crane is thoughtful, or that a wife whose husband has gone on a journey is thoughtful. Now such thoughtfulness is easy for those who sit; and we therefore conclude herefrom also that meditation is the occupation of a sitting person.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And with reference to immobility (scripture ascribes thought to the earth, &amp;amp;c.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in the passage &amp;lsquo;The earth thinks as it were&amp;rsquo; scripture ascribes thought to the earth, with regard to its immobility. This also helps us to infer that meditation is the occupation of one who is sitting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And Smr̥ti-passages say the same.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Authoritative authors also teach in their Smr̥tis that a sitting posture subserves the act of meditation: cp. e.g. Bha. Gītā VI. 11,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having made a firm seat for one&amp;rsquo;s self on a pure spot.&amp;rsquo; For the same reason the Yogaśāstra teaches different sitting posture, viz. the so-called lotus position and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Where concentration of mind (is possible), there (meditation may be carried on), on account of there being no difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A doubt here arises with regard to direction, place, and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;time, viz. whether any restrictive rules exist or not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Against the view of those who maintain that such rules exist because we have analogous rules concerning the locality, &amp;amp;c., of Vedic works, the Sūtrakāra remarks that all rules concerning direction, place, and time depend on the aim merely; that is to say: Let a man meditate at whatever time, in whatever place and facing whatever region, he may with case manage to concentrate his mind. For while scripture prescribes an easterly direction, the time of forenoon, and a spot sloping towards the cast for certain sacrifices, no such specific rules are recorded for meditation, since the requisite concentration may be managed indifferently anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Up to death (meditations have to be repeated); for then also it is thus seen in scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first adhikaraṇa (of the present adhyāya) has established that repetition is to be observed with regard to all meditations. But now a distinction is made. Those meditations which aim at complete knowledge, terminate&amp;ndash;in the same way as the beating of the rice grains is terminated by the husks becoming detached from the grains&amp;ndash;with their effect being accomplished; for as soon as the effect, i.e. perfect knowledge, has been obtained, no further effort can be commanded since scriptural instruction does not apply to him who knows that Brahman&amp;ndash;which is not the object of injunction&amp;ndash;constitutes his Self. On the other hand a doubt arises whether the devotee is to repeat those meditations which aim at certain forms of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On the attainment of this (viz. Brahman) (there take place) the non-clinging and the destruction of later and earlier sins; this being declared (by scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The supplement to the third adhyāya is finished herewith, and an inquiry now begins concerning the fruit of the knowledge of Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The doubt here presents itself whether, on the attainment of Brahman, sins the results of which are opposed in nature to such attainment are extinguished or not. They cannot possibly be extinguished, the pūrvapakshin maintains, before they have given their results, because the purpose of all works is their result. For we understand from scripture that work possesses the power of producing results; if, therefore, the work would perish without the enjoyment of its result, scripture would thereby be rendered nugatory. Smr̥ti also declares that &amp;lsquo;works do not perish.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of the other (i.e. good works) also there is, in the same way, non-clinging; but at death.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding adhikaraṇa it has been shown that, according to scriptural statements, all natural sin&amp;ndash;which is the cause of the soul&amp;rsquo;s bondage&amp;ndash;does, owing to the power of knowledge, either not cling to the soul or undergo destruction. One might now think that works of religious duty which are enjoined by scripture are not opposed to knowledge also founded on scripture. In order to dispel this notion the reasoning of the last adhikaraṇa is formally extended to the case under discussion. For him who knows there is &amp;lsquo;in the same way,&amp;rsquo; i.e. as in the case of sin, &amp;rsquo;non-clinging&amp;rsquo; and destruction &amp;lsquo;of the other also,&amp;rsquo; i.e. of good works also; because such works also, as productive of their own results, would be apt to obstruct thereby the result of knowledge. Scripture also&amp;ndash;in passages such as &amp;lsquo;He overcomes both&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22)&amp;ndash;declares that good works are extinguished no less than evil ones, and the extinction of works which depends on the cognition of the Self not being an agent is the same in the case of good and of evil works, and moreover there is a passage making a general statement without any distinction, viz. &amp;lsquo;And his works are extinguished&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 2, 8). And even there where the text mentions evil works only, we must consider good works also to be implied therein, because the results of the latter also are inferior to the result of knowledge. Moreover scripture directly applies the term &amp;rsquo;evil works&amp;rsquo; to good works also, viz. in the passage, Cḥ. Up. VIII, 4, i, &amp;lsquo;Day and night do not pass that bank,&amp;rsquo; where good works are mentioned together with evil works, and finally the term &amp;rsquo;evil&amp;rsquo; is without any distinction applied to all things mentioned before, &amp;lsquo;All evil things&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But only those former (works) whose effects have not yet begun (are destroyed by knowledge); because (scripture states) that (i.e. the death of the body) to be the term.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the two preceding adhikaraṇas it has been proved that good as well as evil works are annihilated through knowledge. We now have to consider the question whether this annihilation extends, without distinction, to those works whose effects have already begun to operate as well as to those whose effects have not yet begun; or only to works of the latter kind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the Agnihotra and the like (tend) towards the same effect; scripture showing this.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The reasoning as to evil deeds has been extended to the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;non-clinging and destruction of good deeds also. Against a notion which now might present itself, viz. that this extension comprehends all good works alike, the Sūtrakāra remarks, &amp;lsquo;But the Agnihotra and so on.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; is meant to set that notion aside. Works of permanent obligation enjoined by the Veda, such as the Agnihotra, tend &amp;rsquo;towards the same effect,&amp;rsquo; i e. have the same effect as knowledge. For this is declared by texts such as the following one, &amp;lsquo;Brāhmaṇas seek to know him by the study of the Veda, by sacrifices, by gifts&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 22).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For (there is) also (a class of good works) other than this, according to some. (There is agreement) of both (teachers) (as to the fate of those works.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;For also one other than this,&amp;rsquo; i.e. there is also a class of good works different from works of permanent obligation, viz. those good works which are performed with a view to a fruit. Of those latter works the passage quoted above from some Śākhā (&amp;lsquo;His friends enter on his good works&amp;rsquo;) teaches the application. And first of those works Sūtra 14 teaches that, in the same way as evil deeds, they do not cling to the doer or else are destroyed. Both teachers, Jaimini as well as Bādarāyaṇa, are agreed that such works, undertaken for the fulfilment of some special wish, do not contribute towards the origination of true knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For (the text) &amp;lsquo;Whatever he does with knowledge&amp;rsquo; (intimates that).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding adhikaraṇa the following conclusion has been established:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Works of permanent obligation such as the Agnihotra, if performed by a person desirous of release with a view to release, lead to the extinction of evil deeds committed, thus become a means of the purification of the mind, and thereby cause the attainment of Brahman, which leads to final release; they therefore operate towards the same effect as the knowledge of Brahman. Now the Agnihotra and similar works are either connected with a special knowledge based on the constituent members of the sacrificial work, or absolute (non-connected with such knowledge). This appears from scriptural texts such as &amp;lsquo;He who knowing this sacrifices; he who knowing this makes an offering; he who knowing this recites; he who knowing this sings; therefore let a man make him who knows this his Brahman-priest&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/4/1/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But having destroyed by fruition the two other (sets of work) he becomes one with Brahman.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been shown that all good and evil deeds whose effects have not yet begun are extinguished by the power of knowledge. &amp;lsquo;The two others,&amp;rsquo; on the other hand, i.e. those good and evil works whose effects have begun, a man&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;has at first to exhaust by the fruition of their consequences, and then he becomes one with Brahman. This appears from scriptural passages such as &amp;lsquo;For him there is delay so long as he is not delivered (from the body), then he will become one with Brahman&amp;rsquo;(Cḥ. Up. VI, 14, 2); and &amp;lsquo;Being Brahman he goes to Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
