<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;fourth-pāda&#34;&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thus the vital airs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the third pāda it has been shown that a conflict of Vedic passages as to ether, &amp;amp;c., does not exist. The same is now done in this fourth pāda with regard to the vital airs. On the one hand the chapters treating of the origin of things do not record an origin of the vital airs; so e.g. (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 3) &amp;lsquo;It sent forth fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.; and (Taitt. Up. II, 1) &amp;lsquo;From that Self sprang ether,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. On the other hand it is said expressly in some places that the vital airs were not produced. The following passage, e.g. &amp;lsquo;Non-being indeed was this in the beginning; they say: what was that non-being? those r̥shis indeed were the non-being in the beginning; they say: who are those r̥shis? the vital airs indeed are the r̥shis&amp;rsquo; (Śat. Br. VI, 1, 1, 1), states that the vital airs existed before the origin of things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the impossibility of a secondary (origin of the prāṇas).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Against the objection that the origin of the prāṇas must be understood in a secondary sense because the text states that they existed before the origin of the world, the Sūtrakāra declares &amp;lsquo;on account of the impossibility of a secondary origin.&amp;rsquo; The statement as to the origin of the prāṇas cannot be taken in a secondary sense because therefrom would result the abandonment of a general assertion. For after the text has asserted that the knowledge of everything depends on the knowledge of one (&amp;lsquo;What is that through which when it is known everything else becomes known?&amp;rsquo; Mu. Up. I, 1, 3), it goes on to say, in order to prove that assertion, that &amp;lsquo;From him is born prāṇa,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Mu. Up. II, 1, 3). Now the assertion is made good only if the whole world including the prāṇas is an effect of Brahman, because then there is no effect independent of the material cause; if on the other hand the statement as to the origin of the prāṇas were taken in a secondary sense, the assertion would thereby be stultified. The text, moreover, makes some concluding statements about the matter asserted, &amp;lsquo;The Person is all this, sacrifice, penance, Brahman, the highest Immortal&amp;rsquo; (II, 1, 10), and &amp;lsquo;Brahman alone is all this; it is the Best.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of that (word which indicates origin) being enunciated at first (in connexion with the prāṇas).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the scriptural statement about the origin of the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;prāṇas is to be taken in its literal sense just as the statements about the ether, &amp;amp;c., appears from that circumstance also that the one word which (in the passage from the Mu. Up.) indicates origination, viz. &amp;lsquo;is born&amp;rsquo; (jāyate in the first place connected with the prāṇas and has afterwards to be joined with ether, &amp;amp;c., also (&amp;lsquo;from him is born breath, mind, and all organs of sense, ether, air,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.). Now as it is a settled matter that the phrase &amp;lsquo;is born&amp;rsquo; must be taken in its primary sense with reference to ether and so on, it follows that the origin of the prāṇas also to which the same word is applied must be understood as a real origin. For it would be impossible to decide that a word enunciated once only in one chapter and one sentence, and connected with many other words, has in some cases to be taken in its primary sense, and in others in a secondary sense; for such a decision would imply want of uniformity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Because speech is preceded by that (viz. fire and the other elements).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although in the chapter, &amp;lsquo;That sent forth fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., the origin of the prāṇas is not mentioned, the origin of the three elements, fire, water, and earth only being stated, nevertheless, the fact of the text declaring that speech, prāṇa, and mind presuppose fire, water, and earth&amp;ndash;which in their turn have Brahman for their causal substance&amp;ndash;proves that they&amp;ndash;and, by parity of reasoning, all prāṇas&amp;ndash;have sprung from Brahman. That speech, prāṇa, and mind presuppose fire, water, and earth is told in the same chapter, &amp;lsquo;For truly, my child, mind consists of earth, breath of water,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The prāṇas are) seven, on account of this being understood (from scriptural passages) and of the specification (of those seven).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So far we have shown that there is in reality no conflict of scriptural passages regarding the origin of the prāṇas. It will now be shown that there is also no conflict regarding their number. The chief vital air (mukhya prāṇa) will be discussed later on. For the present the Sūtrakāra the number of the other prāṇas. A doubt arises here owing to the conflicting nature of the scriptural passages. In one place seven prāṇas are mentioned, &amp;lsquo;The seven prāṇas spring from him&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 1, 8). In another place eight prāṇas are mentioned as being grahas, &amp;lsquo;Eight grahas there are and eight atigrahas&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 2, 1). In another place nine, &amp;lsquo;Seven are the prāṇas of the head, two the lower ones&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Saṁh. V, 3, 2, 5). Sometimes ten, &amp;lsquo;Nine prāṇas indeed are in men, the navel is the tenth&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Saṁh. V, 3, 2, 3). Sometimes eleven, &amp;lsquo;Ten are these prāṇas in man, and Ātman is the eleventh&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 9, 4). Sometimes twelve, &amp;lsquo;All touches have their centre in the skin,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Br̥. Up. II, 4, 11). Sometimes thirteen, &amp;lsquo;The eye and what can be seen,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Pr. Up. IV, 8).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (there are also, in addition to the seven prāṇas mentioned,) the hands and so on. This being a settled matter, therefore (we must) not (conclude) thus (viz. that there are seven prāṇas only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the seven prāṇas scripture mentions other prāṇas also, such as the hands, &amp;amp;c., &amp;lsquo;The hand is one graha and that is seized by work as the atigraha; for with the hands one does work&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 2, 8), and similar passages. And as it is settled that there are more than seven, the number seven may be explained as being contained within the greater number. For wherever there is a conflict between a higher and a lower number, the higher number has to be accepted because the lower one is contained within it; while the higher is not contained within the lower. We therefore must not conclude that, in deference to the lower&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (they are) minute.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The author of the Sūtras adds another characteristic quality of the prāṇas. The prāṇas under discussion must be viewed as minute. By their minuteness we have to understand subtilty and limited size; but not atomic size, as otherwise they would be incapable of producing effects which extend over the whole body. They must be subtle; for if they were big the persons surrounding a dying man would see them coming out from the body at the moment of death, as a snake comes out of its hole. They must be limited; for if they were all-pervading the scriptural statements as to their passing out of the body, going and coming, would be contradicted thereby, and it could not be established that the individual soul is &amp;rsquo;the essence of the qualities of that&amp;rsquo; (i.e. the manas; cp. II, 3, 29). Should it be said that they may be all-pervading, but at the same time appear as functions (vr̥tti) in the body only, we rejoin that only a function can constitute an instrument. Whatever effects perception, may it be a function or something else, just that is an instrument for us. The disagreement is therefore about a name only, and the assumption of the instruments (prāṇas) being all-pervading is thus purposeless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the best (i.e. the chief vital air).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtra extends to the chief vital air (mukhya prāṇa) a quality already asserted of the other prāṇas, viz. being an effect of Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But, an objection may be raised, it has already been stated of all prāṇas without difference that they are effects of Brahman; e.g. the passage, &amp;lsquo;From him&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;is born breath, mind, and all organs of sense&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II. 1, 3), states the origin of prāṇa separately from the senses and the manas; and there are other passages also such as &amp;lsquo;He sent forth prāṇa&amp;rsquo; (Pr. Up. VI, 4). Why then the formal extension?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The chief prāṇa is) neither air nor function, on account of its being mentioned separately.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An inquiry is now started concerning the nature of that chief prāṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that the prāṇa is, according to Śruti, nothing but air. For Śruti says, &amp;lsquo;Breath is air; that air assuming five forms is prāṇa, apāna, vyāna, udāna, samāna.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or else the pūrvapaksha may be formulated according to the view of another philosophical doctrine, and prāṇa may be considered as the combined function of all organs. For so the followers of another doctrine (viz. the Sāṅkhyas) teach, &amp;lsquo;The five airs, prāṇa, &amp;amp;c., are the common function of the instruments &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But (the prāṇa is subordinate to the soul) like the eye, &amp;amp;c., on account of being taught with them (the eye, &amp;amp;c.), and for other reasons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; sets aside the independence of the prāṇa. As the eye and so on stand, like the subjects of a king, in mere subordinate relation to the acting and enjoying of the soul and are not independent, so the chief vital air also, occupying a position analogous to that of a king&amp;rsquo;s minister, stands in an entirely subordinate relation to the soul and is not independent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (its) not being an instrument the objection is not (valid); for thus (scripture) declares.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The objection urged, viz. that there would result another sense-object, is not valid; because the prāṇa is not an&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;instrument. For we do not assume that the prāṇa is, like the eye, an organ because it determines a special sense-object. Nor is it on that account devoid of an effect; since scripture declares that the chief vital air has a specific effect which cannot belong to the other prāṇas. For in the so-called colloquies of the prāṇas we read in the beginning, &amp;lsquo;The prāṇas quarrelled together who was best;&amp;rsquo; after that we read, &amp;lsquo;He by whose departure the body seems worse than worst, he is the best of you;&amp;rsquo; thereupon the text, after showing how, on the successive departure of speech and so on, the life of the body, although deprived of one particular function, went on as before, finally relates that as soon as the chief prāṇa was about to depart all other prāṇas became loosened and the body was about to perish; which shows that the body and all the senses subsist by means of the chief prāṇa. The same thing is declared by another passage, &amp;lsquo;Then prāṇa as the best said to them: Be not deceived; I alone dividing myself fivefold support this body and keep it&amp;rsquo; (Pr. Up. II, 3). Another passage, viz. &amp;lsquo;With prāṇa guarding the lower nest&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 12), shows that the guarding of the body depends on prāṇa. Again, two other passages show that the nourishing of the body depends on prāṇa, &amp;lsquo;From whatever limb prāṇa goes away that limb withers&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 3, 19), and &amp;lsquo;What we eat and drink with it supports the other vital breaths.&amp;rsquo; And another passage declares that the soul&amp;rsquo;s departing and staying depend on prāṇa, &amp;lsquo;What is it by whose departure I shall depart, and by whose staying I shall stay?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It is designated as having five functions like mind.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The chief vital air has its specific effect for that reason also that in scripture it is designated as having five functions, prāṇa, apāna, vyāna, udāna, samāna. This distinction of functions is based on a distinction of effects. Prāṇa is the forward-function whose work is aspiration, &amp;amp;c.; apāna is the backward-function whose work is inspiration, &amp;amp;c.; vyāna is that which, abiding in the junction of the two,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And it is minute.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And the chief vital air is to be considered as minute like the other prāṇas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here also we have to understand by minuteness that the chief vital air is subtle and of limited size, not that is of atomic size; for by means of its five functions it pervades the entire body. It must be viewed as subtle because when passing out of the body it is not perceived by a bystander, and as limited because scripture speaks of its passing out, going and coming.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But there is guidance (of the prāṇas) by fire, &amp;amp;c., on account of that being declared by scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here there arises a discussion whether the prāṇas of which we have been treating are able to produce their effects by their own power or only in so far as guided by divinities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that the prāṇas being endowed with the capacity of producing their effects act from their own power. If we, moreover, admitted that the prāṇas act only in so far as guided by divinities, it would follow that those guiding divinities are the enjoyers (of the fruits of the actions), and the individual soul would thus cease to be an enjoyer. Hence the prāṇas act from their own power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(It is not so) (because the prāṇas are connected) with that to which the prāṇas belong (i.e. the individual soul), (a thing we know) from scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although there are divinities guiding the prāṇas, yet we learn from scripture that those prāṇas are connected with the embodied soul which is the Lord of the aggregate of&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;instruments of action. The following passage, e.g. &amp;lsquo;where the sight has entered into the void there is the person of the eye; the eye itself is the instrument of seeing. He who knows, let me smell this, he is the Self; the nose is the instrument of smelling, declares that the prāṇas are connected with the embodied soul only. Moreover the plurality of the divinities guiding the organs renders it impossible that they should be the enjoyers in this body. For that there is in this body only one embodied enjoyer is understood from the possibility of the recognition of identity and so on &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the permanence of this (viz. the embodied soul).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This embodied soul abides permanently in this body as the enjoyer, since it can be affected by good and evil and can experience pleasure and pain. Not so the gods; for they exist in the state of highest power and glory and cannot possibly enter, in this wretched body, into the condition of enjoyers. So scripture also says, &amp;lsquo;Only what is good approaches him; verily evil does not approach the devas&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 5. 20).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;They (the prāṇas) are senses, on account of being so designated, with the exception of the best (the mukhya prāṇa).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have treated of the mukhya prāṇa and the other&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;eleven prāṇas in due order.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now there arises another doubt, viz. whether the other prāṇas are functions of the mukhya prāṇa or different beings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin that they are mere functions, on account of scriptural statement. For scripture, after having spoken of the chief prāṇa and the other prāṇas in proximity, declares that those other prāṇas have their Self in the chief prāṇa, &amp;lsquo;Well, let us all assume his form. Thereupon they all assumed his form&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 5, 2l).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the scriptural statement of difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The prāṇa is everywhere spoken of as different from speech, &amp;amp;c. The passage, e.g. beginning with &amp;lsquo;They said to speech&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. I, 3, 2), enumerates speech, &amp;amp;c., which were overwhelmed by the evil of the Asuras, concludes thereupon the section treating of speech, &amp;amp;c., and then specially mentions the mukhya prāṇa as overcoming the Asuras, in the paragraph beginning &amp;lsquo;Then they said to the breath in the mouth.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the difference of characteristics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is moreover a difference of characteristics between the chief prāṇa and the other prāṇas. When speech &amp;amp;c. are asleep, the chief prāṇa alone is awake. The chief prāṇa alone is not reached by death, while the other prāṇas are. The staying and departing of the chief prāṇa&amp;ndash;not that of the sense-organs&amp;ndash;is the cause of the maintenance and the destruction of the body. The sense-organs, on the other hand, are the cause of the perception of the sense-objects, not the chief prāṇa. Thus there are manifold differences distinguishing the prāṇa from the senses, and this also shows the latter to be different in being from the prāṇa&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the fashioning of names and forms belongs to him who renders tripartite, on account of the teaching (of scripture).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the chapter treating of the Being (sat), subsequently to the account of the creation of fire, water, and food (earth), the following statement is made, &amp;lsquo;That divinity thought, let me now enter those three beings with this living Self (jīva ātmā), and let me evolve names and forms &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;;&amp;ndash;let me make each of these three tripartite&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, Kh 3, 2; 3).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The flesh, &amp;amp;c., originates from earth, according to the scriptural statement; and (so also) in the case of the two other (elements).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From tripartite earth when assimilated by man there are produced as its effects flesh, &amp;amp;c., according to scripture. For the text says, &amp;lsquo;Food (earth) when eaten becomes threefold; its grossest portion becomes feces, its middle portion flesh, its subtlest portion mind.&amp;rsquo; The meaning is that the tripartite earth is eaten in the shape of food such as rice, barley, &amp;amp;c.; that its grossest parts are discharged in the form of feces, that its middle parts nourish the flesh of the body, and its subtlest parts feed the mind. Analogously we have to learn from the text the effects of the two other elements, viz. fire and water; viz. that urine, blood, and breath are the effects of water; bone, marrow, and speech those of fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/2/4/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But on account of their distinctive nature there is a (distinctive) designation of them.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; repels the objection raised. By &amp;lsquo;distinctive nature&amp;rsquo; we have to understand preponderance. Although all things are tripartite, yet we observe in different places a preponderance of different elements; heat preponderates in fire, water in all that is liquid, food in earth. This special tripartition aims at rendering possible the distinctions and terms of ordinary life. For if the tripartition resulted in sameness, comparable to that of the three strands of a tripartite rope, we could not distinguish&amp;ndash;and speak of as distinguished&amp;ndash;the three elements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
