<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;४ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 fourth pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;fourth-pāda&#34;&gt;FOURTH PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that some (mention) that which is based on inference (i.e. the pradhāna); we deny this, because (the term alluded to) refers to what is contained in the simile of the body (i.e. the body itself); and (that the text) shows.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding part of this work&amp;ndash;as whose topic there has been set forth an enquiry into Brahman&amp;ndash;we have at first defined Brahman (I, 1, 2); we have thereupon refuted the objection that that definition applies to the pradhāna also, by showing that there is no scriptural authority for the latter (I, 1, 5), and we have shown in detail that the common purport of all Vedānta-texts is to set forth the doctrine that Brahman, and not the pradhāṇa, is the cause of the world. Here, however, the Sānkhya again raises an objection which he considers not to have been finally disposed of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the subtle (body is meant by the term avyakta) on account of its capability (of being so designated).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been asserted, under the preceding Sūtra, that the term &amp;rsquo;the Undeveloped&amp;rsquo; signifies, on account of the general&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;subject-matter and because the body only remains, the body and not the pradhāna of the Sānkhyas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But here the following doubt arises: How can the word &amp;lsquo;undeveloped&amp;rsquo; appropriately denote the body which, as a gross and clearly appearing thing, should rather be called vyakta, i.e. that which is developed or manifested?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Such a previous seminal condition of the world may be admitted) on account of its dependency on him (the Lord); (for such an admission is) according to reason.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here a new objection is raised.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If, the opponent says, in order to prove the possibility of the body being called undeveloped you admit that this world in its antecedent seminal condition before either names or forms are evolved can be called undeveloped, you virtually concede the doctrine that the pradhāna is the cause of the world. For we Sānkhyas understand by the term pradhāna nothing but that antecedent condition of the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the pradhāna cannot be meant) because&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;there is no statement as to (the avyakta) being something to be cognised.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sānkhyas, moreover, represent the pradhāna as something to be cognised in so far as they say that from the knowledge of the difference of the constitutive elements of the pradhāna and of the soul there results the desired isolation of the soul. For without a knowledge of the nature of those constitutive elements it is impossible to cognise the difference of the soul from them. And somewhere they teach that the pradhāna is to be cognised by him who wishes to attain special powers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And if you maintain that the text does speak (of the pradhāna as an object of knowledge) we deny that; for the intelligent (highest) Self is meant, on account of the general subject-matter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the Sānkhya raises a new objection, and maintains that the averment made in the last Sūtra is not proved, since the text later on speaks of the pradhāna&amp;ndash;which had been referred to as the Undeveloped&amp;ndash;as an object of knowledge. &amp;lsquo;He who has perceived that which is without sound, without touch, without form, without decay, without taste, eternal, without smell, without beginning, without end, beyond the great and unchangeable, is freed from the jaws of death&amp;rsquo; (Ka. Up. II, 3, 15). For here the text speaks of the pradhāna,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And there is question and explanation relative to three things only (not to the pradhāna).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To the same conclusion we are led by the consideration of the circumstance that the Kaṭḥavallī-upanishad brings forward, as subjects of discussion, only three things, viz. the fire sacrifice, the individual soul, and the highest Self. These three things only Yama explains, bestowing thereby the boons he had granted, and to them only the questions of Naciketas refer. Nothing else is mentioned or enquired&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the case of the term avyakta) is like that of the term mahat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the Sānkhyas employ the term &amp;rsquo;the Great one,&amp;rsquo; to denote the first-born entity, which is mere existence  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(? viz. the intellect), the term has a different meaning in Vedic use. This we see from its being connected with the Self, &amp;amp;c. in such passages as the following, &amp;lsquo;The great Self is beyond the Intellect&amp;rsquo; (Ka. Up. I, 3, 10); &amp;lsquo;The great omnipresent Self (Ka. Up. I, 2, 23); &amp;lsquo;I know that great person&amp;rsquo; (Śve. Up. III, 8). We thence conclude that the word avyakta also, where it occurs in the Veda, cannot denote the pradhāna.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(It cannot be maintained that ajā means the&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;pradhāna) because no special characteristic is stated; as in the case of the cup.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the advocate of the pradhāna comes again forward and maintains that the absence of scriptural authority for the pradhāna is not yet proved. For, he says, we have the following mantra (Śve. Up. IV, 5), &amp;lsquo;There is one ajā &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, red, white, and black, producing manifold offspring of the same nature. There is one ajā who loves her and lies by her; there is another who leaves her after having enjoyed her.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But the (elements) beginning with light (are meant by the term ajā); for some read so in their text.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the term ajā we have to understand the causal matter of the four classes of beings, which matter has sprung from the highest Lord and begins with light, i.e. comprises fire, water, and earth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; (in the Sūtra) gives emphasis to the assertion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This ajā is to be considered as comprising three elementary substances, not as consisting of three guṇas in the Sānkhya sense. We draw this conclusion from the fact that one śākhā, after having related how fire, water, and earth sprang from the highest Lord, assigns to them red colour, and so on. &amp;lsquo;The red colour of burning fire&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the statement of the assumption (of a metaphor) there is nothing contrary to reason (in ajā denoting the causal matter); just as in the case of honey (denoting the sun) and similar cases.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word ajā neither expresses that fire, water, and earth belong to the goat species, nor is it to be explained as meaning &amp;lsquo;unborn;&amp;rsquo; it rather expresses an assumption, i.e. it intimates the assumption of the source of all beings (which source comprises fire, water, and earth), being compared to a she-goat. For as accidentally some she-goat might be partly red, partly white, partly black, and might have many young goats resembling her in colour, and as some he-goat might love her and lie by her, while some other he-goat might leave her after having enjoyed her; so the universal causal matter which is tri-coloured, because comprising fire, water, and earth, produces many inanimate and animate beings similar to itself, and is enjoyed by the souls fettered by Nescience, while it is abandoned by those souls which have attained true knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The assertion that there is scriptural authority for the pradhāna, &amp;amp;c. can) also not (be based) on the mention of the number (of the Sānkhya categories), on account of the diversity (of the categories) and on account of the excess (over the number of those categories).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The attempt to base the Sānkhya doctrine on the mantra speaking of the ajā having failed, the Sānkhya again comes forward and points to another mantra: &amp;lsquo;He in whom the five &amp;ldquo;five-people&amp;rdquo; and the ether rest, him alone I believe to be the Self; I who know believe him to be Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 17). In this mantra we have one word which expresses the number five, viz. the five-people, and then another word, viz. five, which qualifies the former; these two words together therefore convey the idea of five pentads, i.e. twenty-five. Now as many beings as the number twenty-five presupposes, just so many categories the Sānkhya system counts. Cp. Sānkhya Kārikā, 3: &amp;lsquo;The fundamental causal substance (i.e. the pradhāna) is not an effect. Seven (substances), viz. the Great one (Intellect), and so on, are causal substances as well as effects. Sixteen are effects. The soul is neither a causal substance nor an effect.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The pañcajanāḥ are) the breath and so on, (as is seen) from the complementary passage.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mantra in which the pañcajanāḥ are mentioned is followed by another one in which breath and four other things are mentioned for the purpose of describing the nature of Brahman. &amp;lsquo;They who know the breath of breath, the eye of the eye, the ear of the ear, the food of food, the mind of mind  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo; Hence we conclude, on the ground of proximity, that the five-people are the beings mentioned in this latter mantra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the case of (the text of) some (the Kāṇvas) where food is not mentioned, (the number five is made full) by the light (mentioned in the preceding mantra).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Kāṇva-text, although not mentioning food, makes up the full number five, by the light mentioned in the mantra preceding that in which the five-people are spoken of. That mantra describes the nature of Brahman by saying, &amp;lsquo;Him the gods worship as the light of lights.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Although there is a conflict of the Vedānta-passages with regard to the things created, such as) ether and so on; (there is no such conflict with regard to the Lord) on account of his being represented (in one passage) as described (in other passages), viz. as the cause (of the world).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the preceding part of the work the right definition of Brahman has been established; it has been shown that all the Vedānta-texts have Brahman for their common topic; and it has been proved that there is no scriptural authority for the doctrine of the pradhāna.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the connexion (with passages treating of Brahman, the passages speaking of the Non-being do not intimate absolute Non-existence).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage &amp;lsquo;Non-being indeed was this in the beginning&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 7) does not declare that the cause of the world is the absolutely Non-existent which is devoid of all Selfhood. For in the preceding sections of the Upanishad Brahman is distinctly denied to be the Non-existing, and is defined to be that which is (&amp;lsquo;He who knows the Brahman as non-existing becomes himself non-existing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(He whose work is this is Brahman), because (the &amp;lsquo;work&amp;rsquo;) denotes the world.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Kaushītaki-brāhmaṇa, in the dialogue of Bālāki and Ajātaśatru, we read, &amp;lsquo;O Bālāki, he who is the maker of&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;those persons, he of whom this is the work, he alone is to be known&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. IV, 19). The question here arises whether what is here inculcated as the object of knowledge is the individual soul or the chief vital air or the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that this is not so, on account of the inferential marks of the individual soul and the chief vital air; we reply that that has already been explained.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It remains for us to refute the objection that on account of the inferential marks of the individual soul and the chief vital air, which are met with in the complementary passage, either the one or the other must be meant in the passage under discussion, and not the highest Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But Jaimini thinks that (the reference to the individual soul) has another purport, on account of&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the question and answer; and thus some also (read in their text).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whether the passage under discussion is concerned with the individual soul or with Brahman, is, in the opinion of the teacher Jaimini, no matter for dispute, since the reference to the individual soul has a different purport, i.e. aims at intimating Brahman. He founds this his opinion on a question and a reply met with in the text. After Ajātaśatru has taught Bālāki, by waking the sleeping man, that the soul is different from the vital air, he asks the following question, &amp;lsquo;Bālāki, where did this person here sleep? Where was he? Whence came he thus back?&amp;rsquo; This question clearly refers to something different from the individual soul. And so likewise does the reply, &amp;lsquo;When sleeping he sees no dream, then he becomes one with that prāṇa alone;&amp;rsquo; and, &amp;lsquo;From that Self all prāṇas proceed, each towards its place, from the prāṇas the gods, from the gods the worlds.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Self to be seen, to be heard, &amp;amp;c. is the highest Self) on account of the connected meaning of the sentences.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in the Br̥hadāraṇyaka, in the Maitreyī-brāhmaṇa the following passage, &amp;lsquo;Verily, a husband is not dear that you may love the husband, &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c.; verily, everything is not dear that you may love everything; but that you may love the Self therefore everything is dear. Verily, the Self is to be seen, to be heard, to be perceived, to be marked, O Maitreyī! When the Self has been seen, heard, perceived, and known, then all this is known&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The circumstance of the soul being represented as the object of sight) indicates the fulfilment of the promissory statement; so Āśmarathya thinks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fact that the text proclaims as the object of sight that Self which is denoted as something, dear indicates the fulfilment of the promise made in the passages, &amp;lsquo;When the Self is known all this is known,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;All this is that Self.&amp;rsquo; For if the individual soul were different from the highest Self, the knowledge of the latter would not imply the knowledge of the former, and thus the promise that through the knowledge of one thing everything is to be known would not be fulfilled. Hence the initial&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The initial statement identifies the individual soul and the highest Self) because the soul when it will depart (from the body) is such (i.e. one with the highest Self); thus Auḍulomi thinks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The individual soul which is inquinated by the contact with its different limiting adjuncts, viz. body, senses, and mind (mano-buddhi), attains through the instrumentality of knowledge, meditation, and so on, a state of complete serenity, and thus enables itself, when passing at some future time out of the body, to become one with the highest Self; hence the initial statement in which it is represented as non-different from the highest Self. This is the opinion of the teacher Auḍulomi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The initial statement is made) because (the highest Self) exists in the condition (of the individual soul); so Kāśakr̥tsna thinks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the highest Self exists also in the condition of the individual soul, therefore, the teacher Kāśakr̥tsna thinks, the initial statement which aims at intimating the non-difference of the two is possible. That the highest Self only is that which appears as the individual soul, is evident from the Brāhmaṇa-passage, &amp;lsquo;Let me enter into them with this living Self and evolve names and forms,&amp;rsquo; and similar passages. We have also mantras to the same effect, for instance, &amp;lsquo;The wise one who, having produced all forms and made all names, sits calling the things by their names&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Ār. III, 12, 7) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Brahman is) the material cause also, on account of (this view) not being in conflict with the promissory statements and the illustrative instances.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been said that, as practical religious duty has to be enquired into because it is the cause of an increase of happiness, so Brahman has to be enquired into because it is the cause of absolute beatitude. And Brahman has been defined as that from which there proceed the origination, sustentation, and retractation of this world. Now as this definition comprises alike the relation of substantial causality in which clay and gold, for instance, stand to golden ornaments and earthen pots, and the relation of operative&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the statement of reflection (on the part of the Self).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fact of the sacred texts declaring that the Self reflected likewise shows that it is the operative as well as the material cause. Passages like &amp;lsquo;He wished, may I be many, may I grow forth,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;He thought, may I be many, may I grow forth,&amp;rsquo; show, in the first place, that the Self is the agent in the independent activity which is preceded by the Self&amp;rsquo;s reflection; and, in the second place, that it is the material cause also, since the words &amp;lsquo;May I be many&amp;rsquo; intimate that the reflective desire of multiplying itself has the inward Self for its object.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of both (i.e. the origin and the dissolution of the world) being directly declared (to have Brahman for their material cause).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Sūtra supplies a further argument for Brahman&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;being the general material cause.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahman is the material cause of the world for that reason also that the origination as well as the dissolution of the world is directly spoken of in the sacred texts as having Brahman for their material cause, &amp;lsquo;All these beings take their rise from the ether and return into the ether&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. I, 9, 1). That that from which some other thing springs and into which it returns is the material cause of that other thing is well known. Thus the earth, for instance, is the material cause of rice, barley, and the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Brahman is the material cause) on account of (the Self) making itself; (which is possible) owing to modification.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahman is the material cause for that reason also that Scripture&amp;ndash;in the passage, &amp;lsquo;That made itself its Self&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 7)&amp;ndash;represents the Self as the object of action as well as the agent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But how can the Self which as agent was in full existence previously to the action be made out to be at the same time that which is effected by the action?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because Brahman is called the source.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahman is the material cause for that reason also that it is spoken of in the sacred texts as the source (yoni); compare, for instance, &amp;lsquo;The maker, the Lord, the person who has his source in Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, i, 3); and &amp;lsquo;That which the wise regard as the source of all beings&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 6). For that the word &amp;lsquo;source&amp;rsquo; denotes the material cause is well known from the use of ordinary language; the earth, for instance, is called the yoni of trees and herbs. In some places indeed the word yoni means not source, but merely place; so, for instance, in the mantra, &amp;lsquo;A yoni, O Indra, was made for you to sit down upon&amp;rsquo; (R̥k. Saṁh. I, 104, 1). But that in the passage quoted it means &amp;lsquo;source&amp;rsquo; follows from a complementary passage, &amp;lsquo;As the spider sends forth and draws in its threads,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/4/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hereby all (the doctrines concerning the origin of the world which are opposed to the Vedānta) are explained, are explained.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The doctrine according to which the pradhāna is the cause of the world has, in the Sūtras beginning with I, 1, 5, been again and again brought forward and refuted. The chief reason for the special attention given to that doctrine is that the Vedānta-texts contain some passages which, to people deficient in mental penetration, may appear to contain inferential marks pointing to it. The&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
