<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 METHODS OF SĀDHANA on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 METHODS OF SĀDHANA on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 JÑĀNA-MĀRGA (PATH OF KNOWLEDGE)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/01_jnAna-mArga_PATH_OF_KNOWLEDGE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/01_jnAna-mArga_PATH_OF_KNOWLEDGE/</guid>
      <description>Jñanamarga, as Yoga-Vāsiṣṭa’s definition goes, issamyak avekṣaṇam- whatever wrong notions we have, about the nature of sukha and about our own nature, we correct them by right ideas. This is the safest method and is most productive. A sick person can do that, a paralytic patient can do that, a woman with a child can do that, a suckling mother can do that, a boy can do that because there is no toil in this process and there is no struggle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 YOGA MĀRGA (PATH OF YOGA)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/02_YOGA_mArga_PATH_OF_YOGA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/02_YOGA_mArga_PATH_OF_YOGA/</guid>
      <description>Yogaḥ citta vṛtti nirodhaḥas per Patanjali. **yogo cittarodhohi-**as per Yoga-Vāsiṣṭha. In the later, through suggestions you are softening the mind and purifying it, whereas in the former, you are actually controlling the forces. I hope you see the slight difference there. Yoga-Vāsiṣṭha further declares that:
मनः प्रशमनोपायो योग इत्यभिधीयते ।
Manaḥ praśamanōpāyō yōga iti-abhidhīyatē.
(Yoga-Vāsiṣṭha 3-9-132)
Mellowing the mind is termed as yoga. It is tuning the mind from the harsh state to gentle state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 ŚUBHAKARMA (PIOUS NEUTRAL ACTIVITIES)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/03_shubhakarma_PIOUS_NEUTRAL_ACTIVITIES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/03_shubhakarma_PIOUS_NEUTRAL_ACTIVITIES/</guid>
      <description>We have understood the main difference between Jñānamārga and Yogamārga and have studied the various methods that can be adopted to mellow the mind. The question arises now as to why we should look for other methods of sādhana when these two methods are more than sufficient to put us in the desired path.
If one carefully examines, these two paths are very difficult to adopt for common people like us who have great load of rajas and tamas compared to those who are advanced in their pursuit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 SĀKĀRADHYĀNA (MEDITATION ON A FORM)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/04_sAkAradhyAna_MEDITATION_ON_A_FORM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/04_sAkAradhyAna_MEDITATION_ON_A_FORM/</guid>
      <description>We will now discuss the details of practice to be undertaken at each functional centre. Let us first take up the CITTAor the mind centre.
If you sit and start contemplating on Brahma (Nirguṇabrahma), you will only waste your time ending up in developing headache. Instead, have a picture of God of your choice and engage your mind on that. It is a wonderful tool in your hands. Now you relate yourself with your Iṣṭadevata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 JAPA (CHANTING OF HOLY NAME)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/05_JAPA_CHANTING_OF_HOLY_NAME/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/05_JAPA_CHANTING_OF_HOLY_NAME/</guid>
      <description>Till now we looked at the optical centre- a picture. The next centre is the Śabdasthāna or sound as a medium.
When you come down to the śabdasthāna, the same principle has to work that the bothering energy must be spent away and during that process mind is not excited. The prescription given under this centre is called JAPA. Continuous repetition of God’s name or a Mantra or a chosen word introduced at this centre is termed as japa</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 OTHER NEUTRAL ACTIVITIES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/06_OTHER_NEUTRAL_ACTIVITIES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/06_OTHER_NEUTRAL_ACTIVITIES/</guid>
      <description>For some people, japa is not sufficient for expenditure of large amounts of energy. For them, still a courser activity is required for spending the stock of energy. Japa is inner articulation. For that reason, our ancestors suggested the use of loud chanting of names of the Lord. Again this is a neutral activity. They designed the Sandhyā-Vandana which was a still coarser method. Performance of this involves time, resulting in spending larger amounts of the bothering energy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 KARMAYOGA (PATH OF SELFLESS ACTION)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/07_KARMAYOGA_PATH_OF_SELFLESS_ACTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/07_KARMAYOGA_PATH_OF_SELFLESS_ACTION/</guid>
      <description>If you say you have no time for doing any of the above mentioned sādhanā-s since your profession takes away much of the time, there is an alternative method for such situations. For such persons Karma yoga is the remedy.
Bhagavadgīta dwells on this in great detail and wherein Sri Kṛṣṇa elaborates on the approach to one’s activities. This, I think is the biggest research tried only in Bhagavadgīta. We shall take up the important points from that and see how it fits in to our sādhana.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 PREMA AND BHAKTI (LOVE AND DEVOTION)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/08_PREMA_AND_BHAKTI_LOVE_AND_DEVOTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/08_PREMA_AND_BHAKTI_LOVE_AND_DEVOTION/</guid>
      <description>We went through śubha-karmamārga which was very important since we cannot always use -Jñānamārga and Yogamārga. We have to incorporate karmakāṇḍa methods of doing pūja, reciting sahasranāma, etc. as an alternative. Apart from these any karma which is not exciting can be taken up in our daily lives as a portion of our time table wherein the boredom forces can be easily dissolved. One needs to take care that the activities so taken up should not raise kāma and krodha.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 DHARMA (RIGHTEOUNESS) – AS A TOOL OF SĀDHANA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/09_DHARMA_RIGHTEOUNESS_AS_A_TOOL_OF_sAdhana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/articles/satyanArAyaNa-shAstrI/let_go/02_sAdhana_-_PRACTICE/02_METHODS_OF_sAdhana/09_DHARMA_RIGHTEOUNESS_AS_A_TOOL_OF_sAdhana/</guid>
      <description>Shastriji”s concept of Dharma throws light on a variety of modern way of thinking and the apprehensions of the younger generation regarding the old value systems enunciated in the dhārmic principles. A totally new dimension has been opened by Shastriji by way of his arguments which capture the imagination of the youngsters. His primary aim of using any method to tame the mind to attain peace and tranquillity leads one to think positively about applying dhārmic tenets in one’s own daily lives as a means of sādhana to achieve happiness.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
