<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;३ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 third pāda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-pāda&#34;&gt;THIRD PĀDA.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;REVERENCE TO THE HIGHEST SELF!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The abode of heaven, earth, and so on (is Brahman), on account of the term &amp;lsquo;own,&amp;rsquo; i.e. Self.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Mu. Up. II, 2, 5), &amp;lsquo;He in whom the heaven, the earth, and the sky are woven, the mind also with all the vital airs, know him alone as the Self, and leave off other words! He is the bridge of the Immortal.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of its being designated as that to which the Released have to resort.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the abode of heaven, earth, and so on, we have to understand the highest Brahman for that reason also that we find it denoted as that to which the Released have to resort.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The conception that the body and other things contained in the sphere of the Not-self are our Self, constitutes Nescience; from it there spring desires with regard to whatever promotes the well-being of the body and so on, and aversions with regard to whatever tends to injure it; there further arise fear and confusion when we observe anything threatening to destroy it. All this constitutes an endless series of the most manifold evils with which we all are acquainted. Regarding those on the other hand who have freed themselves from the stains of Nescience desire aversion and so on, it is said that they have to resort to that, viz. the abode of heaven, earth, &amp;amp;c. which forms the topic of discussion. For the text, after having said, &amp;lsquo;The fetter of the heart is broken, all doubts are solved, all his works perish when He has been beheld who is the higher and the lower&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 2, 8), later on remarks, &amp;lsquo;The wise man freed from name and form goes to the divine Person who is greater than the great&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. III, 2, 8). That Brahman is that which is to be resorted to by the released, is known from other scriptural passages, such as &amp;lsquo;When all desires which once entered his heart are undone then does the mortal become immortal, then he obtains Brahman&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 7). Of the pradhāna and similar entities, on the other hand, it is not known from any source that they are to be resorted to by the released. Moreover, the text (in the passage, &amp;lsquo;Know him alone as the Self and leave off other words&amp;rsquo;) declares that the knowledge of the abode of heaven and earth, &amp;amp;c. is connected with the leaving off of all speech; a condition which, according to another scriptural passage, attaches to (the knowledge of) Brahman; cp. Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 21, &amp;lsquo;Let a wise Brāhmaṇa, after he has discovered him, practise wisdom. Let him not seek after many words, for that is mere weariness of the tongue.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not (i.e. the abode of heaven, earth, &amp;amp;c. cannot be) that which is inferred, (i.e. the pradhāna), on account of the terms not denoting it.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While there has been shown a special reason in favour of Brahman (being the abode), there is no such special reason in favour of anything else. Hence he (the sūtrakāra) says that that which is inferred, i.e. the pradhāna assumed by the Sānkhya-smr̥ti, is not to be accepted as the abode of heaven, earth, &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Nor) also the individual soul (prāṇabhr̥t).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although to the cognitional (individual) Self the qualities of Selfhood and intelligence do belong, still omniscience and similar qualities do not belong to it as its knowledge is limited by its adjuncts; thus the individual soul also cannot be accepted as the abode of heaven, earth, &amp;amp;c., for the same reason, i.e. on account of the terms not denoting it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the attribute of forming the abode of heaven, earth, and so on, cannot properly be given to the individual soul because the latter is limited by certain adjuncts and therefore non-pervading (not omnipresent) &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the declaration of difference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The passage &amp;lsquo;Know him alone as the Self&amp;rsquo; moreover implies a declaration of difference, viz. of the difference of the object of knowledge and the knower. Here the individual soul as being that which is desirous of release is the knower, and consequently Brahman, which is denoted by the word &amp;lsquo;self&amp;rsquo; and represented as the object of knowledge, is understood to be the abode of heaven, earth, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the subject-matter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The highest Self constitutes the subject-matter (of the entire chapter), as we see from the passage, &amp;lsquo;Sir, what is that through which, when it is known, everything else becomes known?&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. I, 1, 3) in which the knowledge of everything is declared to be dependent on the knowledge of one thing. For all this (i.e. the entire world) becomes known if Brahman the Self of all is known, not if only the individual soul is known.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the two conditions of standing and eating (of which the former is characteristic of the highest Lord, the latter of the individual soul).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reference to that which is the abode of heaven, earth, and so on, the text says, &amp;lsquo;Two birds, inseparable friends,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Mu. Up. III, 1, 1). This passage describes the two states of mere standing, i.e. mere presence, and of eating, the clause, &amp;lsquo;One of them eats the sweet fruit,&amp;rsquo; referring to the eating, i.e. the fruition of the results of works,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The bhūman (is Brahman), as the instruction about it is additional to that about the state of deep sleep (i.e. the vital air which remains awake even in the state of deep sleep).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Cḥ. Up. VII, 23; 24), &amp;lsquo;That which is much (bhūman) we must desire to understand.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sir, I desire to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where one sees nothing else, hears nothing else, understands nothing else, that is what is much (bhūman). Where one sees something else, hears something else, understands something else, that is the Little.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the agreement of the attributes (mentioned in the text).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The attributes, moreover, which the sacred text ascribes to the bhūman agree well with the highest Self. The passage, &amp;lsquo;Where one sees nothing else, hears nothing else, understands nothing else, that is the bhūman,&amp;rsquo; gives us to understand that in the bhūman the ordinary activities of seeing and so on are absent; and that this is characteristic of the highest Self, we know from another scriptural passage, viz. &amp;lsquo;But when the Self only is all this, how should he see another?&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. (Br̥. Up. IV, 5, 15). What is said about the absence of the activities of seeing and so on in the state of deep sleep (Pra. Up. IV, 2) is said with the intention of declaring the non-attachedness of the Self, not of describing the nature of the prāṇa; for the highest Self (not the vital air) is the topic of that passage. The bliss also of which Scripture speaks as connected with that state is mentioned only in order to show that bliss constitutes the nature of the Self. For Scripture says (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 32), &amp;lsquo;This is his highest bliss. All other creatures live on a small portion of that bliss.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Imperishable (is Brahman) on account of (its) supporting (all things) up to ether.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Br̥. Up. III, 8, 7; 8). &amp;lsquo;In what then is the ether woven, like warp and woof?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He said: O Gārgī, the Brāhmaṇas call this the akshara (the Imperishable). It is neither coarse nor fine,&amp;rsquo; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the doubt arises whether the word &amp;lsquo;akshara&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;syllable&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;the highest Lord.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin maintains that the word &amp;lsquo;akshara&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;syllable&amp;rsquo; merely, because it has, in such terms as akshara-samāmnāya, the meaning of &amp;lsquo;syllable;&amp;rsquo; because we have no right to disregard the settled meaning of a word; and because another scriptural passage also (&amp;lsquo;The syllable Om is all this,&amp;rsquo; Cḥ. Up. II, 23, 4) declares a syllable, represented as the object of devotion, to be the Self of all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This (supporting can), on account of the command (attributed to the Imperishable, be the work of the highest Lord only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The supporting of all things up to ether is the work of the highest Lord only.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of the command.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the sacred text speaks of a command (&amp;lsquo;By the command of that akshara, O Gārgī, sun and moon stand apart!&amp;rsquo; III, 8, 9), and command can be the work of the highest Lord only, not of the non-intelligent pradhāna. For non-intelligent causes such as clay and the like are not capable of command, with reference to their effects, such as jars and the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (Scripture) separating (the akshara) from that whose nature is different (from Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also on account of the reason stated in this Sūtra Brahman only is to be considered as the Imperishable, and the supporting of all things up to ether is to be looked upon as the work of Brahman only, not of anything else. The meaning of the Sūtra is as follows. Whatever things other than Brahman might possibly be thought to be denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;akshara,&amp;rsquo; from the nature of all those things Scripture separates the akshara spoken of as the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of his being designated as the object of sight (the highest Self is meant, and) the same (is meant in the passage speaking of the meditation on the highest person by means of the syllable Om).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(In Pra. Up. V, 2) the general topic of discussion is set forth in the words, &amp;lsquo;O Satyakāma, the syllable Om is the highest and also the other Brahman; therefore he who knows it arrives by the same means at one of the two.&amp;rsquo; The text then goes on, &amp;lsquo;Again, he who meditates with this syllable Om of three mātrās on the highest Person,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The small (ether) (is Brahman) on account of the subsequent (arguments).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 1, 1),&amp;rsquo; There is this city of Brahman, and in it the palace, the small lotus, and in it that small ether. Now what exists within that small ether that is to be sought for, that is to be understood,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the doubt arises whether the small ether within the small lotus of the heart of which Scripture speaks, is the elemental ether, or the individual soul (vijñānātman), or the highest Self. This doubt is caused by the words &amp;rsquo;ether&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;city of Brahman.&amp;rsquo; For the word &amp;rsquo;ether,&amp;rsquo; in the first place, is known to be used in the sense of elemental ether as well as of highest Brahman. Hence the doubt whether the small ether of the text be the elemental ether or the highest ether, i. e. Brahman. In explanation of the expression &amp;lsquo;city of Brahman,&amp;rsquo; in the second place, it might be said either that the individual soul is here called Brahman and the body Brahman&amp;rsquo;s city, or else that the city of Brahman means the city of the highest Brahman. Here (i.e. in consequence of this latter doubt) a further doubt arises as to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The small ether is Brahman) on account of&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the action of going (into Brahman) and of the word (brahmaloka); for thus it is seen (i. e. that the individual souls go into Brahman is seen elsewhere in Scripture); and (this going of the souls into Brahman constitutes) an inferential sign (by means of which we may properly interpret the word &amp;lsquo;brahmaloka&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been declared (in the preceding Sūtra) that the small (ether) is the highest Lord, on account of the reasons contained in the subsequent passages. These subsequent reasons are now set forth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the supporting also (attributed to it), (the small ether must be the Lord) because that greatness is observed in him (according to other scriptural passages).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And also on account of the &amp;lsquo;supporting&amp;rsquo; the small ether can be the highest Lord only.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The text at first introduces the general subject of discussion in the passage, &amp;lsquo;In it is that small ether;&amp;rsquo; declares thereupon that the small one is to be compared with the universal ether, and that everything is contained in it; subsequently applies to it the term &amp;lsquo;Self,&amp;rsquo; and states it to possess the qualities of being free from sin, &amp;amp;c.; and, finally, declares with reference to the same general subject of discussion, &amp;lsquo;That Self is a bank, a limitary support (vidhr̥ti), that these worlds may not be confounded.&amp;rsquo; As &amp;lsquo;support&amp;rsquo; is here predicated of the Self, we have to understand by it a supporting agent. Just as a dam stems the spreading water so that the boundaries of the fields are not confounded, so that Self acts like a limitary dam in order that these outer and inner worlds, and all the different castes and āśramas may not be confounded. In accordance with this our text declares that greatness, which is shown in the act of holding asunder, to belong to the small (ether) which forms the subject of discussion; and that such greatness is found in the highest Lord only, is seen from other scriptural passages, such as &amp;lsquo;By the command of that Imperishable, O Gārgī, sun and moon; are held apart&amp;quot;(Br̥. Up. III, 8, 9). Similarly, we read in another passage also, about whose referring to the highest&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the settled meaning.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The small ether within cannot denote anything but the highest Lord for this reason also, that the word &amp;rsquo;ether&amp;rsquo; has (among other meanings) the settled meaning of &amp;lsquo;highest Lord.&amp;rsquo; Compare, for instance, the sense in which the word &amp;rsquo;ether&amp;rsquo; is used in Cḥ. Up. VIII, 14, &amp;lsquo;He who is called ether is the revealer of all forms and names;&amp;rsquo; and Cḥ. Up. I, 9, 1, &amp;lsquo;All these beings take their rise from the ether,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. On the other hand, we do not meet with any passage in which the word &amp;rsquo;ether&amp;rsquo; is used in the sense of &amp;lsquo;individual soul.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that the other one (i.e. the individual soul) (is meant) on account of a reference to it (made in a complementary passage), (we say) no, on account of the impossibility.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If the small (ether) is to be explained as the highest Lord on account of a complementary passage, then, the pūrvapakshin resumes, we point out that another complementary passage contains a reference to the other one, i. e. to the individual soul: &amp;lsquo;Now that serene being (literally: serenity, complete satisfaction), which after having risen out from this earthly body and having reached the highest light, appears in its true form, that is, the Self; thus he spoke&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 3, 4). For there the word &amp;lsquo;serenity,&amp;rsquo; which is known to denote, in another scriptural passage, the state of deep sleep, can convey the idea of the individual soul only when it is in&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that from the subsequent (chapter it appears that the individual soul is meant), (we point out that what is there referred to is) rather (the individual soul in so far) as its true nature has become manifest (i. e. as it is non-different from Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The doubt whether, &amp;lsquo;on account of the reference to the other,&amp;rsquo; the individual soul might not possibly be meant, has been discarded on the ground of &amp;lsquo;impossibility.&amp;rsquo; But, like a dead man on whom amr̥ta has been sprinkled, that doubt rises again, drawing new strength from the subsequent chapter which treats of Prajāpati. For there he (Prajāpati)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And the reference (to the individual soul) has a different meaning.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The alleged reference to the individual soul which has been pointed out (by the pūrvapakshin) in the passage complementary to the passage about the small ether (&amp;lsquo;Now that serene being,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., VIII, 3, 4) teaches, if the small ether is interpreted to mean the highest Lord, neither the worship of the individual soul nor any qualification of the subject under discussion (viz. the small ether), and is therefore devoid of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that on account of the scriptural&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;declaration of the smallness (of the ether) (the Lord cannot be meant; we reply that) that has been explained (before).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The pūrvapakshin has remarked that the smallness of the ether stated by Scripture (&amp;lsquo;In it is that small ether&amp;rsquo;) does not agree with the highest Lord, that it may however be predicated of the individual soul which (in another passage) is compared to the point of a goad. As that remark calls for a refutation we point out that it has been refuted already, it having been shown&amp;ndash;under I, 2, 7&amp;ndash;that a relative smallness may be attributed to the Lord. The same refutation is&amp;ndash;as the Sūtra points out&amp;ndash;to be applied here also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the acting after (i.e. the shining after), (that after which sun, moon, &amp;amp;c. are said to shine is the highest Self), and (because by the light) of him (all this is said to be lighted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Mu. Up. II, 2, 10, and Ka. Up. V, 15), &amp;lsquo;The sun does not shine there, nor the moon and the stars, nor these lightnings, much less this fire. After him when he shines everything shines; by the light of him all this is lighted.&amp;rsquo; The question here arises whether he &amp;lsquo;after whom when he shines everything shines, and by whose light all this is lighted,&amp;rsquo; is some luminous substance, or the highest Self (prājña ātman).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moreover Smr̥ti also speaks of him (i.e. of the prājña. Self as being the universal light).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Moreover that aspect of the prājña Self is spoken of in Smr̥ti also, viz. in the Bhagavad Gītā (XV, 6, 12), &amp;lsquo;Neither the sun, nor the moon, nor the fire illumines that; having gone into which men do not return, that is my highest seat.&amp;rsquo; And &amp;lsquo;The light which abiding in the sun illumines the whole world, and that which is in the moon and that which is in the fire, all that light know to be mine.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the term, (viz. the term &amp;rsquo;lord&amp;rsquo; applied to it) the (person) measured (by a thumb) (is the highest Lord).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Ka. Up. II, 4, 12), &amp;lsquo;The person of the size of a thumb stands in the middle of the Self,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c., and (II, 4, 13), &amp;lsquo;That person, of the size of a thumb, is like a light without smoke, lord of the past and of the future, he is the same to-day and to-morrow. This is that.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But with reference to the heart (the highest Self is said to be of the size of a span), as men are entitled (to the study of the Veda).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The measure of a span is ascribed to the highest Lord, although omnipresent with reference to his abiding within the heart; just as to ether (space) the measure of a cubit is ascribed with reference to the joint of a bamboo. For, on the one hand, the measure of a span cannot be ascribed directly to the highest Self which exceeds all measure, and, on the other hand, it has been shown that none but the highest Lord can be meant here, on account of the term &amp;lsquo;Lord,&amp;rsquo; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Also (beings) above them, (viz. men) (are qualified for the study and practice of the Veda), on account of the possibility (of it), according to Bādarāyaṇa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been said above that the passage about him who is of the size of a thumb has reference to the human heart, because men are entitled to study and act according to the śāstra. This gives us an occasion for the following discussion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (the corporeal individuality of the gods involves) a contradiction to (sacrificial) works; we deny that, on account of the observation of the assumption (on the part of the gods) of several (forms).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If the right of the gods, and other beings superior to men, to the acquisition of knowledge is founded on the assumption of their corporeality, &amp;amp;c., we shall have to admit, in consequence of that corporeality, that Indra and the other gods stand in the relation of subordinate members (anga) to sacrificial acts, by means of their being present in person&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that a contradiction will result) in respect of the word; we refute this objection on the ground that (the world) originates from the word, as is shown by perception and inference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let it then be granted that, from the admission of the corporeal individuality of the gods, no contradiction will result in the case of sacrificial works. Still a contradiction will result in respect of the &amp;lsquo;word&amp;rsquo; (śabda).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And from this very reason there follows the eternity of the Veda.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the eternity of the Veda is founded on the absence of the remembrance of an agent only, a doubt with regard to it had been raised owing to the doctrine that the gods and other individuals have sprung from it. That doubt has been refuted in the preceding Sūtra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The present Sūtra now confirms the, already established, eternity of the Veda. The eternity of the word of the Veda has to be assumed for this very reason, that the world with its definite (eternal) species, such as gods and so on, originates from it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the equality of names and forms there is no contradiction (to the eternity of the word of the Veda) in the renovation (of the world); as is seen from Śruti and Smr̥ti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If&amp;ndash;the pūrvapakshin resumes&amp;ndash;the individual gods and so on did, like the individual animals, originate and pass away in an unbroken succession so that there would be no break of the course of practical existence including denominations, things denominated and agents denominating; the connexion (between word and thing) would be eternal, and the objection as to a contradiction with reference to the word (raised in Sūtra 27) would thereby be refuted. But if, as Śruti and Smr̥ti declare, the whole threefold&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the impossibility of (the gods being qualified) for the madhu-vidyā, &amp;amp;c., Jaimini (maintains) the non-qualification (of the gods for the Brahma-vidyā).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A new objection is raised against the averment that the gods, &amp;amp;c. also are entitled to the knowledge of Brahman. The teacher, Jaimini, considers the gods and similar beings not to have any claim.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On account of the impossibility, in the case of the so-called Madhu-vidyā, &amp;amp;c. If their claim to the knowledge of Brahman were admitted, we should have to admit their claim to the madhu-vidyā (&amp;rsquo;the knowledge of the honey&amp;rsquo;) also, because that also is a kind of knowledge not different (from the knowledge of Brahman). But to admit this latter claim is not possible; for, according to the passage, &amp;lsquo;The Sun is indeed the honey of the devas&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. III, 1, 1), men are to meditate on the sun (the god Āditya) under the form of honey, and how, if the gods themselves are admitted as meditating worshippers, can Āditya meditate upon another Āditya?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the devas, &amp;amp;c. are not qualified) on account of (the words denoting the devas, &amp;amp;c.) being (used) in the sense of (sphere of) light.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To that sphere of light, the pūrvapakshin resumes, which is stationed in the sky, and during its diurnal revolutions illumines the world, terms such as Āditya, i.e. the names of devas, are applied, as we know from the use of ordinary language, and from Vedic complementary passages &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But of a mere sphere of light we cannot understand how it should be endowed with either a bodily form, consisting of the heart and the like, or intelligence, or the capability of forming wishes &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. For mere light we know to be, like earth, entirely devoid of intelligence. The same observation applies to Agni (fire), and so on. It will perhaps be said that our objection is not valid, because the personality of the devas is known from the mantras, arthavādas, itihāsas, purāṇas, and from the conceptions of ordinary life &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; but we contest the relevancy of this remark. For the conceptions of ordinary life do not constitute an independent means of knowledge; we rather say that a thing is known from ordinary life if it is known by the (acknowledged) means of knowledge, perception, &amp;amp;c. But none of the recognised means of knowledge, such as perception and the like, apply to the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bādarāyaṇa, on the other hand, (maintains) the existence (of qualification for Brahma-vidyā on the part of the gods); for there are (passages indicatory of that).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The expression &amp;lsquo;on the other hand&amp;rsquo; is meant to rebut the pūrvapaksha. The teacher, Bādarāyaṇa, maintains the existence of the qualification on the part of the gods, &amp;amp;c. For, although the qualification of the gods cannot be admitted with reference to the madhu-vidyā, and similar topics of knowledge, in which the gods themselves are implicated, still they may be qualified for the pure knowledge of Brahman, qualification in general depending on the presence of desire, capability, &amp;amp;c. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nor does the impossibility of qualification in certain cases interfere with the presence of qualification in those other cases where it is not impossible. To the case of the gods the same reasoning applies as to the case of men; for among men also, all are not qualified for everything, Brāhmaṇas, for instance, not for the rājasūya-sacrifice &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Grief of him (i.e. of Jānaśruti) (arose) on account of his hearing a disrespectful speech about himself; on account of the rushing on of that (grief) (Raikva called him Śūdra); for it (the grief) is pointed at (by Raikva).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(In the preceding adhikaraṇa) the exclusiveness of the claim of men to knowledge has been refuted, and it has been declared that the gods, &amp;amp;c. also possess such a claim. The present adhikaraṇa is entered on for the purpose of removing the doubt whether, as the exclusiveness of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because the kshattriyahood (of Jānaśruti) is understood from the inferential mark (supplied by his being mentioned) later on with Caitraratha (who was a kshattriya himself).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gānaśruti cannot have been a Śūdra by birth for that reason also that his being a kshattriya is understood from an inferential sign, viz. his being mentioned together (in one chapter) with the kshattriya Caitraratha Abhipratārin. For, later on, i.e. in the passage complementary to the saṁvarga-vidyā, a kshattriya Caitrarathi Abhipratārin is glorified, &amp;lsquo;Once while Śaunaka Kāpeya and Abhipratārin Kākshaseni were being waited on at their meal a religious student begged of them&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 3, 5). That this Abhipratārin was a Caitrarathi (i.e. a descendant of Citraratha) we have to infer from his connexion with a Kāpeya. For we know (from Śruti) about the connexion of Citraratha himself with the Kāpeyas (&amp;rsquo;the Kāpeyas made Citraratha perform that sacrifice;&amp;rsquo; Tāṇḍya. Br. XX, 12, 5), and as a rule sacrificers of one and the same family employ officiating priests of one and the same family. Moreover, as we understand from Scripture (&amp;lsquo;from him a Caitrarathi descended who was a prince &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;rsquo;) that he (Caitraratha) was a prince, we must&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the reference to ceremonial purifications (in the case of the higher castes) and on account of their absence being declared (in the case of the Śūdras).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the Śūdras are not qualified, follows from that circumstance also that in different places of the vidyās such ceremonies as the upanayana and the like are referred to. Compare, for instance, Śat. Br. XI, 5, 3, 13, &amp;lsquo;He initiated him as a pupil;&amp;rsquo; Cḥ. Up. VII, 1, 1, &amp;lsquo;Teach me, Sir! thus he approached him;&amp;rsquo; Pra. Up. I, 1, &amp;lsquo;Devoted to Brahman, firm in Brahman, seeking for the highest Brahman they, carrying fuel in their hands, approached the venerable Pippalāda, thinking that he would teach them all that.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of (Gautama) proceeding (to initiate Jābāla) on the ascertainment of (his) not being that (i.e. a Śūdra).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Śūdras are not qualified for that reason also that Gautama, having ascertained Jābāla not to be a Śūdra from his speaking the truth, proceeded to initiate and instruct him. &amp;lsquo;None who is not a Brāhmaṇa would thus speak out. Go and fetch fuel, friend, I shall initiate you. You have not swerved from the truth&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. IV, 4, 5); which scriptural passage furnishes an inferential sign (of the Śūdras not being capable of initiation).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the prohibition, in Smr̥ti, of (the Śūdras&amp;rsquo;) hearing and studying (the Veda) and (knowing and performing) (Vedic) matters.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Śūdras are not qualified for that reason also that Smr̥ti prohibits their hearing the Veda, their studying the Veda, and their understanding and performing Vedic matters. The prohibition of hearing the Veda is conveyed by the following passages: &amp;lsquo;The ears of him who hears the Veda are to be filled with (molten) lead and lac,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;For a Śūdra is (like) a cemetery, therefore (the Veda) is not to be read in the vicinity of a Śūdra.&amp;rsquo; From this latter passage the prohibition of studying the Veda results at once; for how should he study Scripture in whose vicinity it is not even to be read? There is, moreover, an express prohibition (of the Śūdras studying the Veda). &amp;lsquo;His tongue is to be slit if he pronounces it; his body is to be cut through if he preserves it.&amp;rsquo; The prohibitions of hearing and studying the Veda already imply the prohibition of the knowledge and performance of Vedic matters; there are, however, express prohibitions also, such as &amp;lsquo;he is not to impart knowledge to the Śūdra,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;to the twice-born belong study, sacrifice, and the bestowal of gifts.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The prāṇa is Brahman), on account of the trembling (predicated of the whole world).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The discussion of qualification for Brahma-knowledge&amp;ndash;on which we entered as an opportunity offered&amp;ndash;being finished we return to our chief topic, i.e. the enquiry into the purport of the Vedānta-texts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read (Ka. Up. II, 6, 2), &amp;lsquo;Whatever there is, the whole world when gone forth trembles in the prāṇa. It (the prāṇa) is a great terror, a raised thunderbolt. Those who know it become immortal  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The light (is Brahman), on account of that (Brahman) being seen (in the scriptural passage).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We read in Scripture, &amp;lsquo;Thus does that serene being, arising from this body, appear in its own form as soon as it has approached the highest light&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 12, 3). Here the doubt arises whether the word &amp;rsquo;light&amp;rsquo; denotes the (physical) light, which is the object of sight and dispels darkness, or the highest Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The ether is (Brahman), as it is designated as something different, &amp;amp;c. (from name and form).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture says, &amp;lsquo;He who is called ether, (ākāśa) is the revealer of all forms and names. That within which these forms and names are contained is the Brahman, the Immortal, the Self (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 14, 1).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There arising a doubt whether that which here is called ether is the highest Brahman or the ordinary elemental ether, the pūrvapakshin declares that the latter alternative is to be embraced, firstly, because it is founded on the conventional meaning of the word &amp;rsquo;ether;&amp;rsquo; and, secondly, because the circumstance of revealing names and forms can very well be reconciled with the elemental ether, as that which affords room (for all things). Moreover, the passage contains no clear indicatory mark of Brahman, such as creative power, and the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/3/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For in representing the states of waking, and so on, the passage does not aim at describing the soul as subject to different states or transmigration, but rather as free from all particular conditions and transmigration. This is evident from the circumstance that on Janaka&amp;rsquo;s question, which is repeated in every section, &amp;lsquo;Speak on for the sake of emancipation,&amp;rsquo; Yājñavalkya replies each time, &amp;lsquo;By all that he is not affected, for that person is not attached to anything&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. IV, 3, 14-16). And later on he says (IV, 3, 22), &amp;lsquo;He is not followed by good, not followed by evil, for he has then overcome all the sorrows of the heart.&amp;rsquo; We have, therefore, to conclude that the chapter exclusively aims at setting forth the nature of the non-transmigrating Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
