<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;En - Tapasyananda on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;En - Tapasyananda on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/00/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/00/</guid>
      <description>The Book A biography of Sri Sankara on modern lines is an impossible for want of exact data from contemporary writings. We have therefore to depend on the type of Sanskrit works called Sankaravijayas, the traditional lives of the Acharya, to know whatever is now possible to gather about this saintly philosopher who has left so vivid an impression on the Indian mind. As these Vijayas have a mythological bias, they have their obvious defect in respect of chronology and recording of facts and events, but they got their excellences too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>01 PROLOGUE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/01_PROLOGUE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/01_PROLOGUE/</guid>
      <description>Prefatory Remarks
(1-17) 1. Offering my prostrations to Sri Vidyatirtha (my Guru), who is one with the Self of all, I am attempting to give here a clear and precise summary of the ancient literature connected with the glorious life of Acharya Sankara (or of the book named Purasankarajaya). 2. In a small mirror, even the big forehead of an elephant can be clearly seen. Even so, in this, my brief work, you will get the essence of all the extensive accounts about Sankara and his teachings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02 THE BIRTH OF SANKARA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/02_THE_BIRTH_OF_SANKARA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/02_THE_BIRTH_OF_SANKARA/</guid>
      <description>Sankara&amp;rsquo;s Parents
(1-5) God Siva, the self-created and merciful Being, the destroyer of Cupid, manifested himself as His holy emblem, usually called Sivalingam, on a hill known as Vrishachala situated near the course of the river Purna in the Kerala country. Coming to know of the divinity and greatness of that Sivalingam through a dream, a king called Rajasekhara built a fine temple to house the Lingam and made arrangements for its worship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03 THE EARTHLY MANIFESTATION OF DEVAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/03_THE_EARTHLY_MANIFESTATION_OF_DEVAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/03_THE_EARTHLY_MANIFESTATION_OF_DEVAS/</guid>
      <description>The Antecedents of Mandana
(1-8) While God Siva, the crescent-crested, thus took birth on earth, many other Divinities also embodied themselves as off- spring in the houses of learned Brahmana scholars. Mahavishnu was born as the son of a learned Brahmana named Vimala and came to be known as Padmapada (having in early life the name of Sanandana), before whom no scholar could keep up his reputation for scholarship. The deity Vayu took birth as the son of the fanati- cal ritualist Prabhakara under the name of Hastamalaka who always humbled the pride of his opponents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04 BOYHOOD DAYS UP TO THE AGE OF EIGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/04_BOYHOOD_DAYS_UP_TO_THE_AGE_OF_EIGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/04_BOYHOOD_DAYS_UP_TO_THE_AGE_OF_EIGHT/</guid>
      <description>Sankara as a Precocious Boy
(1-20) Within his first year this child, who was God Siva embodied as the son of these Brahmana parents, showed himself proficient in languages. By the second year, he could recite all books and showed an untaught mastery of Kavyas and Puranas. Hearing once, he could learn anything, and so, he not only gave the least trouble to the teacher on his own account, but relieved him from much of his burdens by offering to teach his fellow students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05 EMBRACING SANNYASA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/05_EMBRACING_SANNYASA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/05_EMBRACING_SANNYASA/</guid>
      <description>Reputation of Boy Sankara attracts the King
(1-9) Thus at the age of seven that wonderful child, having spanned the ocean of Vedic learning, left the house of the Guru and returned home to pay his respect to his mother. Thenceforth he spent his time quietly at home, engaging himself in the service of his mother, in studying the Veda and in offering oblations in the sacred fire twice a day along with observing all allied rituals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>06 ESTABLISHMENT OF THE PRISTINE PHILOSOPHY OF THE SELF</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/06_ESTABLISHMENT_OF_THE_PRISTINE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_SELF/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/06_ESTABLISHMENT_OF_THE_PRISTINE_PHILOSOPHY_OF_THE_SELF/</guid>
      <description>Advent of Sanandana alias Padmapada
(1-15) One day a Brahmana, learned in Vedas and of handsome and commanding appearance, went to see the Acharya and pay his respects to him. Being full of the spirit of renunciation and free from the bondage of a home and a spouse, he came to the Acharya and fell at his feet, recognising in him a seaworthy boat of a Guru that could help him cross this turbulent ocean of Samsara.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>07 THE MEETING WITH VYASA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/07_THE_MEETING_WITH_VYASA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/07_THE_MEETING_WITH_VYASA/</guid>
      <description>Sankara in Confrontation with Sage Vyasa
(1-21) Once, seated on the banks of the Ganga, the Acharya was teaching his commentaries to his disciples till late in the noon. Finding the disciples exhausted, the Acharya closed the session and got up, when he was confronted by an old Brahmana with the question: &amp;ldquo;What are you teaching, Sir? And may I know who you are?&amp;rdquo; Thereupon the disciples intervened and said: &amp;ldquo;This is our teacher, the great Acharya Sankara, the master of all the Upani- shads, who has established the doctrine of Non-dualism through his commentaries on Särīraka-sutras (Brahma-sutras).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>08 </title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/08_CONTROVERSY_WITH_MANDANA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/08_CONTROVERSY_WITH_MANDANA/</guid>
      <description>Towards Mahishmati to meet Mandana (1-13) Bhagavan Sankara now left Prayaga, and travelling through the skies, reached the splendid city of Mahishmati which had gained great reputation as the residence of Mandana. Admi- ring the beauty and splendour of the numerous buildings of the city, he descended from the skies even like the sun at the close of the day, in a lovely wooded park of that place. There his physical exhaustion was assuaged by a gentle breeze coming through palm groves, carrying the cool water particles from the extensive sheets of lotus-flowers that covered its lakes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>09 ESTABLISHING THE CLAIM TO BE THE MASTER OF ALL LEARNING</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/09_ESTABLISHING_THE_CLAIM_TO_BE_THE_MASTER_OF_ALL_LEARNING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/09_ESTABLISHING_THE_CLAIM_TO_BE_THE_MASTER_OF_ALL_LEARNING/</guid>
      <description>The Correct Interpretation of Jaimini
(1-3) Though the words of the great Sannyasin, expounding the words of the Veda in such a clear and cogent way, put an end to Mandana&amp;rsquo;s desire for controversy, he still had one doubt uncleared owing to his fanatical devotion to the path of Vedic rituals. He said: &amp;ldquo;O great Sannyasin! Defeat in debate is some- thing new for me. Still it does not depress me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 ACQUIREMENT OF KNOWLEDGE OF SEX-LOVE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/10_ACQUIREMENT_OF_KNOWLEDGE_OF_SEX-LOVE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/10_ACQUIREMENT_OF_KNOWLEDGE_OF_SEX-LOVE/</guid>
      <description>(1-10) Next various propitiatory and auspicious rites were performed by priests for the king&amp;rsquo;s welfare. Then accompanied by his friends and the ministers, the king went in procession on an elephant&amp;rsquo;s back to his city. After pacifying his sorrow-stricken subjects, the king, along with his ministers, ruled the kingdom like Indra over the heavens, receiving the tribute and respect of all feudatory rulers. While the great Sankara began to rule the kingdom through the body of Amaruka, his astute ministers began to feel some doubts about the identity of their master and spoke thus among themselves: &amp;ldquo;It is by the rare good fortune of the people of this land that the king has come back to life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 ENCOUNTER WITH THE FIERCE BHAIRAVA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/11_ENCOUNTER_WITH_THE_FIERCE_BHAIRAVA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/11_ENCOUNTER_WITH_THE_FIERCE_BHAIRAVA/</guid>
      <description>The Kapalika&amp;rsquo;s plea for the Acharya&amp;rsquo;s Head
(1-28) One day Sankara, the conqueror of all the passions and the resort of even rishis who have conquered their lower self, was resting at a solitary spot after he had delivered his discourses on the Bhashya. A fierce and cruel-hearted Kapalika now appro- ached him with evil intentions in the guise of an ascetic, even as Ravana did in times of old. Delighted with the thought that his long awaited opportunity had now dawned, he approached the Acharya and curtly told him what he wanted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 THE COMING OF SOME DISCIPLES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/12_THE_COMING_OF_SOME_DISCIPLES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/12_THE_COMING_OF_SOME_DISCIPLES/</guid>
      <description>The Acharya at Gokarna
(1-5) Once, while the Acharya was travelling with his disciples from one pilgrimage to another, the party arrived at the holy spot of Gokarna on the sea-shore. The Acharya worshipped there at the shrine of Siva, who is the divine director of this stage of the world, who is adored by Brahma and all the gods, and who has His consort Parvati on the left side of His body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13 PREACHING OF BRAHMA VIDYA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/13_PREACHING_OF_BRAHMA_VIDYA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/13_PREACHING_OF_BRAHMA_VIDYA/</guid>
      <description>Writing of an Exegesis on Sutra-bhashya
(1-21) One day Sureswara, desirous of writing some exegesis on his Master&amp;rsquo;s great commentary on the Säriraka-bhāshya, approached him and said: &amp;ldquo;O great teacher! Please tell me how I could help you in your mission. To live in the service of his teacher is the only desirable form of life for a disciple.&amp;rdquo; Glad at the disciple&amp;rsquo;s request, Sankara said to him: &amp;ldquo;You may write for my commentary a vārtikam (an exegesis giving a critical exposi- tion).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14 THE PILGRIMAGE OF PADMAPADA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/14_THE_PILGRIMAGE_OF_PADMAPADA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/14_THE_PILGRIMAGE_OF_PADMAPADA/</guid>
      <description>The Rationale of Pilgrimage
(1-19) Once Padmapada approached the Acharya and sought permission to go on a pilgrimage to holy places. The Acharya thereupon said to him, &amp;ldquo;The proximity of the Guru is the real place of pilgrimage. The washings of his feet are the holy waters. The attainment of the Atman through the Guru&amp;rsquo;s instruction is the real experience of the Holy Presence which men seek indirectly through the adoration of holy images installed in temples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15 TRIUMPHANT TOUR OF THE LAND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/15_TRIUMPHANT_TOUR_OF_THE_LAND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/15_TRIUMPHANT_TOUR_OF_THE_LAND/</guid>
      <description>Confrontation with Kapalikas in Karnataka
(1-23) Now Acharya Sankara, along with the king Sudhanya and a large number of disciples, started on a Dig-vijaya-a mis- sionary tour for the propagation of the Advaita doctrine by con- troverting all philosophies opposed to it. He first travelled towards the Setu. On his way, he came across a sect whose followers were externally Saivas, but drank liquor in their worship like the Saktas. He entered into a very heated debate with these Brahmanas of Sakta persuasion, silenced them in argument for the good of the world, and made them accept the right code of rituals that he formulated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 ACCESSION TO SHARADAPITHA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/16_ACCESSION_TO_SHARADAPITHA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/paramparA/shankara-digvijayaH/mAdhavIyaH/en_tapasyAnanda/16_ACCESSION_TO_SHARADAPITHA/</guid>
      <description>Navagupta&amp;rsquo;s Black Magic
(1-8) Navagupta, the master of black magic, was, as stated before, planning, ever since his defeat at the hands of Sankara, to bring about his death by black magic. By Abhichara (a form of black magic) this evil one produced in the body of the Acharya a rectal fistula of an incurable nature. The disciple Totaka always nursed his teacher and, washed and cleansed his cloth stained with blood and faecal matter that flowed through the fistula, which yielded to no treatment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
