<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१ on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of this Vedānta-mīmāṁsā about to be explained by us the first Sūtra is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Then therefore the enquiry into Brahman.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;rsquo;then&amp;rsquo; is here to be taken as denoting immediate consecution; not as indicating the introduction of a new subject to be entered upon; for the enquiry into Brahman (more literally, the desire of knowing Brahman) is not of that nature &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Nor has the word &amp;rsquo;then&amp;rsquo; the sense&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Brahman is that) from which the origin, &amp;amp;c. (i.e. the origin, subsistence, and dissolution) of this (world proceed).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The term, &amp;amp;c. implies subsistence and re-absorption. That the origin is mentioned first (of the three) depends on the declaration of Scripture as well as on the natural development of a substance. Scripture declares the order&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of succession of origin, subsistence, and dissolution in the passage, Taitt. Up. III, I, &amp;lsquo;From whence these beings are born,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. And with regard to the second reason stated, it is known that a substrate of qualities can subsist and be dissolved only after it has entered, through origination, on the state of existence. The words &amp;lsquo;of this&amp;rsquo; denote that substrate of qualities which is presented to us by perception and the other means of right knowledge; the genitive case indicates it to be connected with origin, &amp;amp;c. The words &amp;lsquo;from which&amp;rsquo; denote the cause. The full sense of the Sūtra therefore is: That omniscient omnipotent cause from which proceed the origin, subsistence, and dissolution of this world&amp;ndash;which world is differentiated by names and forms, contains many agents and enjoyers, is the abode of the fruits of actions, these fruits having their definite places, times, and causes &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the nature of whose arrangement cannot even be conceived by the mind,&amp;ndash;that cause, we say, is Brahman. Since the other forms of existence (such as increase, decline, &amp;amp;c.) are included in origination, subsistence, and dissolution, only the three latter are referred to in the Sūtra. As the six stages of existence enumerated by Yāska &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are possible only during the period of the world&amp;rsquo;s subsistence, it might&amp;ndash;were they referred to in the Sūtra&amp;ndash;be suspected that what is meant are not the origin, subsistence, and dissolution (of the world) as dependent on the first cause. To preclude this suspicion the Sūtra is to be taken as referring, in addition to the world&amp;rsquo;s origination from Brahman, only to its subsistence in Brahman, and final dissolution into Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The omniscience of Brahman follows) from its being the source of Scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Brahman is the source, i.e. the cause of the great body of Scripture, consisting of the R̥g-veda and other branches, which is supported by various disciplines (such as grammar, nyāya, purāṇa, &amp;amp;c.); which lamp-like illuminates all things; which is itself all-knowing as it were. For the origin of a body of Scripture possessing the quality of omniscience cannot be sought elsewhere but in omniscience itself. It is generally understood that the man from whom some special body of doctrine referring to one province of knowledge only originates, as, for instance, grammar from Pāṇini possesses a more extensive knowledge than his work, comprehensive though it be; what idea, then, shall we have to form of the supreme omniscience and omnipotence of that great Being, which in sport as it were, easily as a man sends forth his breath, has produced the vast mass of holy texts known as the R̥g-veda, &amp;amp;c., the mine of all knowledge, consisting of manifold branches, the cause of the distinction of all the different classes and conditions of gods, animals, and men! See what Scripture says about him, &amp;lsquo;The R̥g-veda, &amp;amp;c., have been breathed forth from that great Being&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 4, 10).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;But that (Brahman is to be known from Scripture), because it is connected (with the Vedānta-texts) as their purport.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;but&amp;rsquo; is meant to rebut the pūrva-paksha (the primā facie view as urged above). That all-knowing, all-powerful Brahman, which is the cause of the origin, subsistence, and dissolution of the world, is known from the Vedānta-part of Scripture. How? Because in all the Vedānta-texts the sentences construe in so far as they have for their purport, as they intimate that matter (viz. Brahman). Compare, for instance, &amp;lsquo;Being only this was in the beginning, one, without a second&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, 1); &amp;lsquo;In the beginning all this was Self, one only&amp;rsquo; (Ait. Ār. II, 4, 1, 1); &amp;lsquo;This is the Brahman without cause and without effect, without anything inside or outside; this Self is Brahman perceiving everything&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. II, 5, 19); &amp;lsquo;That immortal Brahman is before&amp;rsquo; (Mu. Up. II, 2, 11); and similar passages. If the words contained in these passages have once been determined to refer to Brahman, and their purport is understood thereby, it would be improper to assume them to have a different sense; for that would involve the fault of abandoning the direct statements of the text in favour of mere assumptions. Nor can we conclude the purport of these passages to be the intimation of the nature of agents, divinities, &amp;amp;c. (connected with acts of religious duty); for there are certain scriptural passages which preclude all actions, actors, and fruits, as, for instance, Br̥. Up. II, 4, 13, &amp;lsquo;Then by what should he see whom?&amp;rsquo; (which passage intimates that there is neither an agent, nor an object of action, nor an instrument.) Nor again can Brahman, though it is of the nature of an accomplished thing, be the object of perception and the other means of&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of seeing (i. e. thinking being attributed in the Upanishads to the cause of the world; the pradhāna) is not (to be identified with the cause indicated by the Upanishads; for) it is not founded on Scripture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to find room in the Vedānta-texts for the non-intelligent pradhāna, the fiction of the Sānkhyas; because it is not founded on Scripture. How so? Because the quality of seeing, i. e. thinking, is in Scripture ascribed to the cause. For the passage, Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, (which begins: &amp;lsquo;Being only, my dear, this was in the beginning, one only, without a second,&amp;rsquo; and goes on, &amp;lsquo;It thought (saw),&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it is said that (the word &amp;lsquo;seeing&amp;rsquo;) has a figurative meaning, we deny that, on account of the word Self (being applied to the cause of the world).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Your assertion that the term &amp;lsquo;Being&amp;rsquo; denotes the non-intelligent pradhāna, and that thought is ascribed to it in a figurative sense only, as it is to fire and water, is untenable. Why so? On account of the term &amp;lsquo;Self.&amp;rsquo; For the passage Cḥ. Up. VI, 2, which begins &amp;lsquo;Being only, my dear, this was in the beginning,&amp;rsquo; after having related the creation of fire, water, and earth (&amp;lsquo;it thought,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.; &amp;lsquo;it sent forth fire,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.), goes on&amp;ndash;denoting the thinking principle of which the whole chapter treats, and likewise fire, water, and earth, by the term&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;divinities&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;as follows, &amp;lsquo;That divinity thought: Let me now enter those three divinities with this living Self (jīva. ātman) and evolve names and forms.&amp;rsquo; If we assumed that in this passage the non-intelligent pradhāna is figuratively spoken of as thinking, we should also have to assume that the same pradhāna&amp;ndash;as once constituting the subject-matter of the chapter&amp;ndash;is referred to by the term &amp;rsquo;that divinity.&amp;rsquo; But in that case the divinity would not speak of the jīva as &amp;lsquo;Self.&amp;rsquo; For by the term &amp;lsquo;Jiva&amp;rsquo; we must understand, according to the received meaning and the etymology of the word, the intelligent (principle) which rules over the body and sustains the vital airs. How could such a principle be the Self of the non-intelligent pradhāna? By &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo; we understand (a being&amp;rsquo;s) own nature, and it is clear that the intelligent Jiva cannot constitute the nature of the non-intelligent pradhāna. If, on the other hand, we refer the whole chapter to the intelligent Brahman, to&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The pradhāna cannot be designated by the term &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo;) because release is taught of him who takes his stand on that (the Sat).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The non-intelligent pradhāna cannot be the object of the term &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo; because in the passage Cḥ. Up. VI, 2 ff., where the subtle Sat which is under discussion is at first referred to in the sentence, &amp;lsquo;That is the Self,&amp;rsquo; and where the subsequent clause, &amp;lsquo;That art thou, O Śvetaketu,&amp;rsquo; declares the intelligent Śvetaketu to have his abode in the Self, a passage subsequent to the two quoted (viz. &amp;lsquo;a man who has a teacher obtains true knowledge; for him there is only delay as long as he is not delivered, then he will be perfect&amp;rsquo;) declares final release. For if the non-intelligent pradhāna were denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;Sat&amp;rsquo; and did comprehend&amp;ndash;by means of the phrase &amp;lsquo;That art thou&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;persons desirous of final release who as such are intelligent, the meaning could only be &amp;lsquo;Thou art non-intelligent;&amp;rsquo; so that Scripture would virtually make contradictory statements to the disadvantage of man, and would thus cease to be a means of right knowledge. But to assume that the faultless śāstra is not a means of right knowledge, would be contrary to reason. And if the śāstra, considered as a means of right knowledge, should point out to a man desirous of release, but ignorant of the way to it, a non-intelligent Self as the real Self, he would&amp;ndash;comparable to the blind man who had caught hold of the ox&amp;rsquo;s tail &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;ndash;cling to the view of that being the Self,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And (the pradhāna cannot be denoted by the word &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo;) because there is no statement of its having to be set aside.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If the pradhāna which is the Not-Self were denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;Being&amp;rsquo; (Sat), and if the passage &amp;lsquo;That is the Self, that art thou, O Śvetaketu,&amp;rsquo; referred to the pradhāna; the teacher whose wish it is to impart instruction about the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;true Brahman would subsequently declare that the pradhāna is to be set aside (and the true Brahman to be considered); for otherwise his pupil, having received the instruction about the pradhāna, might take his stand on the latter, looking upon it as the Non-Self. In ordinary life a man who wishes to point out to a friend the (small) star Arundhatī at first directs his attention to a big neighbouring star, saying &amp;rsquo;that is Arundhatī,&amp;rsquo; although it is really not so; and thereupon he withdraws his first statement and points out the real Arundhatī. Analogously the teacher (if he intended to make his pupil understand the Self through the Non-Self) would in the end definitely state that the Self is not of the nature of the pradhāna. But no such statement is made; for the sixth Prapāṭḥaka arrives at a conclusion based on the view that the Self is nothing but that which is (the Sat).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of (the individual Soul) going to the Self (the Self cannot be the pradhāna).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With reference to the cause denoted by the word &amp;lsquo;Sat,&amp;rsquo; Scripture says, &amp;lsquo;When a man sleeps here, then, my dear, he becomes united with the Sat, he is gone to his own (Self). Therefore they say of him, &amp;ldquo;he sleeps&amp;rdquo; (svapiti), because he is gone to his own (svam apīta).&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 1.) This passage explains the well-known verb &amp;rsquo;to sleep,&amp;rsquo; with reference to the soul. The word, &amp;lsquo;his own,&amp;rsquo; denotes the Self which had before been denoted by the word Sat; to the Self he (the individual soul) goes, i.e. into it it is resolved, according to the acknowledged sense of api-i, which means &amp;rsquo;to be resolved into.&amp;rsquo; The individual soul (jīva) is called awake as long as being connected with the various external objects by means of the modifications of the mind&amp;ndash;which thus constitute limiting adjuncts of the soul&amp;ndash;it apprehends those external objects, and identifies itself with the gross body, which is one of those external objects &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. When, modified by the impressions which the external objects have left, it sees dreams, it is denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;mind &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rsquo; When, on the cessation of the two limiting adjuncts (i.e. the subtle and the gross bodies), and the consequent absence of the modifications due to the adjuncts, it is, in the state of deep sleep, merged in the Self as it were, then it is said to be asleep (resolved into the Self). A similar etymology of the word &amp;lsquo;hr̥daya&amp;rsquo; is given by śruti, &amp;lsquo;That Self abides in the heart. And this is the etymological explanation: he is in the heart (hr̥di ayam).&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VIII, 3, 3.) The words aśanāya and udanyā are similarly etymologised: &amp;lsquo;water is carrying away what has been eaten by him;&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;fire carries away what has been drunk by him&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 3; 5). Thus the passage quoted above explains the resolution (of the soul) into the Self, denoted by the term &amp;lsquo;Sat,&amp;rsquo; by means of the etymology of the word &amp;lsquo;sleep.&amp;rsquo; But the intelligent&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On account of the uniformity of view (of the Vedānta-texts, Brahman is to be considered the cause).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If, as in the argumentations of the logicians, so in the Vedānta-texts also, there were set forth different views concerning the nature of the cause, some of them favouring the theory of an intelligent Brahman being the cause of the world, others inclining towards the pradhāna doctrine, and others again tending in a different direction; then it might perhaps be possible to interpret such passages as those, which speak of the cause of the world as thinking, in such a manner as to make them fall in with the pradhāna theory. But the stated condition is absent since all the Vedānta-texts uniformly teach that the cause of the world is the intelligent Brahman. Compare, for instance, &amp;lsquo;As from a burning fire sparks proceed in all directions, thus from that Self the prāṇas proceed each towards its place; from the prāṇas the gods, from the gods the worlds&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. III, 3). And &amp;lsquo;from that Self sprang ether&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 1). And &amp;lsquo;all this springs from the Self&amp;rsquo; (Cḥ. Up. VII, 26, 1). And &amp;rsquo;this prāṇa is born from the Self&amp;rsquo; (Pr. Up. III, 3); all which passages declare the Self to be the cause. That the word &amp;lsquo;Self&amp;rsquo; denotes an intelligent being, we have already shown.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because it is directly stated in Scripture (therefore the all-knowing Brahman is the cause of the world).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the all-knowing Lord is the cause of the world, is also declared in a text directly referring to him (viz. the all-knowing one), viz. in the following passage of the mantropanishad of the Śvetāśvataras (VI, 9) where the word &amp;lsquo;he&amp;rsquo; refers to the previously mentioned all-knowing Lord, &amp;lsquo;He is the cause, the lord of the lords of the organs, and there is of him neither parent nor lord.&amp;rsquo; It is therefore finally settled that the all-knowing Brahman is the general cause, not the non-intelligent pradhāna or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Self) consisting of bliss (is the highest Self) on account of the repetition (of the word &amp;lsquo;bliss,&amp;rsquo; as denoting the highest Self).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Taittirīya-upanishad (II, 1-5), after having enumerated the Self consisting of food, the Self consisting of the vital airs, the Self consisting of mind, and the Self consisting of understanding, says, &amp;lsquo;Different from this which consists of understanding is the other inner Self which consists of bliss.&amp;rsquo; Here the doubt arises whether the phrase, &amp;rsquo;that which consists of bliss,&amp;rsquo; denotes the highest Brahman of which it had been said previously, that &amp;lsquo;It is true Being, Knowledge, without end,&amp;rsquo; or something different from Brahman, just as the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If (it be objected that the term ānandamaya, consisting of bliss, can) not (denote the highest Self) on account of its being a word denoting a modification&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(or product); (we declare the objection to be) not (valid) on account of abundance, (the idea of which may be expressed by the affix maya.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the pūrvapakshin raises the objection that the word ānandamaya (consisting of bliss) cannot denote the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And because he is declared to be the cause of it, (i.e. of bliss; therefore maya is to be taken as denoting abundance.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maya must be understood to denote abundance, for that reason also that Scripture declares Brahman to be the cause of bliss, &amp;lsquo;For he alone causes bliss&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 7). For he who causes bliss must himself abound in bliss; just as we infer in ordinary life, that a man who enriches others must himself possess abundant wealth. As, therefore, maya may be taken to mean &amp;lsquo;abundant,&amp;rsquo; the Self consisting of bliss is the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moreover (the ānandamaya is Brahman because)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the same (Brahman) which had been referred to in the mantra is sung, (i.e. proclaimed in the Brāhmaṇa passage as the ānandamaya.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Self, consisting of joy, is the highest Brahman for the following reason also &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. On the introductory words &amp;lsquo;he who knows Brahman attains the highest&amp;rsquo; (Taitt. Up. II, 1), there follows a mantra proclaiming that Brahman, which forms the general topic of the chapter, possesses the qualities of true existence, intelligence, infinity; after that it is said that from Brahman there sprang at first the ether and then all other moving and non-moving things, and that, entering into the beings which it had emitted, Brahman stays in the recess, inmost of all; thereupon, for its better comprehension, the series of the different Selfs (&amp;lsquo;different from this is the inner Self,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c.) are enumerated, and then finally the same Brahman which the mantra had proclaimed, is again proclaimed in the passage under discussion, &amp;lsquo;different from this is the other inner Self, which consists of bliss.&amp;rsquo; To assume that a mantra and the Brāhmaṇa passage belonging to it have the same sense is only proper, on account of the absence of contradiction (which results therefrom); for otherwise we should be driven to the unwelcome inference that the text drops the topic once started, and turns to an altogether new subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Self consisting of bliss is the highest Self,) not the other (i.e. the individual Soul), on account of the impossibility (of the latter assumption).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And for the following reason also the Self consisting of bliss is the highest Self only, not the other, i.e. the one which is other than the Lord, i.e. the transmigrating individual soul. The personal soul cannot be denoted by the term &amp;rsquo;the one consisting of bliss.&amp;rsquo; Why? On account of the impossibility. For Scripture says, with reference to the Self consisting of bliss, &amp;lsquo;He wished, may I be many, may I grow forth. He brooded over himself. After he had thus brooded, he sent forth whatever there is.&amp;rsquo; Here, the desire arising before the origination of a body, &amp;amp;c., the non-separation of the effects created from the creator, and the creation of all effects whatever, cannot possibly belong to any Self different from the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of the declaration of the difference (of the two, the ānandamaya cannot be the transmigrating soul).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Self consisting of bliss cannot be identical with the transmigrating soul, for that reason also that in the section treating of the Self of bliss, the individual soul and the Self of bliss are distinctly represented as different; Taitt. Up. II, 7, &amp;lsquo;It (i.e. the Self consisting of bliss) is a flavour; for only after perceiving a flavour can this (soul) perceive bliss.&amp;rsquo; For he who perceives cannot be that which is perceived.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And on account of desire (being mentioned as belonging to the ānandamaya) no regard is to be had to what is inferred, (i.e. to the pradhāna inferred by the Sānkhyas.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since in the passage &amp;lsquo;he desired, may I be many, may I grow forth,&amp;rsquo; which occurs in the chapter treating of the ānandamaya (Taitt. Up. II, 6), the quality of feeling desire is mentioned, that which is inferred, i.e. the non-intelligent pradhāna assumed by the Sānkhyas, cannot be regarded as being the Self consisting of bliss and the cause of the world. Although the opinion that the pradhāna is the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And, moreover, it (i.e. Scripture) teaches the joining of this (i.e. the individual soul) with that, (i.e. the Self consisting of bliss), on that (being fully known).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And for the following reason also the term, &amp;rsquo;the Self consisting of bliss,&amp;rsquo; cannot denote either the pradhāna or the individual soul. Scripture teaches that the individual soul when it has reached knowledge is joined, i.e. identified, with the Self of bliss under discussion, i.e. obtains final release. Compare the following passage (Taitt. Up. II, 7), &amp;lsquo;When he finds freedom from fear, and rest in that which is invisible, incorporeal, undefined, unsupported, then he has obtained the fearless. For if he makes but the smallest distinction in it there is fear for him.&amp;rsquo; That means, if he sees in that Self consisting of bliss even a small difference in the form of non-identity, then he finds no release from the fear of transmigratory existence. But when he, by means of the cognition of absolute identity, finds absolute rest in the Self consisting of bliss, then he is freed from the fear of transmigratory existence. But this (finding absolute rest) is possible only when we understand by the Self consisting of bliss, the highest Self, and not either the pradhāna or the individual soul. Hence it is proved that the Self consisting of bliss is the highest Self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The one within (the sun and the eye) (is the highest Lord), on account of his qualities being declared &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following passage is found in Scripture (Cḥ. Up. I, 6, 6 ff.), &amp;ldquo;Now that person bright as gold who is seen within&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the sun, with beard bright as gold and hair bright as gold, bright as gold altogether to the very tips of his nails, whose eyes are like blue lotus; his name is Ut, for he has risen (udita) above all evil. He also who knows this rises above all evil. So much with reference to the devas.&amp;rsquo; And further on, with reference to the body, &amp;lsquo;Now the person who is seen in the eye,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. Here the following doubt presents itself. Do these passages point out, as the object of devotion directed on the sphere of the sun and the eye, merely some special individual soul, which, by means of a large measure of knowledge and pious works, has raised itself to a position of eminence; or do they refer to the eternally perfect highest Lord?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And there is another one (i.e. the Lord who is different from the individual souls animating the sun, &amp;amp;c.), on account of the declaration of distinction.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is, moreover, one distinct from the individual souls which animate the sun and other bodies, viz. the Lord who rules within; whose distinction (from all individual souls) is proclaimed in the following scriptural passage, &amp;lsquo;He who dwells in the sun and within the sun, whom the sun does not know, whose body the sun is, and who rules the sun within; he is thy Self, the ruler within, the immortal&amp;rsquo; (Br̥. Up. III, 7, 9). Here the expression, &amp;lsquo;He within the sun whom the sun does not know,&amp;rsquo; clearly indicates that the Ruler within is distinct from that cognising individual soul whose body is the sun. With that Ruler within we have to identify the person within the sun, according to the tenet of the sameness of purport of all Vedānta-texts. It thus remains a settled conclusion that the passage under discussion conveys instruction about the highest Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The ākāśa, i.e. ether (is Brahman) on account of characteristic marks (of the latter being mentioned).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Cḥāndogya (I, 9) the following passage is met with, &amp;lsquo;What is the origin of this world?&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Ether,&amp;rsquo; he replied. &amp;lsquo;For all these beings take their rise from the ether only, and return into the ether. Ether is greater than these, ether is their rest.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here the following doubt arises. Does the word &amp;rsquo;ether&amp;rsquo; denote the highest Brahman or the elemental ether?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For the same reason breath (is Brahman).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Concerning the udgītha it is said (Cḥ. Up. I, 10, 9), &amp;lsquo;Prastotr̥, that deity which belongs to the prastāva, &amp;amp;c.,&amp;rsquo; and, further on (I,11,4; 5), &amp;lsquo;Which then is that deity? He said: Breath. For all these beings merge into breath alone, and from breath they arise. This is the deity belonging to the prastāva.&amp;rsquo; With reference to this passage doubt and decision are to be considered as analogous to those stated under the preceding Sūtra. For while in some passages&amp;ndash;as, for instance, &amp;lsquo;For indeed, my son, mind is fastened to prāṇa,&amp;rsquo; Cḥ. Up. VI, 8, 2; and, &amp;rsquo;the prāṇa of prāṇa,&amp;rsquo; Br̥. Up. IV, 4, 18&amp;ndash;the word &amp;lsquo;breath&amp;rsquo; is seen to denote Brahman, its use&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The &amp;rsquo;light&amp;rsquo; (is Brahman), on account of the mention of feet (in a passage which is connected with the passage about the light).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scripture says (Cḥ. Up. III, 13, 7), &amp;lsquo;Now that light which shines above this heaven, higher than all, higher than everything,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in the highest worlds beyond which there are no other worlds that is the same light which is within man.&amp;rsquo; Here the doubt presents itself whether the word &amp;rsquo;light&amp;rsquo; denotes the light of the sun and the like, or the highest Self. Under the preceding Sūtras we had shown that some words which ordinarily have different meanings yet in certain passages denote Brahman, since characteristic marks of the latter are mentioned. Here the question has to be discussed whether, in connexion with the passage quoted, characteristic marks of Brahman are mentioned or not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be objected that(Brahman is) not (denoted) on account of the metre being denoted; (we reply) not so, because thus (i.e. by means of the metre) the direction of the mind (on Brahman) is declared; for thus it is seen (in other passages also).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now address ourselves to the refutation of the assertion (made in the pūrvapaksha of the preceding Sūtra) that in the previous passage also Brahman is not referred to, because in the sentence, &amp;lsquo;Gāyatrī is everything whatsoever here exists,&amp;rsquo; the metre called Gāyatrī is spoken of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;And thus also (we must conclude, viz. that Brahman is the subject of the previous passage), because (thus only) the declaration as to the beings, &amp;amp;c. being the feet is possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That the previous passage has Brahman for its topic, we must assume for that reason also that the text designates the beings and so on as the feet of Gāyatrī. For the text at first speaks of the beings, the earth, the body, and the heart &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and then goes on &amp;rsquo;that Gāyatrī has four feet and is sixfold.&amp;rsquo; For of the mere metre, without any reference to Brahman, it would be impossible to say that the beings and so on are its feet. Moreover, if Brahman were not meant, there would be no room for the verse, &amp;lsquo;Such is the greatness,&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;c. For that verse clearly describes Brahman in its own nature; otherwise it would be impossible to represent the Gāyatrī as the Self of everything as is done in the words, &amp;lsquo;One foot of it are all the beings; three feet of it are what is immortal in heaven.&amp;rsquo; The purusha-sūkta also (R̥k&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The objection that (the Brahman of the former passage cannot be recognised in the latter) on account of the difference of designation, is not valid because in either (designation) there is nothing contrary (to the recognition).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The objection that in the former passage (&amp;rsquo;three feet of it are what is immortal in heaven&amp;rsquo;), heaven is designated as the abode, while in the latter passage (&amp;rsquo;that light which shines above this heaven&amp;rsquo;), heaven is designated as the boundary, and that, on account of this difference of designation, the subject-matter of the former passage cannot be recognised in the latter, must likewise be refuted. This we do by remarking that in either designation nothing is contrary to the recognition. Just as in ordinary language a falcon, although in contact with the top of a tree, is not only said to be on the tree but also above the tree, so Brahman also, although being in heaven, is here referred to as being beyond heaven as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prāṇa (breath) is Brahman, that being understood from a connected consideration (of the passages referring to prāṇa).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the Kaushītaki-brāhmaṇa-upanishad there is recorded a legend of Indra and Pratardana which begins with the words, &amp;lsquo;Pratardana, forsooth, the son of Divodāsa came by means of fighting and strength to the beloved abode of Indra&amp;rsquo; (Kau. Up. III, 1). In this legend we read: &amp;lsquo;He said: I am prāṇa, the intelligent Self (prajñātman), meditate on me as Life, as Immortality&amp;rsquo; (III, 2). And later on (III, 3), &amp;lsquo;Prāṇa alone, the intelligent Self, having laid hold of this body, makes it rise up.&amp;rsquo; Then, again (III, 8), &amp;lsquo;Let no man try to find out what speech is, let him know the speaker.&amp;rsquo; And in the end (III, 8), &amp;lsquo;That breath indeed is the intelligent Self, bliss, imperishable, immortal.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said that (Brahman is) not (denoted) on account of the speaker denoting himself; (we reply that this objection is not valid) because there is in that (chapter) a multitude of references to the interior Self.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An objection is raised against the assertion that prāṇa denotes Brahman. The word prāṇa, it is said, does not denote the highest Brahman, because the speaker designates himself. The speaker, who is a certain powerful god called Indra, at first says, in order to reveal himself to Pratardana, &amp;lsquo;Know me only,&amp;rsquo; and later on, &amp;lsquo;I am prāṇa, the intelligent Self.&amp;rsquo; How, it is asked, can the prāṇa, which this latter passage, expressive of personality as it is, represents as the Self of the speaker, be Brahman to which, as we know from Scripture, the attribute of being a speaker cannot be ascribed; compare, for instance, Br̥. Up. III, 8, 8, &amp;lsquo;It is without speech, without mind.&amp;rsquo; Further on, also, the speaker, i.e. Indra, glorifies himself by enumerating a number of attributes, all of which depend on personal existence and can in no way belong to Brahman, &amp;lsquo;I slew the three-headed son of Tvash_tri_; I delivered the Arunmukhas, the devotees, to the wolves,&amp;rsquo; and so on. Indra may be called prāṇa on account of his strength. Scripture says, &amp;lsquo;Strength indeed is prāṇa,&amp;rsquo; and Indra is known as the god of strength; and of any deed of strength people say, &amp;lsquo;It is Indra&amp;rsquo;s work.&amp;rsquo; The personal Self of a deity may, moreover, be called an intelligent Self; for the gods, people say, possess unobstructed knowledge. It thus being a settled matter that some passages convey information about the personal Self&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The declaration (made by Indra about himself, viz. that he is one with Brahman) (is possible) through intuition vouched for by Scripture, as in the case of Vāmadeva.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The individual divine Self called Indra perceiving by means of r̥shi-like intuition &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;ndash;the existence of which is vouched for by Scripture&amp;ndash;its own Self to be identical with the supreme Self, instructs Pratardana (about the highest Self) by means of the words &amp;lsquo;Know me only.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 None</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/shankaraH/brahma-sUtrANi/thibaut/1/1/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If it be said (that Brahman is) not (meant), on account of characteristic marks of the individual soul and the chief vital air (being mentioned); we say no, on account of the threefoldness of devout meditation (which would result from your interpretation); on account of (the meaning advocated by us) being accepted (elsewhere); and on account of (characteristic marks of Brahman) being connected (with the passage under discussion).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although we admit, the pūrvapakshin resumes, that the chapter about the prāṇa does not furnish any instruction regarding some outward deity, since it contains a multitude of references to the interior Self; still we deny that it is concerned with Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
