<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;कुलकरणि-देवरावः on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/sachchidAnandendraH/kulakaraNi-devarAvaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;कुलकरणि-देवरावः on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/sachchidAnandendraH/kulakaraNi-devarAvaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Guidelines to shAnkara-vedAnta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/sachchidAnandendraH/kulakaraNi-devarAvaH/guidelines-to-shAnkara-vedAnta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/shAnkara-darshanam/tattvam/sachchidAnandendraH/kulakaraNi-devarAvaH/guidelines-to-shAnkara-vedAnta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;GUIDE-LINES TO SHANKARA-VEDANTA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;AUTHOR:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;BRAHMAJNA KAVI, VEDANTA CHATURA  SHRI DEVARAO KULKARNI&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ADHYATMA PRAKASHA KARYALAYA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;0&#34;&gt;0&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays it is very essential to know Acharya  Shaṅkara&amp;rsquo;s teachings in its true perspective according to his  Prasthānatraya Bhashyas, because Shaṅkara-Vedānta has been  misunderstood and misinterpreted by the sub-commentators  on Shri Shaṅkara&amp;rsquo;s Bhāṣyas. Accordingly the seekers are  confused and confounded by many distortions, misinterpretations and misguiding versions of Shaṅkara&amp;rsquo;s original  Bhashyas. To comprehend the fullest import of the teachings  of Shaṅkara, we have to take the traditional works of  Gaudapāda&amp;rsquo;s Kārikā on Mānḍukya Upanishad, Upadesha  Sāhasrī, an independent work of Shri Shaṅkara and Sureshvara&amp;rsquo;s Vārtikas on Taittiriya and Brhadaranyaka Bhashyas  of Shri Shaṅkara and his independent work called Naishkarmya Siddhi. All these contain the idea of pristine pure Vedānta in unequivocal voice. Teachings based on these works are not easily available to the aspirants of  Shaṅkara-Vedānta. To remove this scarcity, Shri Shri  Satchidānandendra Saraswati Swāmiji of Karnataka State,  has made a sustained effort to show the genuine teachings  through his writings. The first book is published in Kannada viz. &amp;ldquo;Shānkara Vedānta Sara.&amp;rdquo; In the introduction to this  book Swamiji has declared that &amp;ldquo;never before in any part  of the world a book of this type which contain subject wise classification of the sentences of the Bhashya and  traditional books referred to above has been published.&amp;rdquo;  In this direction he has published hundreds of books in  three languages viz. Kannada, Sanskrit and English.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
