<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on आगमे ब्राह्मे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>drAmiDAchArya ID</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/drAmiDAchArya_ID/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/drAmiDAchArya_ID/</guid>
      <description>reject his (KuppusvAmi shAstri) identification of dramidacharya with tirumazhisai for obvious reasons.
If it was so, we would be seeing yamuna, ramanuja, desika etc mentioning abt this identity somewhere - we see no such reference. no hagiography mentions abt such Sanskrit works either. Otoh, we hear how he avoided reciting any Vedic phrase in keeping with his varna dharma. And none of the reasons given by sastri are really strong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vishAl on bhAruchi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/vishAl_on_bhAruchi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/vishAl_on_bhAruchi/</guid>
      <description>Bharuchi and his Vedantic Views
Introduction Ramanujacharya (1017-1137 C.E.), in his Vedarthasamgraha [ref. 1, pg. 250-251], states: “This path which is shown in all the *srutis *whose meaning is very lucidly explained by the ancient commentaries composed by Bodhayana, Tanka, Dramida, Guhadeva, Kapardi, Bharuchi etc., and accepted by all those who are competent to judge, is only arrived at by *Bhakti *that has developed along the above lines.” From this passage, it appears that Ramanujacharya acknowledges these 6 teachers as ancient authorities whose views are acceptable to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vishiShTAdvaita and panentheism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/vishiShTAdvaita_panentheism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/vishiShTAdvaita_panentheism/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Among all the systems of vedAnta, it is vishiShTadvAita (vadakalai) that puts the most emphasis on trying to give a unified synthesis of the karma &amp;amp; j~nAna kANDa. Their panentheism+++(=God is greater than the universe and includes and interpenetrates it)+++ helps explain almost all the putatively conflicting views of scripture.
Due to this panentheistic realism, the advaitin-s viciously attack them with the charge that their system compromises the nirvikAratva and avyayatva of Brahman.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>आळ्वार-टिप्पन्यः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/AlvAra-TippanyaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/AgamaH_brAhmaH/articles/AlvAra-TippanyaH/</guid>
      <description>Structure Brahma-Meemamsa Shastra Consists of a Total of 4 Adhyaya-s (chapters) (This is further divided into two categories)
सिद्धद्विकम् Consists of 2 Chapters dealing with what is already &amp;lsquo;siddha&amp;rsquo; समन्वयाध्यायः Chapter proves that all the Upanishadic passages converge in accepting the Brahman as the Sole cause of the Universe अविरोधाध्यायः Chapter proves that there is no contradiction of other Vedic or allied texts in accepting the Brahman as the Sole cause of the Universe and this is also logically correct साध्यद्विकम् Consists of 2 chapters that deals with what has to be achieved hereafter साधनाध्यायः Chapter deals with all issues concerning the worship of the Supreme Lord to attain Moksha फलाध्यायः Chapter deals with all issues concerning the nature and other aspects of the &amp;lsquo;phala&amp;rsquo; - Moksha 2 स्मृति-पादः This Pada establishes that there is NO contradiction of the Smriti texts to the fact that the Supreme Brahman is both the material and efficient cause of the Universe!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
